[MUSIC]
More great music.
This time by Chopin.
What do I personally experience here?
What do I feel?
At the beginning a sense of soaring,
perhaps gliding above the cares of life.
Enjoying something very pleasurable.
And then, the bottom falls out.
Something dark and somber.
Chopin was actually thinking
of this as a funeral march.
[MUSIC]
I like to think of music or any art
as a collateral experience to life,
Yo-Yo Ma, the great cellist recently said,
art is life.
Well, I'd life to refine that just a bit,
by suggesting that art is something
close to life but not quite life.
It's another life,
the life of the imagination.
This second life, through art, enhances
our primary, our everyday existence.
It makes our journey through life
a richer, more enjoyable one.
Well, these are semi high
sounding ideas about art and
about life, but let's get to specifics.
What about music?
What is music?
Well my very pedestrian
definition of music would be,
the rational organization of sounds and
silences passing through time.
But the 19th century writer
Victor Hugo expressed it better.
Music is what feelings sound like.
In other words, it's a language.
It's a mode of expression,
of feelings and sensations.
What exactly does music do for us?
Well, music can relax us
after a difficult day.
Take away stress.
Music can excite us.
When you exercise, jog or
run do you listen to music?
Many people do.
Why?
Well, the music helps
us jump start the body.
We'll explore that soon.
Music can show us a vision
of a better world,
where everything is harmony and balance.
I feel that particularly when
listening to the music of Mozart.
Music can help keep us up to date.
Many youngsters listen to pop
music to learn what's going on,
what's current in popular culture.
Music can bring us all together.
We can bond,
show that we belong to a group,
reaffirm common values,
new values, older values.
We do this when we go to a rock
concert at Yankee Stadium,
just as when we go to hear Mozart or
Wagner at the Metropolitan Opera.
We are reaffirming values,
as we bond with the music.
Let's see how this works.
Here's the beginning of
a cantata by JS Bach.
Bach composed it for a German
church in the 18th century, the St.
Thomas Church, Leipzig,
which we'll see on the screen now.
As the listeners,
the congregation, gathers,
the chorus sings a hymn, the tune.
In Bach's day, the listeners and
chorus would have sung together,
sharing a common belief,
bonding with the music.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Now,
another kind of bonding through the music.
A concert of Swedish House Mafia in
San Francisco, where the congregation,
here the audience, sings the melody,
Don't You Worry Child.
>> [MUSIC]
>> As with the Bach example,
those singing in this video are saying,
I'm part of this community, I belong.
We have validity.
But in these contexts, it's the music
that brings us together and that's good.
It's very difficult to hate
someone who passionately loves
the same music that you do.