[MUSIC]
>> Most of the world listen to what
is generally called popular music,
music of the people, and
music that almost everybody likes.
Downloads of pop music outnumber those
of classical music about 30 to one.
But most of this course will be concerned
with listening to classical music.
What does that mean, classical music?
The term applies to any music, indeed,
any object, that's been around for
a long time, that's been passed on
from one generation to the next.
Likely there's a vocabulary of terms
to discuss that music or that artifact.
And finally, that music has certain
universally appreciated qualities.
Balance, proportion, that sort of thing.
We have classics in automobiles,
timepieces, paintings,
architecture, and, of course, music.
These classical objects are associated
today with so-called high end art.
For Western art music, the term classical
didn't appear until rather late,
the 19th century, again, in Germany, when
audiences began to demand that concert
programmers go back and replay older
music, the music of the late 18th century.
Mozart, Hayden and Beethoven.
Up to that point, when you went to
a concert you'd always hear new music.
Why would anyone want to go and
hear old music?
But now, in the 19th century,
concert goers start to look backward to
the now-called classics of Mozart and
Hayden and Beethoven.
How does popular music
differ from Classical music?
Well, here are five important ways,
said quickly.
Popular music often uses electric
instruments, electric guitars and
electric keyboards.
This is an electric instrument
[MUSIC]
made to sound like a keyed
stringed instrument.
But it is an electric instrument.
Classical music, on the other hand,
uses acoustic instruments,
instruments generating sound
from natural materials.
Pop music,
pop music also has a text, lyrics.
They tell you what the music is about.
Classical music, on the other hand,
is usually purely instrumental.
Usually, purely instrumental.
The music itself has to
tell you what it is about.
It has to sound out it's meaning.
Third, pop music tends
to have a strong beat.
In Classical music
the beat is more subdued.
Let's demonstrate now these first three
points by comparing a pop piece by
John Bon Jovi to a classical one by
Peter Tchaikovsky, a piano concerto.
Let's start with the Bon Jovi.
[MUSIC]
>> Is there anybody out there looking for
a party?
[MUSIC]
Shake your money maker, baby.
Smoke it if you got it.
>> So, we hear a lot of electronica here.
A very strong beat,
especially when the drum enters and
the text we've got it going on.
Well, we've got it going
on in classical music, too.
Here's a piece, indeed, a piano concerto
by the classical composer
Peter Tchaikovsky.
[MUSIC]
Well, that piece has a strong melody.
And, actually, also a rather clear beat,
a clearer beat than most Classical music.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
Maybe that's why we like it so much.
Because it does have
a pretty clear beat there.
Finally, two last points.
Popular music tends to be short and
sometimes repetitious.
The melody, the tune,
gets sung again and again.
Classical pieces are often longer.
They can be 20, 30 minutes, even more,
and they unfold more continually.
And fifth, and
finally, popular music is usually
performed without musical notation.
When you see Madonna at Yankee stadium
she's not singing from sheet music.
That'd be ridiculous.
Same thing with Kanye West, or
whoever might be your favorite pop artist.
There is no prescriptive written
document for pop performances, and many
different artists can interpret a song in
a particular way, do a cover of that song.
Classical music, on the other hand, tends
to be performed from a written score.
It's old, and it has to be done more or
less the same way each time.
And because there is a prescriptive
document stipulating precisely how it
should go, Classical music
tends to stay more on message.
Classical performances really don't
differ all that much from one performance
to the next.
Here on the screen,
you see an orchestral score of the famous
Rite of Spring of Igor Stravinsky,
now more than 100 years old.
Look at all those parts sounding together.
Indeed, it's complicated.
So you have to write out this musical
code so that everything fits together, so
that the performers play all
together when they're supposed to.