[MUSIC]
All right, let's have some fun.
But fun with a point.
As we said at the introduction to our
course, music works in mysterious ways.
Here's a riddle for you I've made up.
You can't see it.
You can't touch it or feel it.
You can't hold it in your hand.
But it can touch you, it can grab you.
It can move you to cry or
move you to dance with joy.
What is it?
Well, of course, music.
It's the poetry of the air.
Indeed, music can move us.
Music can manipulate us.
Advertisers and
marketing people know this.
They use music to persuade
us to buy something.
Here's a watch, a high-end watch.
It's a classic.
Now let's assume it's your
job to market this watch,
what kind of music are you going to
put with it to enhance it's appeal?
This kind?
[MUSIC]
Music of Mozart.
Or would you choose this kind.
[MUSIC]
I suspect it would be more effective.
You'd make more sales, if you choose
the Mozart rather than the Eminem.
Here, classical music reinforces
the message you want to create.
That this watch is a classic.
Classic object, timeless music.
Here's another interesting
thing about music.
Did you ever notice this?
Certain musics were better
at different times.
Music of the Baroque period, Bach and
Handel, they generally get played
in the morning, for reasons that
we'll go into later in our course.
There's a longstanding radio show on
PBS called Sunday Morning Baroque,
not late Friday night Baroque.
To see how music and mood and
motivation might work together,
let's suppose that you wish to seduce
the object of your amatory desire.
Your boyfriend, girlfriend, wife,
husband, partner, whatever.
You shop for the food and cook the meal.
Set the table.
Chosen the stemware, flowers, and
now it comes time to select the music
to make this all just perfect.
What kind of music would you
select to make the object of your
desire melt in your arms?
This?
[MUSIC]
Or would you choose this?
Now we're talking.
[MUSIC]
The first one,
the Bach just doesn't do the job.
I think we'd all agree to that.
The questions is, why not?
What is it about the Puccini that
makes us all want to melt or succumb?
And about the Bach that makes
our mind focus intensely,
perhaps think rather than meld?
[MUSIC]
The Bach's a great piece,
but it forces us to think.
And maybe analytical thinking is not
what is required, or wanted, here.
Is it possible that we are engaging
different sections of the brain
when we hear these two different pieces?
Bach is great music, but
is a different kind of music, and
it just doesn't work in this nocturnal,
amatory environment here.
Why not?
You tell me, what's the difference
in sound between these two pieces?