[MUSIC]
Turning now to nature.
There are in fact,
principals about the physics of music
that apply to all musical cultures.
Universal principals about the physics and
the acoustics of sound.
Let's take a look at just one of them,
the overtone series.
The overtone series does indeed involve,
as the Beach Boys say here,
good vibrations.
When any string on an instrument or
column of air in a tube
created by a wind instrument, produces a
sound, actually it's producing many sounds
through something of an auditory trick or
illusion.
We hear only the lowest sound in
part because it's the loudest.
But there are many other strings sounding,
as when I play this pitch.
[SOUND] Now we can represent this sound
by a diagram as you see on the screen.
Here we have one string sounding,
that's the black string.
But it's also being divided.
Halves of that string are sounding,
thirds of that string are sounding,
quarters, fifths, and so on.
And this applies to all
musical instruments.
Now, let's look at these
vibrations in a different way,
now with the lengths of
string standing vertically.
The first, and lowest, the one to
the left, we call the fundamental.
And all the others the overtones.
These overtones are small string sections
vibrating softly in the background.
So, we have the fundamental and
the overtones,
notice that the first overtone is
only half as long as the fundamental.
It reflects a two to one ratio,
which in music always produces
the sound that we call an octave.
A distance of eight letter
names on the scale.
We'll get into all that
in our third session.
Next comes a rate relationship,
a ratio of three to two.
Three units of strings
sounding against two units.
That produces what we call
the interval of a fifth.
So here's the octave.
[SOUND] Here's the interval [INAUDIBLE].
[SOUND] Then we come to four units
of string sounding against three,
which produces the interval of a fourth.
[SOUND] Spans four letter names.
Then five to four which gives us
interval of the third and so on.
[SOUND] Now we can take,
as you see on the screen here,
the fundamental and all these overtones
and apply them to a keyboard.
We hear the fundamental
note way down here.
[SOUND] But we also hear the first
overtone, second overtone,
third overtone, second,
and on up the scale we go.
These others,
[MUSIC]
We hear this and
these others are sounding very quiet.
These are the overtones at work.
The octave the fifth,
the fourth, and so on.
These are the primary units
of music around the world.
In Indonesian gamelan music, Chinese
music, every music, classical or pop.
We all have the same overtones and
therefore the basic notion of consonances.
We all have the same basic
notion of consonance.
Because when I play these
fundamental notes, this fundamental.
[MUSIC]
We get this very [SOUND] consonant sound.
Knowing this was important
to Richard Strauss.
He knew it and he used it.
He used the fundamental,
[MUSIC]
In a famous piece called,
Also sprach Zarathustra.
It's a big piece for
a western symphony orchestra.
The name is German and it sounds
very impressive, very intimidating.
But you've heard this piece
a thousand times on film and
in countless TV commercials.
In it, Strauss builds up the beginning of
the piece by using the primary overtones
[MUSIC]
What's this piece about this,
Also sprach Zarathustra.
Well, said very simply,
it's about the dawn of a superman,
a superhero who is equated with the rising
of the sun and the advent of the new age.
How does composer Strauss depict,
through music, the rising of the sun and
the super hero?
Well, let's give a listen.
[MUSIC]
Well, we start with low rumblings down
underneath to suggest primordial slime.
Then the sound of the trumpet.
Since time immemorial, the trumpet has
been associated with the military,
the army, with royalty,
with power, with the hero.
And this powerful sound is moving upwards.
It reaches a midway point and
then seems to fall back as if the super
hero is not quite equal to the task.
[MUSIC]
Then he tries again, but
is now able to reach,
[MUSIC]
And hold onto the sought after goal.
Eventually we move onto the end,
to the conclusion of
this opening section where we end
with this, a chord progression.
Remember, a syntax tells
us we've got to go home.
[MUSIC]
And that final chord there
is a very consonant chord,
consisting of pitches made
up the fundamental, and
the first four overtones
sounding loudly now all together.
But it sounds a lot better when played
by a full western symphony orchestra.
[MUSIC]
Now that's the power of classical music.