[MUSIC]
So, there's the great man.
The only authentic likeness of J.S. Bach.
He's holding a canon, a round,
because canons are difficult to create.
This shows not only that Bach was
a musician, but a learned musician.
Bach, the learned musician,
that's the title of a book
by my colleague at Harvard,
the great Bach scholar Kristof Wolf.
Our sessions on Bach and
Handel, of course,
will take us to the music of the late
Baroque in it's mature style.
These are long, complex pieces, done with
great ingenuity and great integrity.
Bach and Handel were both Germans and they
were both born in the same year, 1685.
And they were born even near one another,
in Germany as we'll see.
But let's start with the Bachs.
The many faces of the Bachs.
Indeed, they were a dynasty of musicians.
From the 16th through the 19th Century.
Ten generations of Bachs, here we see.
The most famous J.S.
Bach, top of, upper left hand corner
there, Johann Sebastian Bach.
And then his son, Carl Philip Emmanuel
Bach, and then another son of J.S.
Bach, Johann Christian Bach, and then
another one, Wilhelm Friedman Bach, and
then over to the far right, I have no
idea but we can be sure, it's a Bach.
If we look down at the bottom there,
bottom left,
we see a portrait of Bach's father,
Ambrosius Bach.
Bach's father was a town musician,
who often played in the town wind band,
he played an instrument called the shawm,
that we've talked about before, and
here's what a town band looked like, as we
can tell by glancing at this early 17th
century Dutch painting there on
the lower right hand side of this slide.
This first map shows where
Bach was born in 1685.
And rather soon, both his parents died.
Actually they were both
dead by the time he was 11.
And so
he became a ward of his older brother.
And then, he went off, J.S Bach
went off to prep school in effect.
Where he was a boy soprano in
the choir school at Lüneburg,
way up in northern Germany.
Singing paid his way through school.
Thereafter, when his voice broke,
at the age of 18.
He took a job at the church of Arnstadt,
a town then of about 3000 as an organist.
Here we see the pipes of
the original organ of Bach's day,
the framework and the pipes.
And here we see the console,
in a sense the central processing unitwith
keyboards of Bach's original organ.
This is his original instrument,
two manuals, two keyboards for
hands, and a keyboard for
the pedal, pedal keyboard.
And we see the stops,
those round knobs around
the circumference of the in, instrument.
They allow the organist to
sound various groups of pipe.
Sound one group which might
have the sound of a trumpet or
sound another group whichmight have
the sound of an oboe or even a shawm.
And if you pull them out all
together you get a very big sound.
Pulling out all of the stops.
So again, this processing core went
inside the original framework,
the original casement of Bach's organ,
and here we see it.
When he was a young man at Arnstadt,
Bach asked for a leave of absence.
He wanted to visit the city of Lubeck.
So off he goes, he walks the 225 miles one
way, didn't have any money, couldn't fly,
walked 225 miles up there to hear and
meet Dieterich Buxtehude in Lubeck.
And here's the church in
which Buxtehude worked,
Bach went up spent a couple of
weeks there and then returned.
Oddly enough Handel,
Handel made the same sort of trip.
Handel was in Hamburg and he went to Lu,
Lubeck about this same time.
So Bach walks to Lubeck and
then walks back.
And as you can see from this map here.
He returns somewhat late, tardy or
late into Orange dot and then moved on.
And eventually is settled in Weimar,
a slightly larger town
in the court's center.
The center of the Duchy of Weimar.
So here Bach in Weimar was an organist
in the duke's orchestra and
a string player,
violinist into Duke's orchestra as well.
And some of Bach's most famous early
organ works were composed here.
The somewhat frightening sounds of
the Toccata and Fugue in D minor.
Now, a toccata is a type
of keyboard music.
Literally, it means something touched.
So, when one touches an instrument.
But as a musical Toccata
is usually a free flowing
unpredictable composition of
some what improvisatory style.
So here's the music of
the Toccata in D minor.
[MUSIC]
You can see the organist is ornamenting
auction original scores no doubt.
[MUSIC]
And his big diminish chord.
Ornamental resolution to a major chord.
Well, this is a quick look at the life and
music of young Bach.
The beginning of the music
of his mature period, for
mature Bach,
we'll move on to the city of Kothen.