[MUSIC]
In the year 1770,
Bach was on the move yet again.
At stake here was the position of
Kapellmeister, director of music.
A prestigious job in 18th
century German society.
His position was open at Cöthen, so
Bach went over to Cöthen to apply for
the position of Kapellmeister
of the prince of Cöthen.
And Bach was awarded the position.
He got the job.
End of story.
But not exactly.
It turns out that in the 18th century, if
an employee was taken into the service of
a member of the nobility or a high ranking
clergyman he belonged to that lord.
He just couldn't quit.
And the same thing was true later for
Haydn and for Mozart.
In the 18th century, there's no such thing
as we Americans would call free agency,
or he's a free agent.
You were, in the 18th century,
an employee for life,
unless your employer
agreed to release you.
And Bach hadn't played by
the rules of the game.
And when he returned from Cöthen to
Weimar to pick up his possessions and
his family of five, the Duke of
Weimar had Bach thrown in jail.
Bach in jail?
[LAUGH] Yes, in the county jail,
for a month,
from early November to early December,
1770.
At which point, Bach was finally released,
both from jail and
his position in Weimar,
and off he went to Cöthen.
So here's Weimar and here we are moving
up to the northeast where we see Cöthen.
And here's the way Cöthen
looked in the mid 17th century.
Now Bach didn't live in the court
buildings that we see in the center here.
But he lived to the west of town
a couple blocks from the court chapel or
court complex to the west.
And here's the moat
around the court castle.
And here's the bridge going across it.
Right, let me see if I can
show it on the screen here.
There we go, right there.
There's the bridge leading
across the moat in Bach's day,
that's he we got to work every day.
And here's how that same bridge
over the moat looks today,
several hundred years later,
how it looked after the communist regime
relinquished East Germany after
the fall of the Berlin Wall.
And, as we can see by this next slide,
immediately thereafter,
Cöthen was in somewhat
of a state of disrepair.
But the first thing the West Germans
started to fix up was this part
of the castle, the court castle.
The rather well known Hall of Mirrors.
It has been restored.
It has been restored because it was
the most Important room in the castle.
This was the center of entertainment and
music for the court and
it's still used for
concerts that way today.
So let's take a moment now to review
where we stand with regard to JS Bach.
He's in central Germany.
He's married, 35 years old, four children.
He's now a Kapellmeister,
chief musician at court.
He's composing mainly instrumental music,
solo sonatas and suites for
violin and for cello, that sort of thing.
Composing many pieces in
the genre of concerto grosso.
We'll be hearing the Brandenberg
Concertos, at least bits of them,
in a moment and
he's composing preludes and fugues,
in a collection called
the Well Tempered Clavier.
Now, we'll come back to the Well
Tempered Clavier in just a minute.
But before the Well Tempered Clavier
reached fruition, it knew an earlier
life in something called The Keyboard Book
of Wilhelm Friedemann Bach,
which you see on this screen here.
It's an interesting story
about this particular book.
First of all,
it's at Yale University as you can see.
But Wilheim Friedemann Bach was
the first son of JS Bach, and
since most Bachs were musicians,
it was thought that Bach,
too, should train his
children to be musicians.
Train the next generation.
And to teach young Wilhelm Friedemann.
And as was the tradition with all
conscientious music teachers at that time,
Bach created a music book for
his child to learn from.
Father Mozart did the same thing for
his daughter Nannerl and son Wolfgang.
In those days you just couldn't go to the
neighborhood music store and buy music.
It didn't exist.
If you wanted teaching material
you had to create it yourself.
You had to do so by copying it by hand.
That's what was thought to be good and
useful for your pupil.
So here we have JS Bach
beginning such a book,
showing the boys the names
of the notes and
how to read the various clefs and
how to play the scales and so on.
As mentioned, this entire, very valuable
manuscript, perhaps the most valuable of
all Bach manuscripts,
is in the library at Yale University.
And the next slide, well, it shows us the
symbols and the signs of the ornaments,
and he introduces his son,
the fledgling keyboard player,
to these signs and symbols, which
are very important In the Baroque Era.
And then he begins to write his succession
of easy to play preludes and fugues.
The most famous of these
being the Prelude in C Major,
and indeed,
we've actually heard that before.
And if we turn to the end
of this same prelude,
we can see that interestingly enough,
the way it appears in its original
version was not exactly as Bach heard
it in his ear in the final version.
So you know this, this,
prelude, we've all heard it.
[MUSIC]
And then just the last four bars here,
in its original version.
[MUSIC]
Originally Bach ended it right there.
In the last version that we
know it by today there's a long
extra sus on the diminished chord,
I believe,
that brings him back to a different
ending of this prelude.
So what's a prelude?
Well, a prelude, of course, is a warm up
piece, gets the fingers limbered up and
relaxed and ready to play the more
substantive piece, the fugue.
So let's go on now to
learn about the fugue.
And we'll do so by means of a class video.
So we want to know about
how fugues operate, so
let's take a look at the specifics here.
The term fugue actually comes
from an old Latin word fuga,
which means flight or to fly.
So in a fugue,
what you get is one voice going ahead,
leading ahead and
another voice following it.
Now I just used the term voice there.
Fugues can be written for
actual voices, sounding voices.
Or they can be written for instruments
such as the violin or the cello.
Individual lines.
It can even be written for
instruments that can play several lines or
several parts at once.
The piano can do that,
the organ can do that, even the guitar.
And occasionally the violin
will be asked to do that.
Fugues have been written for
as few as two voices.
Yes, you could have a two voice fugue.
Up to as many as 32 voices.
And they can be, as mentioned,
written for, and they are best, perhaps,
performed on, these keyboard instruments
that have the capacity to play many lines,
many parts, many voices at once.
The greatest collection of fugues, as you
may have bumped into or heard about or
at least heard the term,
is this collection of preludes and
fugues by J S Back called
the Well Tempered Clavier.
First of all what's a prelude?
It's just a warm up piece.
[MUSIC]
You sort of get relaxed.
You get a, your fingers get the feel
of the keyboard, or of the lute or
whatever it might happen to be.
A prelude, a preplay, a warm up.
And then we go on to the meat of
the issue, which is the fugue.
Now why is this called
the well tempered clavier?
Anybody know?
Anybody have, it's an odd term.
Clavier just means keyboard.
The well tuned keyboard.
Thoughts there?
Well, what was going on in Bach's day is
that they didn't have a keyboard that
[MUSIC]
they didn't have a tuning system in which
all of the pitches were exactly a half
step apart.
Some were slightly closer together,
and then others farther apart.
And the key of C [SOUND] actually
had a slightly different sound
than the key of D [SOUND].
And it's only the 18th and
19th century that we gradually shifted
from an unequal keyboard to
an equally tuned keyboard.
So Bach is kind of part of this
transition to the equal tuned keyboard.
He was getting close to the equal
temperament of the modern keyboard.
And that's why he called
it the well tuned keyboard.
And by tuning it this way it allows
you to modulate to all keys.
And that's what he did in this collection.
He wrote two books, one in 17,
about 1722 when he was in Curtin and
another in about 1742
when he was in Leipzig.
And in each of these books we have
a total of 24 preludes and fugues.
One a prelude and
fugue in C major [SOUND].
One prelude and fugue in C minor [SOUND].
One prelude and
fugue in C sharp major [SOUND].
And one prelude and
fugue in C sharp minor [SOUND].
And so on it goes, all the way
up the keyboard in that fashion.
Two books of those.
And this is kind of standard fodder for
those that want to become
professional musicians.
Okay.
So that's what that is about.
The well tempered clavier.
We've been referencing Bach here, and
nobody of course wrote
better fugues then J S Bach.
Some continued,
some continued to write fugues.
Mozart wrote some fugues.
Haydn wrote some fugues.
Beethoven wrote some fugues, and so on.
And even into the 20th century
we have a few composers.
Paul Hindemith used to teach at Yale.
Dimitri Shostakovich.
They wrote fugues.
But, generally speaking,
the fugue has its heyday in the Baroque
period, roughly 1600 to 1750.
The heyday of Bach and Handel.
How do fugues work?
Well, they start out, as mentioned,
with one voice leading forward.
And then another voice
imitates that voice, exactly.
Now, if that following voice,
here's a question, if that following
voice imitated the leader exactly from
beginning to end what would we have?
A round.
Okay.
Good.
That's what we would have.
A round.
Or we could call,
use the fancier music word, a cannon.
Cannon, round, the same thing.
One voice imitating the other
exactly from beginning to end.
But in a fugue, what happens is,
after the main idea,
which we'll be calling the subject,
the main idea is stated, then the parts
go their independent ways generating
counterpoint, but they're not exact.
They're not precise duplication of the
rhythms and the pitches of the leaders.
So what we can do would be to visualize
this in a sort of crude way up here.
You have a leader and then a follower.
And the follower duplicates the main idea,
which we're gonna call the subject for
a period of time.
But then it kind of breaks off.
So, voices will come in and
duplicate a certain amount of material and
then break off and go their own way.
So that's a good way of
thinking of the beginning
of a fugue which we will
call the exposition.
I'll come back to that point in a moment.
Notice here I put a little,
silly little tree up here.
We could say that we have
the genus polyphony here.
And we've got monophonic texture,
homophonic texture, and
polyphonic texture.
So, within polyphonic texture we
have non-imitative texture, and
then a stream of imitative polyphony, and
then two forms of imitative polyphony,
rather strict, exactly strict,
imitative polyphony, the canon, and less
strict imitative polyphony, the fugue.
Okay?
Questions about that so far?
All right.
Let's go back to
the beginning of the fugue.
We have this opening melody,
the distinctive part of it which
we're gonna call the subject.
That's what we call the melody in a fugue,
the subject.
And the way this works is, in a fugue,
each of the voices in turn will
come in with that subject.
One will start out, and another will
come in, then another will come in.
After all of the voices are in,
we're at the end of what we call
the exposition of the fugue.
We hear in the fugue we
have just one theme.
But everybody's gonna get
a chance to present it.
And after everyone has
a chance to present it,
every voice has a chance to present it,
then we're finished with the exposition.
All the voices have exposed
the theme in their range.
After that, we go on to what's
called the episode of a fugue.
What happens in an episode?
Well, usually it modulates key.
And the vehicle through which composers
frequently modulate is melodic sequence,
either up or down.
You can kind of move
around by using sequence.
You can get to different
places by using sequence.
So it tends to be contrapuntal because
it's using little motives from the theme.
It modulates, moves around a lot, goes to
different keys, sounds a bit unsettled.
We start out here with the exposition in
which all voices present the subject.
Then you have this kind of free period in
which the motive out of the subjects is
played with, developed,
moved around different pitches.
Then the subject will
come back in a new key
because we've modulated it in the episode.
Subject in just one voice, new key.
Then another episode in which there's
modulation, more counterpoint,
more movement.
Another statement of
the subject in a new key.
Another episode.
Another statement of the subject, and
on it goes until we run out of energy
usually about after about four or
five minutes or so, at which point,
the composer will bring the subject back,
maybe in the bass or in the soprano, in
a very prominent range in the tonic key.
And we have the sense,
this is a very solid moment.
Yes, this fugue is ending.
And maybe they'll throw upon,
throw one or two chords on at the end.
But that's it.
That takes care of the fugue, generally.
But let's review now,
by way of a definition,
and by necessity it has to be a long one.
So what's a fugue?
Well, a fugue is a composition with two,
to as many as 32 lines or
parts, whether they be voices or
instruments.
But usually they're instrumental voices.
A Fugue begins with a succession of
statements of the subject in all voices.
That's called as we've seem the exposition
continues with alternations of subject and
free sections.
These episodes using material
derived from the subject.
The episodes modulate
through different keys.
And ultimately, the subject returns in
the tonic key with a strong affirmation
of that tonic key.
Now, let's dig in to a few now,
specifically the few from
Bach's Well Tempered Clavier in C minor.
So you see the fugue, the music for
the fugue on the screen up there.
We're going to start upper left
hand side of the page there,
and this particular fugue is written for
three voices.
And we'll call them alto,
soprano and bass.
Starts with the alto voice.
Here's the subject.
>> [MUSIC]
Okay, that takes us page one,
third system, middle of the page there.
So, we've got all three of our
statements of the subject,
that's the end of the exposition.
Now, we have an episode.
I'm going to play just the bottom
part here so we can see.
The melodic sequence.
But episodes modulate.
[MUSIC]
And then so on it goes.
So, we have a pitch starting here.
[MUSIC]
Each one of those successively
lower degree, the scale,
the effect of that is to take us from
here, minor key up to hear at this point,
this is the fourth system, the subject
comes back, but this time in a major key.
[MUSIC]
And then another modulation
which takes us over to page two.
Now, I want to point out something of
interest here at page two top system.
Has to do with the episode.
Page two, top system, last two bars.
We have an episode and
we're working with a motive here and
the motive sounds this way.
Part A of the motive.
[MUSIC]
And part b up above against it.
Okay, a and b.
Now, watch what he does in
the continuation of this episode
in the first bar of the second system,
second system, first bar.
B is now down below.
[MUSIC]
And A is now up above.
So, he's switched the two, we have
what's called invertible counterpoint.
We've inverted these motives.
Okay systems three and four we go through.
[MUSIC]
Another episode,
long melodic sequence takes us down to
bottom system where the bass
comes back in the key.
[MUSIC]
And then we're going to head toward
the end, final drive to the cadence here.
[MUSIC]
Final statement.
Of the subject.
And that's how it sounds.
On a harpsichord.
This is a synthesizer
sounding like a harpsichord.
[MUSIC]
But notice the bass has
completely died out.
Bach probably had the sound
of the organ in his ear here,
because we want that tonic note and
some performers actually play it this way.
[MUSIC]
So, we get that tonic
base strongly in our ear.
Now, if Bach had performed
this on the organ, and
through the marvels of the modern
synthesizer, I may be able to do this,
play this on something that may
be the sound of a rock organ.
Yes.
[MUSIC]
Hear the bass sounding.
It continues to sound on an organ and
it works on an organ.
It doesn't work so well on a harpsichord.
Well that holding line there
is called a pedal point, and
obviously the term comes from the Baroque
organ process of having a pedal,
usually in the base, hold out as
upper material slides above it.
[MUSIC]
More effective that way.
Okay, well let's review using some
of the terms that we've discussed
in association with the Fugue.
Subject, obviously you know that's the
main theme episode, excuse me, exposition.
Well that's the section in which
the subject is presented in
succession in all of the voices at
the beginning of a few episode.
Episode is a pre modulatory
section in which
motives out of the subject are derived and
then exploited therein modulation
obviously that's a change of key.
That's what episodes are good at,
getting you from one key to the next.
Melodic sequence, we talked about,
presentation of the mode of
different pitch levels,
it allows the performer to modulate.
And pedal point,
which we were just introduced to,
a sustained note oftentimes in
some sort of tonic fashion and
gives a strong sense of the tonality that
particular point along sustained pitch.
Okay, these are terms for today.
And a final point.
Fugues have always seemed to me
to be somewhat mathematical.
We saw that episode in which the music,
well,
it was first in the bottom,
and then the top.
And then the box switched them around.
They put the top music on the bottom,
and the bottom music on the top.
Well in a sense, you can do the same
sort of thing in mathematics.
These particular parts of this
equation here can be re-shuffled
in any number of different ways, and
the answer will always be the same.
The effect will always be the same.
It's like playing in odd sort of ways,
manipulating I suppose,
Lego's in one fashion or another.
And the same thing happens with the
constructiveness or mathematical design as
I'll call it here in a creation
by Josef Albers entitled Fugue.
Josef Albers used to be the dean of the
school of art and architecture at Yale and
he's got the construction
called a Fugue and
then he's got these motives in the Fugue.
Well, we can take these motives and
as I've done here, I've just arbitrarily
duplicated the image and made it go
backwards, just turned it around so
that we have it going forwards and
backwards at the same time.
Does it look any different really, to you?
Does the bottom one have a different
sort of sense of it for you?
And you could do the same thing as
we'll see from the next slide here.
We could flip it upside down and
make it go backwards.
So, we've got to make it going
backwards and then upside down.
You could hang this thing on your wall
any one of three or four ways and
I don't think it would matter a lot.
So, again,
the parts in something as intellectual
constructivist as a fugue can be arranged
in many different sorts of ways.
And how we feel about the composition,
whether visual or
musical really doesn't change very much.