[MUSIC]
So here we are again in
the hall of mirrors in Cöthen.
Central performance hall of the Prince of
Cöthen anhalt, in the early 18th century.
Bach had just arrived in town and
was placed in charge of
the small court orchestra.
And indeed, he was bulking it up by
means of an active recruiting policy.
He was drawing top musicians to Cöthen,
from important Berlin some
hundred miles to the north.
Bach made a couple of trips
to Berlin in this period.
In one of them he was sent by the Prince
of Cöthen, to acquire and transport back
to Cöthen, a large two manual harpsichord
made by one Michael Mietke in 1719.
During these trips to Berlin,
Bach made the acquaintance of the Margrave
of Brandenburg, one of the relatives of
the King of Prussia, Frederick the Great.
Later, back in Cöthen, but always angling
for a better position, a better job.
Bach gathered up a collection of
six concertos, bound them together,
wrote a flowery and dedication page and
sent them to the Margrave.
Here's some of what Bach's
dedication to the Margrave said.
Well actually [LAUGH] I
can't read it on the screen.
I'm a little bit far away from it,
that doesn't matter.
You've got a closer vision,
view of the slide and you can read it.
But it's written in French,
which was actually the language
of the court in that period.
And it's done in the most
obsequious sort of prose where,
Bach seems to be bending over
backwards to almost prostrate himself,
in order that he can get
this position in Berlin,
impress the Margrave of Brandenburg.
Did it work?
No, apparently the Margrave never
even looked at the collection.
[LAUGH] They sat in a royal
library until the 19th century,
when they were rediscovered.
Bach's fame was finally beginning to grow.
They were rediscovered, but note,
not until the mid 19th century.
Well, let's focus on the fifth of
these six Brandenburg Concertos.
And as you can see here from the slide,
we've got a total of six of them.
They were written in the period 1715 to
1721, and we're gonna focus on Number 5.
It has a Concertino, remember that
it's the little group of soloist,
of solo violin, flute, and harpsichord.
Then the Tutti everybody else in this case
about a dozen or so, plus the Concertino.
The Concertino plus everybody
else that equals the Tutti, and
the Tutti plays the ritornello.
The ritornello has many of the
characteristics of late Baroque melody.
It's idiomatic writing for the violin and
we'll hear why it's
idiomatic in just a second.
And this particular concerto uses
a cadenza, employs a cadenza at the end.
A showy passage for a soloist,
at the end of a movement,
to showcase his or
her particular technical skills.
And as we'll finally observe here,
this particular movement's a long one.
We're not going to hear all of it,
but it is a long one.
9 minutes in length
compared to 3 minutes in
length to a typical movement of
a Concerto Grosso of Vivaldi.
And again, the Margrave put them in a
closet, and they really weren't published,
they didn't become known until 1850,
about 130 years later.
Let's just review again.
Here's a typical layout of
Ritornello form, and as you can see,
it's a very simple idea, where we have
the ritornello played by everybody.
We have this idea of the concertino,
playing excerpts, motis,
out of the ritornello.
It functions very much like an episode,
in a few.
Then the tutti comes back
in with a ritornello.
Concertino comes back in with motis,
derived from the ritornello.
Tutti, concertino, tutti, concertino.
On it goes.
Now we here we see the autograph
of Bach's original here.
This is Bach's autograph
of the first movement of
Brandenburg Concerto Number Five.
As we look up there in the top score,
we can see that the flute part of
the concertino is actually resting.
Then the solo violin comes in.
And the violin of the full
orchestra of the tutti comes in and
they play this melody, something
very typical of baroque music, and
something very idiomatic to the violin
cuz it can repeat pitches rather quickly.
So it's good at this and
it sounds good on a violin.
[MUSIC]
Well, there I played it on a harpsichord,
or a harpsichord synthesizer.
But you get the sense of it.
So here,
you can see the melody of the ritornello.
We'll be hearing that again,
and again as it returns.
Then, the lower strings,
the second violins, and the violas
begin to,
they flesh out the texture underneath.
The bottom two systems,
that's the music for the harpsichord.
But notice that the harpsichord again
has no music actually written for
the right-hand score, it's empty.
That's because the performer,
in this case J S Bach himself.
Bach wrote these numbers,
Bach knew what these numbers meant.
And he used those numbers to
flesh out the harmony above.
Okay, so let's go back now to
our hall of mirrors at Cöthen.
Here we see it as it exists
today with the seats in place,
and there's even a sculpture of J.S.
Bach over there to the left.
And now let's hear a performance of this,
and as you listen to this performance,
ask yourself, or I'm asking you,
what's unusual about this?
What goes on in this
performance that we see here,
and probably wouldn't happen in
a concert of music in the modern day.
[MUSIC]
Well right off the bat, you can see
that the performers are standing up and
that was actually typical.
The only people sitting down are people
that play cello and harpsichord.
Okay.
Flute [INAUDIBLE] wood flute,
transverse flute.
[MUSIC]
We'll pause it right here and notice how
far this violin's hand is up on the bow.
That's typical of Baroque performance.
It allows for a fast and light style of
playing, which is very different then
the later 19th century style where the
hand puts a lot of pressure on the bow.
Let's continue a while.
So we're now having
the concertino perform.
We've had the ritornello.
Now we're having the concertino play.
[MUSIC]
There's the ritornello.
and off the concertino goes again.
Soloing out.
[MUSIC]
>> The ritornello again but
in a different key.
All right let's pause it here now.
We're gonna pause it.
Maybe I can pause it.
I'll pause it.
I'm gonna try to move it up.
We'll see where we are.
We're gonna move it all the way over here,
cuz we want to see the harpsichord
gradually begin to take over.
This is the beginning of
the harpsichord cadenza.
[MUSIC]
It might seem easy, but
this is one of the most difficult pieces
in the entire keyboard repertoire to play.
[MUSIC]
And it's a long Cadenza.
As we swing around a trill
on the left hand there.
[MUSIC]
Two manual harpsichord.
Notice the upper keys are going up and
down with the bottom one.
That means he's got them coupled,
he's using his two-eights in conjunction.
Sounds like a magic trick,
but there's a reason for it.
[MUSIC]
Now he's playing the upper
of the two-eighths.
[MUSIC]
Coming up chromatically,
In a moment you'll hear a pedal point
beginning to bang away underneath.
[MUSIC]
And.
End of cadenza.
Tutti comes back in playing
the ritornello and driving to the end.
[MUSIC]
Wow, quite a workout.
Okay let's recap by means of a slide here.
The Brandenburg Concertos, a collection
of six gathered up 17, 21, 17, 21, four.
The Margrave of Brandenburg,
Concerto Grosso.
In genre showing the differentiation
between the concertino and
the tutti that we've talked about
making use of figured bass.
Continuing to exploit the idea
of the basso continuo,
the keyboard accompanied there by a cello.
They're forming the basso
continuo in this movement.
Idiomatic writing we've talked about is
very easy for a violin to go da da da da,
da da da da, da da da da back and
forth very quickly over the string.
So it works well on the violin, and we saw
a splendid example of a lengthy cadenza.
And let us not forget,
it all makes for wonderful music.