[MUSIC]
In 1723 Bach moved again.
This time to Leipzig for a better job
to be cantor of the city of Leipzig,
the university town.
Free education at that university for
his many sons but not his daughters.
Daughters didn't go to university in
any number until the 19th century.
So here is a slide of
a map showing Leipzig.
And here Kurten, slightly to the north
of Leipzig, Kurten where Bach lived for
six years.
And here's nearby Leipzig
where he moved in 1723.
Now, in 1723 exactly the year
that Bach moved here,
this particular engraving was done.
And here we see the church, front and
center there, the church of Saint Thomas.
And then to the left the choir school.
Now Bach, let's see if I can
show this with my pointer.
Bach lived here in the choir school,
lower left side there.
Second floor, he had these two windows
here, and these two windows here and
they swung around to the other side.
So there was his apartment complex on
the south side of the choir school.
The job of cantor at Leipzig
was a prestigious post, but
it came with limitations and
onerous duties.
Bach was required to superintend
the music at four churches in Leipzig,
teach the boys music, teach the boys
Latin, prepare all the music for
the nearby university, and perform
music at weddings and funerals as well.
Let me read to you, the oath of office
that Bach swore to the town magistrate
when he assumed the position of cantor.
I have my trusty Bach
reader out here today.
Bach agrees to bring the music
in the principle churches of the town into
good estate to the best of my ability.
Show the honorable and wise council
all proper respect and obedience.
I'm skipping some here, but going on,
give due obedience to the honorable
inspectors and directors of the school.
Arrange the music that is shall
not last [LAUGH] too long.
[LAUGH] They didn't want Bach's
music to go on too long.
They knew Bach.
They knew what he might do.
That the music not go on too long,
nor that it be too operatic.
No opera praise.
[LAUGH] To treat the boys
in a friendly manner.
Faithfully attend to
the instruction in the school.
Not go out of town without permission.
Always so far as possible walk
with the boys at funerals.
Well it sounds like Bach is more
of a scoutmaster here than he
is the grand artist.
But the most important thing,
the most time consuming thing that Bach
had to do is to compose a new cantata.
It didn't stipulate this.
It was just assumed that he would
compose a new cantata every week.
Compose what is called
a Lutheran church cantata.
But let's look again at Bach's church and
get a sense of where he and
his musicians were situated
while they performed this music.
So here we see this same slide again.
And here we see the boy,
see that little clump there, the boys, and
you know those are choir boys.
If you've ever followed the perambulations
of a choir, you can see that they
always put the smallest boys at the front
and the elderly gentlemen at the back.
So here they come, out of the front door,
the choir school moving across the yard
here, and
they're about to make a left hand turn.
I can assure you that this,
make a left hand turn,
as we'll see by the next slide here.
So they enter the church
at this door here.
In they come,
they could go right to the high altar, but
far more likely, they're going to
go left up into the choir loft.
So here looking right,
we see the high alter of the church,
but now looking in the other direction,
we see the choir loft.
And here's another slide showing,
I believe, the choir loft,
a fuller view of the choir loft as
it looked in the 19th century on,
with the now late 19th
century Sauer organ up there.
This is what it looked like looking
to the west in the choir loft where
the musicians were.
Now let's see what it
looked like in Bach's day.
This is not JS Bach, but this is
an illustration done in Leipzig itself
in 1732 showing musicians in a choir loft.
And it gives you a sense of what
was going on in a church choir loft
at this time as a Lutheran church
service unfolds with the musicians.
So here we see the continuo
here with the organ now, and
a cello, and a group of violinists
holding the violin bow as we see,
as we saw before in the video, and
then some brass instruments up here.
And they're all playing as stipulated
a Lutheran Church cantata.
So what's a cantata?
Well, as you can see,
a cantata is a kind of mini-musical drama,
about 30 minutes in duration.
It's made up of movements,
movements consisting of arias,
recitatives, and choruses.
In Germany in particular,
it had a spiritual theme.
And usually,
it was based on a chorale tune.
So obviously, the question is,
what then is a chorale tune?
Well, a chorale tune is simply
a straightforward melody on
a sacred text to be sung by
the congregation, sung by everybody.
Some of these chorale tunes are centuries
old, drawn from old Gregorian chant.
Some of them were newly composed,
as early as the 16th century
by Martin Luther himself.
A Mighty Fortress is Our God is
perhaps the most famous one.
Some of them were popular songs.
What would happen is they would take
a pop song, strip the pop lyrics off it,
and assign it religious lyrics.
As Luther himself famously said, why
should the devil have all the good tunes?
So he took those good tunes and
he put them to, in his mind, good use.
And these chorale tunes are strophic,
strophic in a sense, of course,
that they are made up of stanzas of text.
Well, here is the famous portrait of
Martin Luther, painted by Lucas Cranach.
It's today in the Saint Anne Church in
Augsburg where Luther spent some time.
And to the right we see a chorale
tune composed by Luther,
A Mighty Fortress is our God,
with the tune here up on top,
and four strophes of text below.
Let me just play this for you to remind
you what a Lutheran chorale sounds like.
[MUSIC]
Likely you've heard that.
Okay, so that's the first phrase of Martin
Luther's A Mighty Fortress is our God.
Now, let's see how a chorale or
hymn tune can be
used inside of a cantata to
give structure to that cantata.
So, let's turn on to our next slide here.
We'll be working with the cantata,
Wacht auf, ruft uns die Stimme.
Awake, A Voice is Calling,
you can see the date there, 1731.
It was written for a Sunday before Advent,
indeed the fourth Sunday before Advent.
So that means roughly four
Sundays before Christmas.
It is based on a traditional
chorale of the Lutheran Church
made up of seven movements,
which is not unusual.
And movements 1, 4, and 7 use the chorale
tune as you can see here.
So the chorale begins with stanza one and
then the next time you hear the chorale
you get stanza two of the text and
next time we hear the chorale,
we actually get stanza three of the text.
So it provides a kind of
symmetrical structure for it.
The text keeps changing, but
the chorale tune doesn't.
Between stanzas of the chorale tune
come pairs of recitative and aria,
setting newly composed text which talks of
the love between Christ and his people.
Now let's take a look at this
chorale tune in particular here.
This is a chorale tune dating
back to the 16th century.
Awake, His Voice is Calling,
is written in seven phrases.
it has an overall structure of A, A, B.
Which also is standard for chorale tunes.
We get phrases one, two, and three, and
then one, two, and three again, and
then four, five, six, and seven, and
three comes back to round off that melody.
Let me play a bit of this for
you at the keyboard here.
Oh, well,
maybe I'll play it over here off this end.
[MUSIC]
Here's phase three.
Then that repeats, so here is one.
[MUSIC]
Two.
And three.
[MUSIC]
And then it goes on from there.
Let's take a quick look again
at our seven movement format,
I think we'll see that on the next slide.
Here we have our seven movement format.
And we're going to start
off with movement one.
How does the cantata work within
the framework of the Lutheran Sunday
church service?
Well, that service was the civic
high point of the week.
It was partly religious and
partly a social event, was the time when
people of similar beliefs got together.
And it was a long service,
running from about 7 in
the morning to 11 in the morning.
And it could be dark and cold in the
winter, no central heating in those days.
So here you can see the essential events,
the high points of the service with their
reading of the gospel from the pulpit.
This was the essential
spiritual message of the day.
Then came the cantata which was
a commentary on the spiritual message but
in music.
Then came the sermon which was a
commentary on the same spiritual message,
again in words,
in the words of the preacher.
That sermon went on for about an hour.
So scripture, cantata, sermon.
Now, let's read a bit of the scripture for
the day,
to give a sense of what this is all about.
So here's the gospel Matthew, then
shall the kingdom of heaven be likened
unto ten virgins, which took their lamps
and went forth to meet the bridegroom.
And five of them were wise and
five were foolish.
They that were foolish took their
lamps but took no oil with them.
And at midnight there was made a cry.
Behold, the bridegroom cometh,
go ye out to meet him.
And then all those virgins arose, and
trimmed their lamps and so on it goes.
Well obviously this is a parable
about the wise and foolish and
virgins who's wise were prepared, and
the message to those good citizens
of Leipzig was, get your spiritual
house in order because the Lord is about
to arrive, will arrive on Christmas Day.
Let's listen to a performance
of this cantata.
But let's first review, with the aid of
the slide, the structure of the cantata.
So here we have the seven movements, and
we're going to start off with the first
movement, which the chorus will
be singing the chorale tune.
You'll hear it up on high
in the female voices.
The chorus will be
singing the chorale tune.
And here, just to remind us
the way that chorale tune goes.
[MUSIC]
All right, so
let's go on now to have our video
with Ton Koopman performing in Amsterdam.
[MUSIC]
So, they're playing [FOREIGN].
Notice the strange woodwind instrument,
the low oboe.
And here comes the chorale tune.
Up in the soprano part.
Like a beacon on high.
The word of the Lord.
There's that interesting low oboe again.
Phrase two of the chorale.
Panning around where
the falsetto altos [INAUDIBLE].
Notice how high his hand is on that bow.
Bassoon of course.
Phrase three of the chorale.
[FOREIGN] Wake up, heads up.
And now all of this repeats because
we said it was in A, A, B form but
we're going to pause it here.
Let's go on to explore the core
movement of the cantata.
And by far the most famous movement of
this cantata, movement number four.
Here in movement four the chorale tune
returns with stanza two of the text.
[FOREIGN], Zion hears
the Daughters singing.
But the music doesn't
start with the chorale.
But rather it starts with
another instrumental ritornello,
an instrumental refrain.
And this one is
a particularly beautiful one.
You can see it on
the screen up here on top.
And then after the ritornello
is played through,
the chorale tune enters.
But this time, it enters in unison,
all the male voices singing here together.
So, let me play this, and we'll start
out with the instrumental ritornello,
and then the chorale tunes come in.
Think about this,
Bach has a beautiful melody here.
He had a pre-existing beautiful melody
here, and now, he combines the two.
[MUSIC]
You hear the bass moving
along as Baroque basses do,
almost plodding along,
a walking bass, as it's called.
[MUSIC]
Here comes the chorale.
Ritornello continues underneath.
[MUSIC]
And then it repeats, so here we go.
Back to the beginning with the ritornello.
That's a very beautiful passage, a very
beautiful movement and actually the only
one that Bach ever published among these
chorale movements in his own lifetime.
Finally to the last movement,
the grand finale.
So now we've moved on to movement seven,
and
we have the third stanza of
the chorale text being sung here.
The entire congregation actually
sings the chorale tune at this point.
Everybody presumably standing and
affirming the rightness of their
religion and faith in their community.
The community bonds as we said
in session one of our course.
The community bonds through music.
So let's take a look at what's happening
in terms of the music at this point,
as we'll see on the next slide.
This was the emotional high point,
the conclusion of the cantata.
And you can see that it is
written in homophonic style.
Simple homophonic style with
the chorale tune up above.
[MUSIC]
But everybody singing presumably
the soprano, but maybe a clever bass,
knowing how to sing the bass
would have sung the bass.
And all of the instruments and
everybody in the chorus would have been
coming along in the homophonic style.
[MUSIC]
And on it will go.
So again, this is the spiritual
high point of this entire cantata,
the final movement.
Let's give a listen.
[MUSIC]
Then it starts to repeat.
And on it goes.
To sum up, what makes Bach's music great?
Why is he rated by many the number
one composer of all time?
Well, let's review by
means of a slide here.
First of all, his music is universal.
He wrote in all genres of
music in his day except opera.
He was too religious a man,
I suppose, to do that.
Clearly, the greatest
contrapuntalist who every lived.
Music sounds great, but
it's perhaps even greater than
it sounds if that is possible.
It has contrapuntal craftsmanship and
integrity to it.
Bach's sound is not only densely
packed with counterpoint, but
can be grandiose, even majestic as we
heard here with the finale of our cantata.
It's also extremely lyrical at times,
as we heard with movement
four of our cantata.
So Bach combines counterpoint and
grandeur and lyricism.
The scale of Bach's works are enormous.
He doesn't take shortcuts.
Movement of a Bach concerto
grosses such as we saw there at
the first movement of
Brandenburg Concerto number five
is three times longer than a comparable
one in a movement of Vivaldi.
Universality, counterpoint,
craftsmanship, grandeur, integrity.
These are the things that
make Bach's music great.