[MUSIC]
When Bach first came to Leipzig in 1723
he was in middle-age, ambitious and
active and he worked hard.
Writing a new cantata about 30 minutes of
music every work that's a lot of work and
Bach got tired of it.
Hence, toward the end of his life he
went into, in effect, phased retirement.
[LAUGH] Working on only a few
esoteric contrapuntal projects.
But would producing a new cantata
every week really have worn out Bach?
What was the most onerous,
most difficult, most demanding aspect of
producing 30 minutes of music,
30 new minutes of music every week?
Composing the music copying the music,
or rehearsing the music?
What do you think?
In terms of time, copying,
writing music down and
copying all the parts that was
probably the most time consuming part.
Here for
example is the autograph of a full score.
Of the opening page of an early cantata by
Bach, by my count there are 20 instruments
and voices performing here, 20 lines and
each measure goes by in about two seconds.
So you might have a thousand, easily
a thousand measures of music in a cantata.
So you have to create this page,
the master score and then you'll have to
then have all the individual parts copied,
parts for the strings,
parts for the woodwinds, parts for
the voices and so on that's a lot of work.
Where was all this done?
Well, in the church choir school,
where Bach lived and Bach worked.
And this is how it worked in 1723,
Bach worked here as he saw,
I just think I can show you the cursor.
On the south end of the choir school.
And I want you to count the number of
stories in this building before we
reach the roof line.
One, two, three okay, three story.
Now, this is how that building looked,
that same building, looked from 1735 on.
There we have it count
the number of stories now.
One, two, three, four, five.
In 1735, they lifted up the roof and
added two stories to this building.
They did so
to create, in large measure, more
space for Bach because they needed it.
Inside the school where Bach's very
numerous children, in totally he had 20.
Various relatives and a couple of boarding
students, fee-paying boarding students.
This was, this building was
the corporate headquarters of Bach Ink.
But most important, working in this
building was Bach's wife, Anna Magdalena.
So here, we see a slide it may or
may not, be an Anna Magdalena.
Bach, we can't be sure,
but she was a musician,
a talented singer, but she couldn't sing,
in Bach's time, in Leipzig.
No woman sang in church,
in these Lutheran churches in this
period in Bach's religious Leipzig.
But, she was Bach's principal
handmaiden as a copiest.
Now here, you're about to see
a famous manuscript that she
copied Anna Bach's
unaccompanied cello suites.
On the left you see, [INAUDIBLE] We're
just going to listen to this music and
I'm going to talk about this music for
a little.
So here's Anna Magdalena's.
[MUSIC]
Hand over here and
here's her husband's hand over here and
they're virtually identical.
She taught him much about music.
And, undoubtedly, her style,
her style of calligraphy was influenced by
him to the point that they're virtually.
Indistinguishable and sometimes scholars
had difficulty telling the two apart.
[MUSIC]
Well, when old Bach died in 1750 he
was buried in a local parish church
no one paid much attention to him or his
music, then something strange happened.
Around 1830, Bach's unappreciated
music was rediscovered in part by
Felix Mendelsohn, and
it rightly became usually popular.
The good citizens of Leipzig,
had begun to realize that they'd
had in their midst a genius.
So what did they do?
They dug him up to measure his skull.
What?
[LAUGH] Measure his skull?
Well, measure his skull, yes because
at the end of the 19th century,
some scientists, one might say mad
scientists, had a theory that having
a diminished size skull,
being microcephalic, was a mark of genius.
So they dug him up, measured his skull,
and found it to be completely normal.
Now what to do?
Well, capitalize on the event.
So, instead of putting Bach back
in an outlying parish church.
Why not give him a place of
prominence that he deserves?
Bury him at the high
altar as you see here and
that's what the plaque is here,
the high altar of the St. Thomas Church.
Today the most important
church in the life saving.
And while we're at it here at
the end of the 19th century why not
make a real shrine to Bach?
Let's put in a huge stained glass window
a Bach, with references to his music so
that tourists,
musical tourists like you and
like me will visit Leipzig, inveterate
the late, great Bach, the church becoming
something akin to a musical hall of fame,
and that's exactly what happened.
So, if you ever have the chance,
go there, it's actually worth the trip,
and you'll hear and
enjoy a lot of great music by Bach.