[MUSIC]
What a contrast between Bach and Handel.
The two formal portraits in this
opening slide tells us much.
Bach is dressed modestly, holding
a contrapuntal canon, smallish sized,
something that only the musicians,
who played it could appreciate.
Handel, on the other hand,
is dressed in the finery of a wealthy man.
Looking confident and
holding a large score of Messiah,
the grand public piece intended
to be heard by the masses.
[MUSIC]
As we saw at the end of our last session,
when Bach died in 1750 his
music languished in obscurity,.
After Handel's death on the other hand,
Handel's reputation only grew in renown.
He became postmortem the most
famous composer in the west.
Bach worked in church choir lofts
in small to mid sized German towns.
Handel worked in large theaters,
in the largest and
most prosperous city in the western world,
London.
And generally speaking,
Bach sought integrity,
even perfection,
in the internal workings of his music.
He often wrote on his music scores,
AMGD, ad
maiorem gloriam Dei,
to the greater glory of God.
Handel on the other hand seems to have
been more concerned about those on
this earth.
He seemed to have composed to
achieve the greatest effect with
the greatest number of
citizens of the day.
And that, he accomplished.
Let's begin with this same map with
which we started our discussion of Bach,
that of eighteenth century Germany.
Let's go to Leipzig where Bach resided and
only forty miles to the north to where
is and where Bach resided for
six years before coming to Leipzig.
And in between them,
then, as now, is Halle.
Here, Handel was born in 1685,
the same year as Bach.
Handel's father was a barber surgeon.
In effect, a medical man,
who first prevented his talented
son from studying music.
But then relented, providing him
with music teachers on the organ,
violin, and in music theory,
music composition.
At the age of 18, Handel moved on his
financial own to the port city of Hamburg.
Here we see Hamburg in the 18th century,
a thriving,
waterfront city on the North Sea.
Handel was employed here as
a second violinist in the orchestra
of the Hamburg opera.
But knowing then that Italy was the center
of opera and all things musical generally,
Handel began a four
year long tour of Italy
moving to Florence and then to Rome
where he spent most of his time and
ultimately, to a few months to Venice
where he embraced Italian opera, but
most of the time as we've
said Handel was in Rome.
Here we see one of the palaces at
which he was sometimes employed.
It was the palaces of the noblemen, and
of the princes of the church,
mostly cardinals.
And they sponsored weekly concerts of
sacred operas and sacred cantatas.
On the screen is one of the more
important of the Roman palaces,
the palace of the Cancellaria,
run by the Ottoboni family,
and that palace is still very
much in downtown Rome today, and
this was where one of Hildo's
largest religious works,
the Resurrection was performed in 1708.
Ultimately having assimilated
the Italian vocal style,
Handel made his way to Venice,
where he produced an opera.
And where somewhat by accident,
he met representatives of the court of the
Elector of Hanover, based back in Germany.
And Handel was offered a job there.
And he accepted.
So now at age 25,
having made the grand tour of Italy,
Hendell was back in Germany but
he did it then, a cheeky thing.
He immediately asked for a leave of
absence to visit London and off he goes.
London, with a population of more than
500,000 in the early 18th century,
was the largest city in Europe,
a growing center of commerce and
trade and hence of wealth.
As Handel's German friend, and
they were good friends, Johan Matheson
famously said, in France and
Italy there is something to learn, but
in London, there is something to earn.
Handel intended to earn by
importing Italian opera to London,
just as fashionistas
import Ferragamo shoes or
Prada handbags to London or
to New York today.
So Handel went to London
in 1710 to sell opera.
But before we delve into that,
let's pause for a moment and see how
it came to be that Handel's
master back in Germany,
the Elector of Hanover,
caught up with Handel in London.
It makes for an interesting story.