[MUSIC]
Welcome back.
Before we continue with our enjoyment with
the music Bach and Handel, let's take
a minute to review what we've discovered
thus far for late Baroque music.
Here we were coming out of
the Renaissance and into the Baroque.
Renaissance music by way of
review was chant inspired,
imitative was the basis of the style.
Most of the music was religious music,
it was predominantly vocal music,
it was performed acapella,
which if you remember,
was music performed without instruments.
Then we had these three types of music or
three genres of music,
mass, motet, and madrigal.
When we come into the 17th
century with the Baroque period,
we have the Jean Rousseau concerto grosso,
fugues and
cantatas and oratorios and
operas, that sort of thing.
It's predominately instrumental.
Violin becomes the leading instrument.
The melodies, generally,
are long and symmetrical.
Strong base line is set
by a basso continuo and
the harpsichord is part
of that basso continuo.
Rhythms are repetitious.
Music chugs along, even drives along,
in an energetic fashion.
And there is a single ethos or mood.
Once a mood is set in a piece,
it doesn't change.
It stays there from beginning to end.
Let's turn now to a slide of some
music of this period, music of Handel.
It's his famous Largo.
Actually, it's an aria out of his opera,
Xerxes, written in 1738.
Let me play a bit of it.
[MUSIC]
Well the tempo is consistent.
There's a slow beat here.
The beat is consistent in its duration.
The dynamic level is constant and
the music moves on sort of nonstop.
One mood, beginning to end.
Now, some music of Bach.
A violin concerto but done in the style
that we might call Bach rock.
Two performers on the Chinese erhu,
in what way is this music Baroque and
what way is it not?
[MUSIC]
You hear the long musical line,
that melody is still going on.
Why it works, in part,
is because of Baroque rhythm.
It's usually driving and
consistent, and so is the pounding,
driving, consistent music and
the rhythm of much rock music.
And a lot of pop music