[MUSIC]
Today we're going to look at
the English Royal Family,
the matronly Queen Elizabeth II,
Prince Charles, the photogenic Duke and
Duchess of Cambridge and their son
baby George, the future King George.
It's perhaps amusing to realize that this
current Baby George is a direct descendent
of Gayhard Ludvig Van Hanover,
the elector of Hanover
who is Handel's patron, and who became
in 1714 King George I of England.
Why a seemingly obscure German prince was
picked by Parliament to be the king of
England has to do with Parliament's
fear oddly enough of Catholics.
When the throne fell vacant in 1714,
parliament looked to
the closest male Protestant in line for
the English throne, and they found him.
An obscure German Lutheran
who spoke no English, and
they elevated him to King of England.
So there was trueth Handel in London
when he supposed to be back in Hanover.
And lo and behold, his patron comes
from Germany to London in 1714 and
becomes King George I.
But fortunately,
the new king bore Handel no grudge.
And in fact George appointed Handel
the music teacher to his wife, the queen.
And thereafter, Handel served as de
facto English Royal Court Composer,
writing music for coronations.
And some of that coronation music
has been used at every English
coronation since then.
And, Handel wrote music for funerals,
and for victories, and battle, and
for birthdays, and for
public entertainment, generally.
Sometimes in the history of the English
monarchy, the royal family seems to be
in favor, as with the very buff looking
Duke and Duchess of Cambridge here.
But at other times, the monarchy
seems to have needed a bit of boost.
Queen Elizabeth II, for example, more than
once invited pop musicians Elton John and
Paul McCartney and, to Buckingham Palace,
offering public concerts outside for
the general populace to enjoy.
But this tradition goes all
the way back to Handel, and
specifically to the water music, and
the music of the royal fireworks that
Handel created for George I and his son.
Let's start with the water music.
In the summer of 1717,
the English court commissioned a nautical
entertainment with music by Handel.
One fine summer evening, the king and
his courtiers went up stream in one
large barge, while behind them,
in another, came Handel's musicians,
about 50 in number.
As they went, they played what has
come to be called the water music.
In fact, they played this hour
long outdoor concert three times,
twice going upstream,
when your screen going right to left, and
then once coming back downstream.
Well, what's this water music?
It's a rather loose connection of
pieces arranged in three groups,
each called a dance suite.
What's a dance suite?
Well a suite is just a succession
of pieces in a logical order.
So we have a succession
of short dances here.
Usually dances called Sarabande, or
Minuet, or Ragaudon, or Country Dances.
Things of that sort.
But obviously, on the water,
these pieces couldn't be danced.
They were just listened to.
Dance music,
as was often the case in the baroque and
classical eras, dance music was becoming,
becoming just listening music.
Called a dance suite,
but just listened to.
Let's give a listen to
just one of these dances.
And to do so, we'll turn to a YouTube clip
coming from a concert given recently at
the famous Prom concerts in the summer in
London at the cavernous Royal Albert Hall.
What your about to see is a group of
performers who specialize in early music,
including baroque music.
We'll be listening to
a minuet with it's trio.
The tempo is very fast, maybe too fast.
But we'll see.
[MUSIC]
So starting with the natural horn,
so you see no valves here.
[MUSIC]
I'm not sure they're playing all the
correct notes, but we'll pass over that.
It's a bit ragged, it seems to me.
And a very fast tempo.
[MUSIC]
One, two, three, one, two, three,
one, two, one, two, three.
There's the trio a trio we
originally meant just three lines or
three parts of music.
Top middle bottom.
Trios are different mood
than the surrounding minuet
[MUSIC]
So here comes the minuet back, and now
orchestrated for violins and woodwinds.
Oh, missed a note or two there.
[MUSIC]
Trio comes back in a minor key.
Firstly bassoons.
[MUSIC]
And back to the minuet.
That's a bit of the water music.
Let's go on now to listen to another
piece of royal music, music for
the Royal Fireworks.
Handel composed it later in 1749 for
an outdoor summer entertainment for
King George II.
Again, a big orchestra by
baroque standards was required.
About 50 players so this music could
be heard, would project outdoors.
Here's a slide.
Indeed a colored etching that
shows what these fireworks on
that evening looked like.
They were placed on barges in
the middle of the Thames River,
in front of what was Whitehall,
the center of the government.
The music for the show had been
premiered at a public rehearsal six days
earlier in the Vauxhall Gardens
on the other side of the river.
More than 12,000 people showed up,
which caused a traffic jam for
three hours over London Bridge.
Then the only bridge as we
saw in a previous slide,
then the only bridge going to
the south side of the Thames.
But what this all shows is that
Handel's music was hugely popular for
the rehearsal, there were no fireworks.
The music was the fireworks.
Anyway, let's listen to a bit of the end
of the music for the Royal Fireworks.
A minuet, the final dance.
I really like the performing
group that you're about to hear.
It's a combination of players.
Combination, we need
a lot of performers here.
A combination of players
from Fribourg Germany.
The Fribourg Baroque Ensemble and
actually we heard them earlier when they
played Bach's Brandenburg
concerto number five.
And combined with them
is the English group,
the orchestra of the age of Enlightenment.
I'll comment as we go.
[MUSIC]
Starting with repertoire of
natural trumpets, no valves.
So here's the minuet.
[MUSIC]
Notice that the tempo,
of course, is much slower.
[MUSIC]
And I would say that
the playing is a lot cleaner.
[MUSIC]
This was a difficult technique,
this clarino playing from the baroque.
Only specialists could do it.
[MUSIC]
Obviously overdid the oboes.
See the old in the middle
of the orchestra.
Authentic performance practice.
What we don't see here is a conductor.
The first violinist is conducting,
and that's correct.
[MUSIC]
There were no conductors standing and
waving batons in those days.
So the first violinist is conducting here.
He's very, very good.
[MUSIC]
The natural horns.
>> [APPLAUSE].
>> A wonderful performance of
the minuet at the end of the Music for
the Royal Fireworks.
Now perhaps I'm overdoing this distinction
between Bach the internal looking
perfectionist, and Handel,
the external-looking projectionist.
Someone who likes to get his music out and
about.
But there are two moments in looking at
the music of Handel over
the years that have caught my eye.
One appears in the Messiah,
in the famous Hallelujah chorus, where
he's setting up a typical four voice feud,
and we clearly hear the soprano and
the bass enter.
We always do,
because they're the outer parts.
But inner parts are more
difficult to hear.
So what does Handel do?
He combines the tenor and alto into one
voice to make sure that we hear it,
turning this into not a four part fugue,
as it perhaps it should be,
but into a three part fugue.
He wants to shine a light on that inner
voice to make sure that we don't miss it.
I don't know of a single
instance where Bach in
a fugue sacrificed ideal purity for
audibility.
So to speak.
There's another tell tale moment.
It occurs in the fugue of Handel that we
were listening to earlier in our quiz.
Let me show the music again.
This is a four part fugue, but
every time a voice enters,
Handle doubles it with another voice.
Again, to make sure that you hear it.
He doubles the alto,
which is the real entering voice we
see with the blue line there,
he doubles that with the soprano.
And then when the tenor comes in, he's
doubling that with, with the bass line.
Bach would not have,
Bach would not have doubled,
as we'll see on this next screen here.
Bach wouldn't have doubled that
alto line with the soprano.
He would have had the alto
start by itself, and
then it would have been picked
up by the soprano later.
Similarly he would not have doubled
the tenor line with the base line.
It's a small point, small point,
but I think it's an important one.
To summarize, maybe even to exaggerate,
the difference between Bach and Hendel.
Bach was an idealist.
Handel was a realist.
Handel really wanted to make
sure that you heard his music.