[MUSIC]
Now we come to Handel and opera.
As we said, Handel first came to London
in 1710 to make money composing and
producing opera.
The kind of opera,
then really the only kind of opera that
dominated the stage of Europe at
this time, called opera seria.
Opera seria literally,
serious opera, was just that.
It was very serious.
Having as a plot contained
in the libretto.
A story of Greek or
Roman kings and queens, or
gods or goddesses, or
larger than life heroes from antiquity.
In other words,
it was high end subject matter, and
that's what the nobility, or the upper
crust of the day, liked to see on stage.
Mirror images of themselves.
And of course because opera had started
in Italy all opera seria was composed
to a libretto written in Italian.
A literary person wrote the story,
the libretto and
then a musician,
the composer set it to music.
Wrote the score.
Opera seria was usually in three acts, and
it was long, usually about three hours,
including intermissions.
Handel's first opera seria for
London was Rinaldo of 1711,
about the loves of a mythical
classical figure of that name.
It was first performed in a London
theater with a long history.
The theater was first built in 1705
in the Haymarket section of London.
It was called the Queen's Theatre
because a Queen then reigned.
Then with the advent of George I, Hendel's
boss, it was called the King's Theatre.
And now it's called Her Majesty's Theatre.
Here we see various views of this
venerable theater over the centuries.
From Handel's Day in the upper left,
to a performance in the 19th century in
the bottom left, to how it looks today.
The shell never really changed but
the inside and
outside were continually refurbished.
And by coincidence it was here that
Andrew Lloyd Webber's Phantom of
the Opera was premiered in 1986.
Which went on to become of course
the most popular of all musicals.
More than 130 million
people have seen it live.
So From Handel's Rinaldo,
to Phantom of the Opera.
Anyway, like all baroque opera seria,
Rinaldo was made up of a succession
of recitatives and arias.
And among the arias, the most famous
has proved to be one sung by Rinaldo.
Lascia chi'o pianga.
Let me weep in my cruel faith.
Let's have a listen to it.
But a word before we do.
As mentioned before baroque opera is for
the high born.
The nobility.
And to be high born in a baroque
opera you had to have a high voice.
Whether male or female.
The hero or
the heroine had to have a high voice.
Either a soprano or a castrato.
The tenor, the high natural male voice,
the tenor hero really
didn't step on to the operatic stage until
later, not really until the 19th century.
So in Handel's Rinaldo, the role of
Rinaldo was sung by a castrato, but
because castratos are in
short supply these days,
indeed non-existent, Rinaldo was
usually sung by a male falsettist.
And that's what we're going to hear here.
In fact we're going to hear and
extraordinary falsettist,
the Frenchman Philippe Jaroussky.
When I first heard this voice,
I couldn't believe it.
It had a purity, a clarity, and
an accuracy of pitch that I thought
were astonishing, at least to me.
As one opera critic has said Jaroussky
has the sound of an angel, but
the technique,
the technical accuracy of the devil.
Let's give a listen to
this very special voice,
the French falsettist Philippe Jaroussky.
[MUSIC]
[INAUDIBLE]
am I picked for
freedom.
[MUSIC]
[INAUDIBLE]
a very slow triple meter.
Coming back to the opening phrase.
[MUSIC]
Cruel fate.
[INAUDIBLE]
[MUSIC]
Now in this period, in the Baroque period,
composers tended to write arias
in something called da capo form.
Well, da capo simply means
take it from the head.
So what you would have is
a piece in two sections.
An A section.
Then a B section in which the key changed,
here we'll see it change to minor and
the mood changed.
So we have an A section, a B section,
then the composer would simply write in da
capo take it from the top, and you'd
go all the way back to the beginning.
Now that seems to be anti dramatic, it
seems the stopper slowed down the drummer.
But it does give the soloist a chance
to reprise a lovely melody and
to add some vocal ornamentation
which was part and
parcel of the Baroque
process in this period.
So let's go on now, we're just going
to continue with the B section.
Shifting to minor the B
section of this da capo aria.
[MUSIC]
>> And here we enter the B section.
[FOREIGN]
>> Tempo increases, gets faster.
You can hear the shift to minor.
>> [FOREIGN]
>> Something
about my internal conflict rages and
in my suffering I pray for mercy.
>> [MUSIC]
>> There's the word pieta, mercy.
And back to the A section.
We've gone back to the head.
And you can hear the singer begin
to introduce ornamentation.
>> [MUSIC]
>> And
then the final singing of this phrase.
>> [MUSIC]
>> All ornamentation.
>> So what did you think
of that voice,
that falsetto's voice?
I find it captivating,
but not everyone does.
What do you think?
Send me an email.
But like that voice or
not, that's what the audience of Handel's
day paid its money for, paid to hear.
Beautiful music and a high male voice.
So this singing by Philippe Jaroussky was
a modern rendition of an opera by Handel.
But, let's use a bit of imagination to
pretend we're back in Handel's day,
listening to a production of
Rinaldo in the Queen's Theatre.
A few years back,
a movie called Farinelli,
did just that, tried to give us
a sense of what opera was like
when the castrato reigned
supreme back in Handel's day.
They created an imaginary stage and
an imaginary voice,
an imaginary castrato voice.
They actually synthesized electronically
the voice of a female soprano and a male
falsettist to come up with something
approximating a baroque castrato voice.
Let's watch a scene of this cinematic
creation of Handel's Let Me Languish.
>> [FOREIGN]
>> So here we are in the B section
of this da capo aria,
the same aria that we just heard.
You can hear the pitch is higher.
>> [FOREIGN]
>> Now the bass will
slide down,
back to the A section.
>> [FOREIGN]
>> Imitation.
He, of course, is lip syncing but
it's still a lovely sound.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Okay, so get ready now as he
begins to fold some notes and
pushes for extreme amount of time.
>> [FOREIGN]
>> Or perhaps
a bit over the top.
But there is much truth to this scene.
The castratis were renowned for
their capacity for long held pitches.
Maybe because of their bigger frame, or
the fact that they were using chest voice.
I'm really not sure.
But this ability to extend
the duration of the pitches
was part of the wow
factor of the castrato.
Anyway, with his opera,
Rinaldo, Handel had a hit and
gradually got more adventuresome.
Producing not just one occasional
opera but an entire season of opera,
and he did so
by means of a grand commercial scheme.
He set up what we in the U.S.
would call a private equity.
A privately held stock company.
Wealthy, knowledgeable individuals with
an appreciation of art were invited to
contribute money to buy a share of the
company, in this case an opera company.
And thereby, pay for
a series of operas each year.
The venture was called
the Royal Academy of Music.
It wasn't so much an academy
in the sense it was a school.
But it was royal in the sense that
the king and queen were investors.
Partners bought shares of the company and
they shared in the profits or
the losses each year.
This was capitalism in
early 18th century London,
where capitalism in the west
really got its start.
Well, Handel ran this opera company.
He chose the theater,
he chose the singers,
he set the pay scale for all
the employees, he composed the music, and
he rehearsed and
conducted all the performances.
Sometimes he enjoyed great artistic and
financial success and sometimes he didn't.
His most successful opera was Julius
Caesar of 1724 based on an episode in
the life of Caesar in which he pursues and
defeats his rival Pompey in Egypt,
but Queen Cleopatra,
in turn, conquers Caesar.
Or at least the heart of Caesar.
Through her beauty and through her music.
Let's hear a bit of
the central aria V'adoro,
Vadoro Pupille during
which Cleopatra attempts
to capture the heart to seduce Caesar
again through the beauty of the music.
We'll hear only a bit of V'adoro Pupille.
We'll pick it up with the return
to the A section of our da capo form.
>> [FOREIGN]
>> So
because we are back in the A section,
we are, of course,
hearing the great beautiful [INAUDIBLE].
>> [FOREIGN]
>> And to make this music even more
beautiful, Handel has required that two
orchestras accompany the singer here.
One is on stage, and one is in the pit.
>> [FOREIGN]
>> And as you can see,
Cleopatra is doing everything possible,
physically and
vocally to seduce Caesar,
who rests upon the stage.
>> [FOREIGN]
>> Well, Handel intended to write
in his opera, the most sensual,
maybe the most sensational music possible
so as to attract and hold an audience.
But as beautiful as Handel's music often
was, and we heard beautiful music here.
It sometimes wasn't enough
to hold his audience.
And this kind of opera was
hugely expensive to produce.
The annual salary of the leading
castrato would have been about $500,000,
roughly, in the money of today.
And this was just one singer in the cast.
Anyway, in most years Handel's opera
company actually lost money, and
in 1729 it went bankrupt, a victim of
high expenses and changing fashions.
Handel and the listening public
gradually turned away from opera and
to a more middle class.
A more populus genre of music, oratorio.
And that's where we too now turn.