[MUSIC]
Today we think of Handel, mostly, as
a composer, not of opera, but of oratorio.
Indeed what we think of as oratorio
was created almost single handedly
by George Frideric Handel.
But first of all where do
we get the term moratorium.
Well the word comes again
from Italian oratorio
which was a building for Christian prayer
and singing that seems to have gotten
started in Rome in the 1616, and
here we have a surviving example in Rome.
In oratorios, these places of singing and
praying, in oratorios such as this,
religious music was sung,
and Handel of course knew about it
because he lived in Rome for three years.
So when opera became more and
more unprofitable for Handel in London,
he started to write more and
more oratorios.
Not oratorios for worship but oratorios
for the theater, oratorios for money.
More Londoners would pay to hear oratorio
in theater than would pay to hear opera.
Indeed, opera and oratorio as conceived
by Handel had many similarities.
They were performed in a theater
before a paying audience.
They began with an overture,
were divided into three acts and
consisted mostly of recitatives and
arias; but there were differences.
First of all,
Handel's oratorios are in English.
Although done in a theater they don't
use scenery and costumes or acting.
The listener has to imagine
the drama in his or her minds eye.
Third, the plots are about events written
in scripture from the new testament but
most often from the old testament.
Fourth, voices tend to be less operatic,
less virtuosic, and
more along the lines of
good church singer voices.
And five, the populace in
the form of the chorus on stage,
does a lot of moralizing,
talks about what's going on in the story.
And thus the chorus plays a larger
role in Handel's oratorials.
Indeed, writing choruses was,
as they say, Handel's sweet spot,
his real strength writing these
choruses in his oratorios.
And sixth, and finally, oratorios appealed
to the increasingly numerous middle class.
Of course Handel's oratorio
Messiah is best known.
It was written in Dublin, Ireland.
Why Dublin, Ireland?
Well, in 1741,
Handel had the opportunity to write and
perform and entire season of
music 1741 and 1742 in Dublin.
So he rounded up some music and
he rounded up some instruments and
wrote some music, new and specific for
Dublin and off he sailed.
Actually he wrote Messiah
remarkably quickly in just three
weeks in September of 1741.
But the work wasn't performed
until April of 1742 because Handel
was waiting for the solemn week
of Holy Week right before Easter,
which he thought was an appropriate
time of year to perform Messiah.
Nowadays, we usually perform
Messiah right before Christmas.
After the Dublin performance in a theater,
Handel brought Messiah back to London,
re-orchestrated it, adding oboes and
bassoons and horns, and
performed it at a local orphanage for
charity.
The Foundling Hospital, and
actually parts of it are still there.
The playing fields of Coram and
the primary school are still there,
not far from Russell Square.
So here you see, the grounds of the
orphanage as it looked in the 18th century
to which Handel transferred Messiah, as
a way of raising money for this orphanage.
And here's the chapel, where Messiah
was first performed outside of Dublin.
First performed and here's the organ case,
for the organ that Handel himself paid for
at the end of his life.
So here for the first time,
again for charity,
Messiah was performed not in a theater,
but in a religious context.
Now rehearsals for these performances of
Messiah took place in Handel's house.
It doesn't look very large, but
it was a large house according to
the standards of the 18th century.
And it was located on a square in the most
prestigious section of
18th century London.
When Handel rehearsed Messiah, he did so
here, in his living room in effect.
Into this room,
numerous performers crammed to rehearse
the solo parts of the oratorio.
Now, the most memorable part of Messiah,
of course, is the Hallelujah Chorus,
which ends Part II of of the drama.
Messiah is in three parts, or three acts.
Part one the prophecy of Christ coming.
Part two, his passion and resurrection.
In part three,
reflections on Christian redemption.
So, it's part two it ends
with the Hallelujah chorus.
It celebrates Christ's
triumphant resurrection.
As you can see,
starting at the upper left corner there,
the artograph calls for two trumpets,
and on the second line,
two timpani,
which is actually quite unusual because.
Normally in a score of the mid
to late eighteenth century,
the timpani parts aren't written.
It's up to the drummer,
the drummer is more or
less free to fill in whatever
timpani sounds he wishes.
So we have to the two trumpets, and then
the timpani, and then the first violins.
Then the second violin's line.
And then the violas, their line.
And then the voices, the four vocal parts.
And then finally down at the bottom,
the bass part for the bass and
the basso continuo.
As you may remember when we studied
musical texture at the beginning of
our course.
We listen to the hallelujah
chorus as an object lesson,
demonstrating how a composer,
skilled composer, such as Handel,
can shuffle between monophonic,
homophonic and polyphonic texture.
Let me play just a bit of the beginning of
the Hallelujah chorus, but making a point.
That in Handel's day,
at least initially, in the 1740s,
the chorus and the orchestra was
very small by our standards.
Specifically in Dublin,
there was a chorus of 23 singers and
choir boys singing the soprano part.
Here's an example of that small but
very authentic sound from Handel's day.
[MUSIC]
A relatively small orchestra
Of about 20 harpsichord in the middle.
[MUSIC]
Chorus also of about 25, with choir boys
as you see singing that soprano part.
[MUSIC]
Handel died in 1759,
nine years after Bach.
And contrary to Bach,
who initially fell into obscurity,
Handel's posthumous reputation only grew.
By the 1750s, there were 50 to 60
singers at a performance of Messiah.
And then, more and
more singers were added.
By 1785,
it was not unknown to have 500 singing.
And, by the mid 1800s, in the low
thousands, Handel Festivals of the People,
as they were called.
Performances of Handel's oratorios became
something akin to arena oratories.
Here you see an engraving showing one
such performance at the Chrystal Palace
in 1857, with thousands of
volunteers in the chorus.
And this tradition of
everyone singing the Messiah,
Messiah singalongs endures
down to the present day.
So let's end our visit with Handel and
the baroque by
hearing not the Hallelujah chorus, we've
heard that earlier in our course, but
the end of the chorus that ends
the Messiah, that ends part three.
It ends with a giant fugue and
that's appropriate for Baroque music.
And it ends on the Hebrew word, amen.
So be it.
I'll comment as we go.
So, our fugue starts with the bass'
doubled with the double bass' and cellos.
And as the camera pans to the left,
[MUSIC]
The tenors have come in.
So you can see it's a large chorus.
Here come the altos.
[MUSIC]
And finally, the sopranos,
giving us the four voices of our
typical four voice fugue texture.
Now the first violins pick
up that same fugue subject.
[MUSIC]
Now, the second violins pick it up.
Now, a moment of homophony,
everybody singing together,
so the fugue has been broken off.
[MUSIC]
More homophony.
Now this is a very large group, and
you can see there in the continual,
we have a small Harpsichord, let it
point in fact the members here are so
great no body could really hear
those continuo instruments.
This is the larger, more modern approach
to a performance of Handel's Messiah.
The conductor here is Neville Marriner
[MUSIC]
>> Sir Neville Marriner.
>> [MUSIC]
>> And here we have polyphonic texture,
in effect the equivalent
of an episode in a fugue.
[MUSIC]
All polyphonic, but
playing motives from the theme,
rather than the theme itself.
[MUSIC]
Melodic sequences rising up.
Very much a modern performing group.
Notice the hand position on the bow there.
That's a modern 19th century style.
Okay timpani.
Trumpet.
A modern valve trumpet.
[MUSIC]
Building up to a huge climax.
We have two timpanis here.
The one on the left plays
the dominant pitch.
The one on the right timpanic and
as we drive to the climax here,
there's the dominant.
Notice this huge silence,
thundering silence.
[MUSIC]
A fitting end to the glories
of baroque music.