[MUSIC]
Have you ever noticed that when you turn
on your TV or watch an ad on the Internet,
or open a newspaper that you see such and
such a watch or such and
such an automobil, even a fancy villa,
advertised as having classical style?
What's that mean, it's a classic?
Well, maybe that that object
is a high end product.
That it has a sense of balance and
proportion, of purity.
Maybe a lack of clutter and
excessive detail that has caused it to
be appreciated over a very
long period of time.
Timeless beauty.
And this is true of high end western art
music, what we call classical music,
as opposed to the generally
beloved popular music.
Classical music, be it Josquin des Prez or
Bach or Mozart, even Wagner, or
Beethoven, Stravinsky, this is all thought
of as classical music with a lowercase c,
music that has been written down and
preserved for us over time.
Music that can be studied.
This broad general use of the term
classical, has this lower case c.
This term classical music was
first used in Germany in 1836,
and it first applied to the music
from Bach to Beethoven.
But gradually it got extended to mean
all notated art music from roughly
the year 1000 up to the present day.
Classical music with an uppercase
C subsequently came to mean more
specifically the music from
the 1750 to roughly 1820.
Haydn, Mozart, Beethoven,
and early Schubert.
So Classical music, with an upper-case C,
is a subset of classical music,
music with a certain style.
The style of Mozart, for example.
But what does it sound like?
Can you picture in your mind's ear,
the sound of Mozart?
Can you bring to mind the sound of Mozart?
Do you recognize Mozart
in the classical style?
Well let's find out.
Which is Mozart?
Let me play three pieces.
One of which is in
the classical style by Mozart.
Which is the one by Mozart?
Is it A, B, or C?
[MUSIC]
Okay, well, that's an introduction to A,
let's go on now to hear Piece B.
Is this Mr. Mozart?
[MUSIC]
Well, how about now this one,
Piece C, is this Mozart?
[MUSIC]
Okay, let's pause it there.
Well it's not A.
It chugs along with a kind of relentless
rhythm and the melody is one long stream.
This is music by Bach.
And it's not B.
The sound is way too big here.
There are large number
of brass instruments.
Trumpets at the end we heard,
trombones and horns earlier.
This means it's from the 19th century or
later.
This selection is by Richard Wagner.
So the correct answer is,
as you may have guessed, C.
Only violins are sounding,
the texture is very light,
no brass at all, the structure
melodically is very symmetrical.
Balanced phrasing here.
Well you've likely heard
enough of Mozart beforehand,
to know that C is indeed
the correct answer.
So you know already a bit about
Classical music with a capital C.
But what about architecture, which is the
building here from the Classical period,
1750 to 1820?
The one from the classical
period is the one to the left.
Even though, again,
we see the columns, the capitals,
the triangular pediment in the rotunda and
the classical windows.
The image to the right is
the original from Roman antiquity.
It's the famous Pantheon,
in Rome, of course.
The one to the left, again,
is Thomas Jefferson's library
at the University of Virginia.
The classical model is drawn upon here.
But they're both classics.
All right,
let's go now to Vienna, Austria.
Here's the Emperor's dancing hall
in Vienna where Mozart and his wife
danced and for which Mozart, Hayden,
Beethoven, they all wrote dance music.
Notice the windows here.
This is something that interests me,
windows from the classical
period 18th century.
Five panes of glass across, with a semi
circular lunette, divided light.
Now let's go to the concert
hall of my own Yale University.
Notice the windows here
are exactly the same.
And indeed, if I took a picture,
I might have done so
of a window in my own living room, I'd get
the same type of design, a classic design.
To make this point In another way,
let's look at this very classical building
constructed in the heart of Paris in the
18th century with its classical features,
and sense how wide-spread it became
in the United States in the 19th and
20th centuries as the US Capital and
one state capital after another was built.
So the classical era looks
rather conservative and
rather conventional, and
a lot of it stays with us today.
But it wasn't always that way.
There was political change and
political revolution came to France with
the French revolution and to North America
in the American Revolution,
with the Declaration of Independence.
And there were changes in fashion,
as you can see here on the screen.
The wig and the sword of
the gentleman of around 1750 and
the face paint and the beauty marks,
they all disappear.
Here's how Handel looked around 1750.
And then Beethoven half a century later,
replaced by a more natural,
less aristocratic look.
And changes were coming to opera as well.
Serious opera, opera seria, was being
infiltrated, if not replaced, by a lighter
kind of opera called Opera comique
in France, or Opera buffa in Italy.
It often had just spoken dialogue and
more tuneful melodies, not the lengthy
del capo aureos that we heard before.
And the plots in the librettos
showcased everyday characters,
a man-servant, a butler or a maid.
The slide to the left shows the famous
castrato from the mid 18th century.
And that on the right, a modern
recreation of how the barber Figaro,
in Mozart's, The Marriage of Figaro,
is often depicted.
Let's watch a portrayal of Barber Figaro
in a production with subtitles.
[MUSIC]
Okay, if you wanna dance.
Notice he's saying [FOREIGN],
the little count.
What is really said in
the vernacular is you little,
you can fill in the blank yourself.
It's a very dismissive
attitude toward his lord and
master on the part of Figero the barber.
[MUSIC]
I'll call the tune [FOREIGN].
Okay.
He begins to ape, mimic, poke fun at,
the fashions of the aristocracy.
[MUSIC]
La Capriola, Capriola was a dance step.
Actually a dance step of the aristocracy.
And if you wanna dance your step,
I'll call the tune.
[MUSIC]
Okay, maybe we'll pause it right here.
Well that kind of opera, subversive opera,
by Mozart is very different from high
flown Opera seria of the baroque.
The classical period,
while conservative architecturally,
was often revolutionary socially.
And sometimes revolutionary musically.
Mozart's opera Figaro was
premiered at a Viennese theatre,
one run by Emperor Joseph II.
But the Emperor's sister,
Marie Antoinette,
Queen of France, literally lost
her head in the French revolution.
That was just to begin just three years
after the premiere of Mozart's opera.
As you heard, there is tension, and
there is drama in this seemingly
serene music of the classical period.