[MUSIC]
All right, in our lest segment we
tried to differentiate between
the aristocratic baroque and
the more democratic classical period.
Admittedly all simplified a bit, but
differentiated in terms of architecture
dress and even social relations,
the tension between the aristocracy and
the middle class,
now let's focus on the music.
I'm going to play two pieces.
One of the Baroque era by Bach, and one
from the classical period by Mozart, and
you are going to differentiate
between the two.
We'll start with Bach's Air,
a slow song or
air, coming from a suite of pieces for
Baroque orchestra.
As we listen and
watch, I want you to think about the
characteristics of style in this music.
Let's focus on the first questions.
Okay, list of questions here.
What's the texture?
-
Monophonic, homophonic, or polyphonic?
Where's the melody?
What's the bass doing?
What's the pulse of the bass?
What is the mood of the music?
Does the mood change?
We'll watch a musical animation here
by my friend Steve Malanowksy from
Richmond, California.
Here we get both a musical score and
a graphic representation.
Obviously, we have four parts.
[MUSIC]
First violin, second violin,
viola and cello.
Cello double [INAUDIBLE] double basses.
Speaking of the double basses.
Knows what they're doing.
All the same beat plotting
along in 8th notes here.
Good example of a Baroque walking bass.
There's melody, well it's up above for
the most part but
sometimes the second violin joins
in to produce a composite melody.
[MUSIC]
Now they double basses work
double time to signify a repeat.
[MUSIC]
Has the mood of the music
changed in any way?
No, I'd say the mood is pretty much
the same from beginning to end.
Okay, let's pause this here.
What have we learned?
Well, let's take a look at a slide
that may help us in this regard.
What's the texture?
Is it monophonic,
homophobic or polyphonic?
Well, polyphonic, that's mostly the
composite of four lines going their own
way at one time.
So I'd say mostly polyphonic texture,
whereas the melody.
Well, the melody is mostly in the first
violin, but sometimes in the second.
What's the bass doing?
Well, as we heard, it's moving along,
almost relentlessly in a steady beat.
What's the pulse of that bass?
Well, as we saw, eighth note but
always the same,
a good example of
the baroque walking bass.
And finally whats the mood of the music?
Well, does the mood change in anyway?
With the mood I would submit
is generally serene relaxed,
i feel secure when I listen to this.
Does it ever change from beginning to
end of this about five minute piece?
No, it has the same ethos
from beginning to end.
So what have we learned here?
Well, we might have learned that
the strings dominate here in the Baroque.
The melody spins out in these long,
sometimes asymmetrical phrases.
That late Baroque music is full of
polyphony that has a very strong bass.
It has consistent rhythmic
patterns driving it forward and
a consistent mood or ethos,
ethos from beginning to end.
Okay, good.
Now, let's take a piece by Mozart.
Again, we're going to grab only
forty seconds or so here but
that's really all we need, and let's focus
on a few questions that will help us
identify the difference between late
baroque and classical musical style.
Our choice here is the opening
of Mozart's symphony number 25
written in 1773 when he was 17.
Wait a minute,
[LAUGH] hang on here a minute.
Symphony number 25?
25 symphonies and he's 17?
That's impossible.
No, that's Mozart.
He was a genius, and more than any
other genius, he was a prodigy and
able to do all of this
at a very young age.
Well, let's look now at
our Mozart questions.
How do we recognize a classical
piece by Haydn or Mozart?
What's the texture, monophonic,
homophonic, polyphonic?
Where is the melody?
What's the bass doing?
What's the pulse of the bass?
What's the mood of the music?
Does the mood change?
So let's now go to a, a video again.
This also by Steve Malinowsky.
It doesn't have a musical score with it,
only the graphics.
And we may be stopping along the way.
[MUSIC]
Okay, I'm going to stop it right there.
At the outset, we heard.
[MUSIC]
And it sounded like a lot
of people were playing.
Actually, it was just one melody line,
everybody playing what's
called at octaves.
So this, although it might sound complex,
is actually just a good
example of monophonic texture.
And then as you see on the screen there,
you have up above a melody.
That's why these animations are useful.
Now you have up above a melody and
have these green blocks underneath.
Well, the green blocks are chords
that are supporting the melody.
So we have an example of
homophonic texture here.
So let's go back to the beginning.
Let me go back to
the beginning that'd be great.
And we're going to pick
it up with that's fine.
We'll start right here, and
in a moment up will come the music
with our monophonic texture.
[MUSIC]
Yeah, back to monophonic
they're all together, in chain.
[MUSIC]
Little bit of polyphony here,
a little bit more activity here.
Notice here back to homophony but notice
how very soft sweet oboe takes over.
Chord, chord.
Okay, we are going to stop it right there.
There we go, we are going to pause
it right there, and go back and
ask us, yes, some questions again
about this piece by Mozart.
So let's go to our first slide here and
just removed what's the texture,
monophonic, homophonic, or polyphonic.
Well, let's see what we had in this piece.
Yep, monophonic and, homophonic,
very little polyphonic here.
Where's the melody?
Well, again, it's always on the top,
more so on the top,
it was virtually all on the top,
always in the first violin.
What's the bass doing?
Well, I didn't hear much bass there,
I just heard melody.
Melody is much more important
here in the classical era.
Then, the bass is,
what's the pulse of the bass?
Well, the pulse of the bass,
difficult really to find.
Difficult to identify because
the pulse is in the melody.
What's the mood of the music?
Well, it starts out as you heard-
[MUSIC]
All that syncopation is very agitated,
veryanxious, but
in the course of just those few seconds,
it changes when the oboe comes to the.
[MUSIC]
The relaxed oboe lines has become very,
very lyrical by that point.
So what do we conclude from this,
by way of classical music?
How might we recognize
a piece by Hayden or Mozart?
Well, listen for
a string dominated style, style.
One in which occasionally
solo woodwinds will pop up.
Melody is generally shorter,
often in units of two, or four, or eight.
It's symmetrical, it's balanced,
the texture in classical
music is mostly homophonic.
You get a melody plus
chordal accompaniment.
And the texture generally is lighter.
The bass is much less obvious
compared to baroque music.
Rhythmic patterns, well, there's more
of a stop and go process at work here.
I always think of this as something
like the slinky that I had as a kid.
It would race to the next step and then
sit there for awhile and then race, sit
there, so it's much more unpredictable,
the rhythmic patterns in classical music.
And as we heard, the mood can change
within the same piece or movement.
There is no constant ethos here.
You can start in agitated fashion,
become very lyrical within
a very short period of time.
Okay, well, that's some music by Mozart.
[INAUDIBLE] And
the composer of this music,
Mozart, was born in Salzburg,
but moved to and died in Vienna.
Haydn was born in Rohrau, Austria,
Beethoven was born in Bonn, Germany,
but moved to and died in Vienna.
What do we detect from this pattern,
don't go to Vienna?
No, on the contrary,
do very much go to Vienna.
So let's go to
Vienna and see
what's going on.