[MUSIC]
What's your favorite city?
New York?
Paris?
Las Vegas?
I know New York City, two of my children
live there, and three work there.
I love Paris,
I spent a year there as a student and
it's my favorite city, I think.
Maybe tied for first place in my mind
is Vienna, which I've visited and
done research in on five occasions.
Vienna, more than any city of the world,
is the capital of western classical music.
Mozart, Haydn, Beethoven,
Shubert, Bruckner, Brahms, Wagner,
Mahler, Schoenberg, Richard Strauss,
Johann Strauss, they all lived
there at one time or another.
How did it come to be that
Vienna came to be called, and
still is called the City of Music?
Well, follow the money.
Follow the excess capital.
In the late 18th century Vienna was
the capital of the Holy Roman Empire.
It was also the last and
the largest city before you
hit a vast agricultural region to
the east, running all the way to Russia.
The fiefs and
the states were run by aristocrats
who came in from the countryside,
in from the cold, during the winter,
where there wasn't much agriculture to do.
For entertainment they
didn't go to the movies or
watch TV, they went to the opera and
the theater, and to the casino.
Yes, there was a casino there,
indeed there were several casinos there.
And they sponsored music and
dancing in their palaces.
There were more aristocrats per capita in
Vienna than in any other city in Europe.
What did it look like?
Well, here's a view of Vienna in
the mid 18th century by Canaletto.
Population of about 200,000.
The fourth largest after London,
Paris, and Naples.
About one in every 175 persons was
an aristocrat, a very high percentage.
And one out of about 200
persons was a music teacher.
A lot of, a lot of aristocrats [LAUGH] and
a lot of music teachers.
Because people wanted to make music in
their homes, and be taught how to do so.
Actually this view of Vienna in the 18th
century is very similar to
the way it still looks today.
On the right you see a Benedictine
monastery there, right corner.
And then in the center slightly to
the left, the Schwarzenberg palace and
the Charles church all
the way to the left.
And in the center distance
the cathedral of Saint Stephens.
Now here we are right in
front of Saint Stevens.
Actually we're right
behind Saint Stevens and
it was here that Mozart's
funeral was held in 1791.
This engraving dates from 192,
and here we are now
in the center of, I can see lets see
if I can get my pointer to work here.
We're going to move over the center
of the city, there's Saint Stevens.
And here is one of the main
drags here in Vienna,
the Graben and here is
the [INAUDIBLE] going out this way.
Current opera houses over here,
Mozart, he lived,
you can,
let me see if I can pull my cursor back.
He lived in a house here in
[INAUDIBLE] strasa at one point.
Another house,
apartment over here on the [FOREIGN].
And where else?
So Mozart lived over here for
a time, Haydn lived out in
the suburbs in the 1790s.
He bought his piano here,
pianos at Kernig showroom here
in Beethoven lived out here in the
Pasqueladie, house on the ramparts, and
right here in the center, this is
the Hofburg, where the emperor lives.
So let's take a look at that.
Here's the emperor's dwelling,
the Hofburg in the 18th century,
with the troops drilling out there.
And here's how that
same plaza looks today.
Hofburg, the Imperial Palace
as it is today.
About a block from there
was the Burgtheater.
Run by the Emperor.
And you can see a show going on and many
of Mozart's, operas were premiered here
and many, public concerts
were given in this theatre.
Now, we said that Vienna was the city
of the aristocracy and here is
just one of the houses of the aristocrats,
this is the Auenshammer Palace in Vienna.
These were patrons of Mozart.
Here we have an engraving of
the Esterhazy Palace in Vienna.
The Esterhazy were the patrons of Haydn.
Here we have another Canaletto painting,
showing on the left,
the Palace of the Lobkowitz.
And it was here that Beethoven's Eroica
Symphony was premiered in 1803 in
that house sponsored by the Lobkowitz.
Even today as you walk around Vienna
on a fine summer evening you can
hear the strains of music from public
concerts coming out of those windows.
All right, let's review here quickly.
Vienna, city of music,
capital of the old holy Roman empire,
fourth largest city in Europe,
the cosmopolitan center,
attractive musicians from throughout
Europe, aristocratic patrons, but not only
aristocratics attending these concerts,
but public concerts developing as well.
Both public and
aristocratic concerts in the Burgtheater.
There were both
aristocratic performers and
amateur performers and
they all needed musical teachers.
And the fact that there were so
many aristocrats and so
much money to be spent in Vienna.
This became the center of what we
call the Viennese classical school.
Classical style epitomized in
the music of such composers as Hayden,
Mozart, Beethoven and Schubert.
They created the Viennese classical style.
So that's a brief introduction to Vienna,
city of music.
Let's go on now to meet Haydn and Mozart.