[MUSIC]
Well, his first name was Franz.
Franz Joseph Haydn.
But more often in his day.
And even today is referred
to just as Joseph Hayden.
Hayden along with Mozart and
Beethoven and a very young Shubert,
were the main figures as we hit scene
in the Viennese classical school.
The heart of classical with a capital C,
the heart of classical music.
Hayden came from very humble lineage.
Indeed his was something
of a rags to riches story.
His father was a wheel maker
in a farm town south of
Vienna with very little formal
education or musical training.
The Hayden family came from here is Rora.
South, South Eastern Austria, at the tip
of the arrow that you see on the screen.
And here's the house in
Rohrau where he was born.
When he was about six,
the choir master of the cathedral of
Saint Stephen in Vienna was going
around the country recruiting.
Scouting for voices and
he heard young Haydn sing.
And he brought him back to
Vienna to be a choir boy in
the cathedral school and church.
Here's a modern view of that imposing
church, where Haydn stayed until his
voice broke in his late teens, stayed
there about ten years and thereafter.
He earned a living as
a freelance musician.
Violinist, keyboardist,
organist at various churches.
Jack of all musical trades.
And he took music lessons as
well to further learn his craft.
Eventually in 1761, almost 30 he
got a job as the Kapellmeister.
Director of Music as we have seen before.
Director of Music at the court of
the family of the Esterhazy who were
arguably the most wealthy and most
powerful of all the nobles in Austria,
save the Austrian royal family,
the Emperor's family itself.
So here's a slide of the Esterhazy Palace.
Very large as you can see and imposing.
Where they stayed during
most of the winter.
This is in downtown Vienna.
But the principle residence
of the Esterhazy was here in
the town of Eisenstadt South of Vienna.
Let's turn to a user
friendly Googlemap here.
So we got Vienna,
we're going south-southeast of Vienna.
And here is the town, city about
35,000 people today of Eisenstadt.
And here's how the palace, the Esterházy
Palace looked in the 18th century.
And heres how it looks today,
hasn't changed that much.
Haydn's house, which he owned in
the 1770's was about a block away.
You can see here his
modest kitchen too and
Haydn would walk to work to
the entrance of the palace everyday.
And here's that entrance right
there in the lower center and
as we look through it,
think about Haydn walking through there,
we see in the distance the Haydn Cafe,
well actually of course the Haydn Cafe
wasn't there in Haydn's day,
this is just another tourist sham in
a sense of the sort that we saw in
Bach's But notice also here in the
Esterhazy Palace the Esterhazy theater.
You can how big this palace and
how this, big this theater was.
They're very large,
indeed, very magnificent.
But this was not the only
palace the Esterhazy had.
Not just the one in Vienna and
not just the one here in Eisenstadt.
Prince Nikolaus built another
one farther to the south.
So let's take a look
again at our Google map.
Vienna, Eisenstadt, and
now down to Eszterhazy.
In the small town, actually it was more or
less in the swamp when
Nikolaus Eszterhazy started to
build this palace called Esterhaza.
And here's how it looked
in the 18th century and
here's how Esterhaza looks today.
Now when Haydn entered the service
of Nicolas Esterhazy in 1761,
he was required to sign a contract,
just as Bach had signed a contract.
By way of an oath to
the town fathers in Leipzig.
As you'll see when I read this
contract it's very restrictive.
Hayden like every musician of
the day was very much a servant,
not the grand artiste.
So let me read this contract for us here.
He and all the musicians
shall appear in uniform, and
the said Joseph Haydn shall
take care that he and
all members of the orchestra follow the
instructions given, and appear in white
stockings, white linen, powdered,
and with either pigtail or tiewig.
He said, Haydn,
shall be under obligation to
compose such music as his Serene Highness
may command, and neither to
communicate such compositions to any
other person nor allow them to be copied.
But he, the prince, shall retain them for
the absolute use of his Highness, and not
compose for any other person without the
knowledge and permission of his Highness.
Well, the work of art created
by the composer belonged not to
the composer here as we see,
but to the patron, the prince.
And Haydn was a servant.
As a matter of fact,
there's a portrait of Haydn in the blue
servant's livery of the Esterhazy princes.
Let's take a look.
Here it is,
it's actually owned by my colleague and
friend, Dan Harts who teaches.
Now Professor Emeritus at the University
of California at Berkeley.
But that's Hayden in livery's dress.
Now here's Hayden composing.
Dressed up here in sort of the business
suit of the day composing at a piano.
You see in his right hand a pen.
With which he wrote down his ideas and
his left hand which he
tried them out on a piano.
And the piano to the right, as you can see
happens to be one built by Hontang Walter.
And it was used at the Esterházy court,
and
believed to have been
played on often by Haydn.
I point this out really only to give you
a sense of how small these pianos were
in Haydn's day,
weighing less than 200 pounds.
Okay, to review here with
our trusty Google map.
The Esterhazy were actually active at
three sites during the nearly 30
years Haydn served Prince Nicolas.
In, first of all, they were active
in Vienna, active in Eisenstadt and
active out in the boondocks,
Esterhazy eventually,
prince Nicholas died, and
Haydn was given a pension.
And he moved back into Vienna.
But very quickly he then set off for
London where he'd been offered a high
paying commission to write a collection of
symphonies, 12 of them,
that were to be performed in London.
And this, he did on and off living
in London between 1791 and 1794.
These were performed in
the Hanover square rooms.
So as you can see by this map the arrow
points to the Hanover square rooms but
if you look just slightly below that
red arrow you see Brook Street and
who died on Brooks street?
None other, then George Frideric Handel.
So there is Handel only about
a block from where Haydn was
performing his symphonies in
the Hanover Square Rooms.
And here is how from this
slide those Hanover Square
performing quarters looked
in the 18th century.
This is something of a bellwether,
a mark of the importance of
the growing number of large
concert halls at this time.
And this is how this same hall
looked in the 19th century.
Under normal conditions it would
accommodate about 900 listeners.
But for a performance of a Haydn symphony
in 1792, 1,500 were squeezed in.
Well, eventually, Haydn retired and
returned to Vienna to become
the toast of the town.
Here, we see a painting of a famous event.
Vienna, 1808 the great hall
of the University of Vienna.
Antonio Salieri conducts a performance
of Haydn's Oratorio the Creation.
In honor of the aging Haydn who is
sitting in a special chair as you
can see the arrow pointing to it there
at the bottom center of the screen.
Everyone of any import had turned out
to hear the music of the aging master.
But because of his success with
the London symphonies Haydn ended up
with a ton of money he made
from those London symphonies.
About 1.2 million dollars
in money of today.
And with it he bought,
bought a splendid new house in what
was then the suburbs of Vienna.
Now it's more or
less in the central district.
It was here that he died in 1809.
The last music he played was
a melody called the Emperor's hymn.
He played this melody everyday on
the piano before retiring at night,
and there's a story behind this melody,
in 1796 the armies in Napoleon Bonaparte
had invaded the Austrian Empire.
The French under Napoleon already had
their national anthem, the Marseillaise.
The English had God Save the Queen but
the Austrians had nothing.
So, Haydn, being the most and
famous, most important musician of
the day, was commissioned to write a hymn,
a song, a anthem in praise of the emperor,
Emperor Franz Joseph II.
It came to be called the Emperor's Hymn.
Here's the melody part.
And I'll try to,
I'll swing around here and play the tune.
[MUSIC]
And then that repeats, next phrase.
Last phrase.
[MUSIC]
Well Hayden was so pleased with that
melody that the next year 1797 he
worked it into the slow
movement of a string quartet.
Now remember a string quarter is
usually written in four movements.
Fast first movement.
Slow second movement.
Minuet in trio fast finale.
And of course it's played
by four instruments.
First and second violins, viola and cello.
And, Haydn used this slow
second movement of a string
quartet to show case
his new Emperor's Hymn,
he used it as the melody for
a set of variations.
Thus we have a movement in theme and
variation form, with the emperor's
hymn providing the theme.
Haydn more or less single handedly
created the string quartet,
music with four more or
less equal parts, equal players.
As you see here.
Here we are in variation two .The
cello has the emperor's theme.
As you can see by the blue arrow.
Let me see if I can play
the cello part here.
[MUSIC]
>> Okay, that's the cello part.
Now let's listen to this movement
of the Emperor's Quartet.
The slow second movement in the Emperor's
Quartet based on the Emperor's Hymn.
And it's performed here by
a young string quartet based at
the New England Conservatory
of Music in Boston.
The Quartet.
As we start off.
The theme is played by the first violin.
[MUSIC]
Phrase one is the theme.
Notice how the first violinist
is shaking that left hand
to play bravado to give a richer
timbre tone to the pitch,
[MUSIC]
Phrase two
In phrase three.
Texture here.
Is homophonic they're all basically.
Playing chords again.
Tune plus chords.
Repeated that third phrase.
And of course we've got first violin,
second violin,
cello and viola on the far right.
[MUSIC]
Okay.
First variation, who's got the melody now?
Can you tell?
Well, the second violin does.
As the first violin plays counterpoint
against it, second phrase.
And generally speaking the counterpoint is
going along in rapid moving 16th notes.
[MUSIC]
Third phrase, obviously the cello and
the viola don't play at
all in this variation.
So it's just melody.
Los accompany.
Variation two.
Clearly the large cello has.
The Emperor's Theme here.
[MUSIC]
The other three instruments providing
accompaniment with light counterpoint
[MUSIC]
Second phrase.
Final phrase.
[MUSIC]
And repeated that final phrase.
Okay, we're going to stop.
And as we proceed with the next slide,
we'll see that we stopped exactly
where the cello was playing.
[MUSIC]
And so on we go, but we can also
see again on this screen the equal
distribution of the music, typical of
a classical string quartet invented
by Haydn with The Emperor's Hymn in
the cello part in the base part.
Alright, let's review,
let's take a moment to review the life and
music of Joseph Haydn.
[INAUDIBLE] He's a representative
of the classical Viennese school of
the late 18th and early 19th century.
Educated musically for
the most part at the Cathedral of, of St.
Stephen in Vienna.
His patron was the Esterhazy.
He was taken in their service in 1761.
Served them for 30 years.
In 1790, he received a pension and went
into something akin to phased retirement.
But still went off to London,
where he composed his 12 last symphonies,
the London symphonies.
Partially resident there in
the year 1971 through 1795.
They were performed in
the Hanover Square Rooms, as we saw.
The Emperor's Hymn was
created in the mid 1790s
as a way of honoring the Emperor
of the Holy Roman Empire.
But notice,
today that's actually the national anthem
of both Austria and Germany.
So every time Germany and
Austria does it occasionally but
most often Germany wins a medal at the
Olympics or the Germans win the World Cup.
What you're hearing a national
anthem is actually the music of
Joseph Hayden that he himself subsequently
incorporated in the Emperor's Quarter.
And, again, Haydn more or
less invented this genre of the quartet.
Which, to paraphrase,
paraphrase the famous Johann Wolfgang von
Goethe is a civilized conversation
of learned and, indeed, equal.
Participants.