[MUSIC]
Of all the characters that I've
ever run into, or read about.
Picasso, Michelangelo, Shakespeare,
Isaac Newton, Einstein.
There are two that stand out in my mind.
To Leonardo Da Vinci and Mozart.
Fascinating personalities, and geniuses of
the short that you just can't understand.
You can't fathom how
they did what they did.
And Mozart is very special.
I think he's the most interesting of all
characters to stud because he was just
that, a real character,
an endlessly fascinating personality.
And we know a lot about Mozart because,
fortunately,
he lived in an age before emails and
text messages that we could delete.
He was a very social creature,
a real party animal.
And he liked to communicate,
he liked to communicate in his music, and
you like to communicate in prose.
And to do so in the 18th century
you had to write letters.
And he did,
more than 600 of them surviving.
Flowing between him and members of
his family, mostly with his father.
Now Beethoven is a special piece
of work too, another character.
But if you wanna study a genius
Mozart is the mother lode of genius.
Genius as prodigy, genius as creator.
A genius who burned bright and
then died young.
That was Mozart.
But let's start.
Let's take a look at his life.
Here's a map of Salzburg.
Then a city of about 20,000.
Today a city of more than
ten times that number.
Owing mostly to Mozart and
the Salzburg festival and
all the people that come there,
and the commerce that it supports.
So, let's take a tour here,
through Mozart's life.
Here's the Mozart's, Mozart Birthhouse,
as you see there in Salzburg,
up in third floor, there.
And I'm going to point out here,
nearby, only about two blocks away,
is the famous St. Peter's Abbey, and those
of you who are fans of The Sound of Music,
that's where Maria was actually a nun
at one point, was a Benedictine house.
Anyway, let's stay on
point here with Mozart.
Mozart was a child prodigy,
and you see here a minuet,
Minuetto del Signoro [FOREIGN]
Mozart 16 December 1761.
So he was five years old
when he wrote this minuet.
It's actually in the hand
of his father but
nonetheless he was five when he
was writing this kind of thing.
But because father Leopold realized that
he had on his hands a genius and
he was an enterprising sort.
He packed up the entire family and
off they went to Vienna where he showcased
the boy's extraordinary
skills to the emperor and
the empress, empress Maria Theresa and
here's a set of clothes,
suit Given to young Mozart by
the empress Maria Theresa.
So after a visit to Vienna
back they are in Salzburg and
then they set off for
a three year grand tour of Europe.
They're heading actually they swing
up into the North countries but
they land initially in Paris and
here they again play for the aristocracy.
This is Father Leopold at the violin.
Sister singing, and
Wolfgang at the keyboard.
Notice where his feet are.
They don't come close
to touching the floor,
shows you how young he was and,
in a way, how diminutive he was.
Well, after a year in Paris,
off they go now to London and
here in London,
Mozart writes his first symphony.
[MUSIC]
So this is Mozart's first
symphony dictated to
his sister in London at the age of 8.
Okay let's move on.
As the Mozarts were moving on.
So after London they went back to the low
countries and came back down into Paris.
Stayed again in Paris and
then made their way home after three years
to this triumphant tour to Salzburg.
And then rather shortly there
after off the Mozart's go
in to Italy down through Verona and
over to Milan.
Here's a portrait of Mozart.
[MUSIC]
The age of about 17,
playing again the G minor symphony
that we listened to a bit before,
and saw the music animation before.
Now at age 25, in 1781,
Mozart moves to and of course,
we have seen this slide
before that's Vienna.
Here we are in the center,
the center of Vienna again with the St.
Stephen's Cathedral.
And this has indicated where
Mozart spent a great deal of
time around this cathedral and
he was actually, his body was actually
displayed in state there in
the chapel where the blue arrow is.
And then his funeral was given and
the body was buried here.
Out to the South there
is that monastery again.
Out to the South in St. Mark's cemetery.
We can't be sure it was said that
Mozart was buried as a pauper,
that's really not the case.
85% of the general population were
buried in these mass graves for
reasons that we need not go into.
So there was Mozart buried in the St.
Mark's Cemetery.
And legend had it that an eagle-eyed
grave keeper was paying attention to
where Mozart was actually buried and dug
up his skull and in the course of time,
that skull has made it's
way back to the Mozartiem.
Is this really the skull of Mozart?
Can we learn anything about Mozart or
how he thought or
how he composed on
the basis of this skull?
Is this really Mozart?
We don't really know although people are
going over into the Saint Sebastian church
on the other side of the river
from the Geburtshaus and
into this cemetery where many of
the relatives of Mozart are now buried,
looking for samples of DNA that
they can match with that skull.
Well, this is taking us rather far afield
here so let's get back to Mozart's music.
I'd like to start with a scene
from the film Amadeus.
It's a spectacular film.
It won eight Academy Awards, I think.
The Mozart that you see in Amadeus often
Is not really true to the way Mozart was.
But sometimes it is and
it's a fascinating and
very insightful representation in so
many ways.
So sometimes Mozart behaved this way,
often times he didn't.
But I'd like to start with
my favorite scene here.
And it's a scene in which Saluary,
a supposed arch enemy of
Mozart has received a raft of
scores from Mozart taken surreptitiously
by his wife and being shown to Saluary.
And Saluary is astonished because,
as he turns the pages of these, he
realizes that this is all completely new,
unknown music, and it shows no sign
whatsoever of actually being worked on.
Sort of miraculous conception here, so
let's watch this really very special,
beautiful scene from Amadeus.
>> These are originals?
>> Um-hum.
[MUSIC]
So this is Mozart's
music from the Flute And
Harp Concerto playing in the background.
[MUSIC]
>> Astounding.
>> Mozart's symphony
now in the background.
>> It was beyond belief.
These were first and only drafts of music.
But they showed no
corrections of any kind.
Not one.
[MUSIC]
He had simply written down music
already finished in his head.
Page after page of it.
As if he were just taking dictation.
>> And this is the mass in C minor here.
[MUSIC]
Soprano solo.
>> And music.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Finished as no music has ever finished.
Displace one note, and
it would be diminishment.
Displace one phrase, and
the structure would fall.
[MUSIC]
>> It was clear to me.
That sound I had heard in the Archbishop's
palace had been no accident.
[MUSIC]
Here again was the very voice of God.
>> Okay, well, we'll pause it here.
It's a beautiful scene.
But is it really accurate?
Is it really accurate, did Mozart's music
really come down directly from God,
untouched almost by human hand?
Well, here is an autograph of Mozart.
It's actually the same music
we were just listening to,
it is the autograph of
the Kyrie of the C minor mass.
Do we see much in the way
of correction there?
No, virtually none.
As we turn over to the next page, yes
there is a smudge in the third line and
a smudge down toward the bottom.
He was changing notes here.
The ink wasn't completely dry and
he was still able to correct
it before that ink did dry.
Here's the most extreme case of
Mozart working on something,
correcting something, that I know of.
It's from the C Minor Piano Concerto, in
which he wrote the right hand of the piano
once, and then twice, and
then a third and indeed a fourth time.
But this is exceptional because the norm
is what we find here in
the D minor piano concerto.
D minor piano concerto, which it looks
like more or less Mozart is in fact
just streaming this all out
with very little labor.
Well, let's delve into Mozart's
music a little more deeply here.
Let's focus on a movement of
a piano concerto, written 1785 for
Vienna, performed in the theater,
the that we had seen earlier.
It's called the Elvira Madigan Concerto
because it was used in a film some 30 or
40 years ago of that name.
We can get a sense of how it's
put together by watching another
animated video.
This again by Steve Malinowski.
Steve has color coded this
one with the accompaniment.
Just these chords.
[MUSIC]
[INAUDIBLE]
Listen to this
[MUSIC]
That note, it's a sharp.
It gives it a intensity that [INAUDIBLE]
[MUSIC]
Here comes the second phrase,
balanced phrase
[MUSIC].
Here comes another one
of those dramatic notes
[MUSIC],
there.
[MUSIC]
[INAUDIBLE] Just a moment of tug at your
heartstring.
Melody up above dives down low.
Melody repeated now, up a step.
Dives down low.
[MUSIC]
Now, listen.
To a melodic sequence.
[MUSIC]
This one's falling down.
Melodic sequences that
fall down tend to relax.
This is very beautiful,
it's also very relaxing.
[MUSIC]
All of the accompaniment is very simple,
the melodies ever so simple.
[MUSIC]
Concluding phrase.
We think we're coming to a cadence.
But he surprises us,
[MUSIC]
there, by going to a minor chord
instead of the expected meter.
He's gonna do a fly over,
starting to land again.
And finally this time he
lands back on the tonic.
[MUSIC]
At which point the pianist comes in.
Notice again how simple the music is.
[MUSIC]
First phrase.
Inflection and the harmony is just
these plunking little chords and
triplets underneath.
[MUSIC]
Answer,
inflection.
[MUSIC]
Okay, maybe we'll pause here.
So this music has the simplest
of musical textures.
But sometimes Mozart wrote
a very complicated texture.
So, again, you can make the most beautiful
things out of the simplest of materials.
Yet at the same time, he had the capacity
to write very, very complex music,
and sometimes a very complex
music will get him into trouble.
And for this, let's go to
another video clip from Amadeus.
Here we have the Emperor, and
he's about to congratulate Mozart for
the successful premiere of
The Abduction from the Seraglio.
He thinks it's great, but not perfect.
>> Well now, Mozart, a good effort.
Oh, well, decidedly that.
An excellent effort.
You have shown us something,
Quite new tonight.
>> It is new, it is, isn't it sire?
>> Yes indeed.
>> So then you liked it?
You really liked it sire?
>> Well of course I did, it's very good,
of course now and then just now and
then, it seemed a touch [CROSSTALK]
>> This is based on a true event.
>> Well, I mean,
occasionally it seems to have
>> An exchange between the emperor and
Mozart
>> Oh, how should one say?
How shall one say directly?
>> Too many notes, Your Majesty.
>> Exactly.
Very well put.
Too many notes.
>> I don't understand.
There are just as many notes, majesty,
as are required, neither more nor less.
>> Well my dear fellow,
there are in fact only so
many notes the ear can hear
in the course of a year.
>> [LAUGH] Alright, let's pause it here.
Too many notes, too many notes.
Well, what's at issue here?
Well let me see if I can reify this
by means of an example Let's turn
to an image,
musical example of the Jupiter Symphony.
And here we have a symphony in the last
movement of which Mozart strung out
over a period of about seven minutes,
five different musical themes.
We've got a first theme, and then a first
theme part two, and then a transition
theme, and then a second theme, and
a second theme part two, and so on.
What we don't realize is, and
maybe Mozart didn't realize this himself
as he was proceeding, was that all of
these themes could actually be combined.
So here are the themes.
[MUSIC]
That's theme one.
Theme three.
[MUSIC]
Theme four.
And theme five.
[MUSIC]
Okay, could those five
all possibly go together?
Well, that's what Mozart does.
We hardly hear it, but
it's very dense counterpoint.
It's sort of a contrapuntal
fireworks here.
Let's give a listen by
means of another musical
animation created by Steve Malinowski.
Theme one.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Four.
>> Two.
You know, all of so
I can't keep track of them all at once.
[MUSIC]
Okay, let's pause it there.
So that's an introduction
to the music of Mozart.
Which can be sublimely simply or and
at the same time devilishly complex.
But stick around For
a Mozart bonus, if you will.
Another favorite scene from Amadeus,
here Mozart is about to be
presented to Emperor Joseph II.
Salieri has written an entry march
in honor of Mozart's arrival,
his first presentation at court.
The Emperor, who studies piano with
Salieri, has played this piece only once.
Only once.
And now on this one hearing,
Mozart will play it back.
The point of this fictitious but
very truthful scene is to show two things.
One that Mozart is an extraordinary talent
he has an extraordinary musical memory.
And that two he can Improvise,
riff on any piece of music
given by anybody at any time.
And that capacity sometimes
makes other people mere mortals,
such as we, very jealous.
>> If you want,
it's already here in my head.
>> What?
From one hearing only?
>> I think so Sire, yes.
>> Show us.
>> Okay, this is Salieri's March.
Supposedly by Salieri.
[MUSIC]
Of course, this actor Tom Holka is
not actually playing this keyboard.
This keyboard has no strings on it.
They patch in the music later.
[MUSIC]
>> The rest is just the same, isn't it?
>> Salieri begins to understand
that the game is up.
>> It doesn't really work, does it?
[MUSIC]
Did you try?
Shouldn't it be a bit more?
Or this.
[MUSIC]
This, yes.
>> So now in Amadeus we have an theme out
of The Marriage of Figaro, sung by Figaro.
Here it goes.
[MUSIC]
[LAUGH]
>> [FOREIGN]
>> So that's an introduction to Mozart.
An extraordinary human being, character,
who wrote equally extraordinary music.