[MUSIC]
Remember we said in an earlier
session that the term classical music
was coined in the 1830's and
applied generally to high art music.
Running from roughly
Bach through Beethoven.
High art music sounds a bit snobby, and
indeed it is, and was, in the sense that
this music was generally music for
the upper middle class and above.
The aristocracy, nobility, whatever.
And it was music that was written down and
could be studied, so
if you were a learned high class dude or
dame this was your kind of music.
This was the sort of music
that you enjoyed listening to.
Everyone else in the 18th century was
listening to the equivalent of pop music,
unwritten, unstudied, folk music.
Another thing that happened at this time,
early 19th century,
music started to be thought of as art.
Again a high art and
not merely entertainment.
What do I mean by that?
Well up to the time of Beethoven all
music even what we would we call
classical music was disposable,
it was entertainment.
Entertainment that the listener
could pay attention to or not.
When they went to a concert,
audiences expected to hear new music.
Why would anyone want to hear old music?
Indeed, before 1800,
the concert was as much a social
event as it was a musical experience.
With rare exception, people talked,
drank, ate, played cards, flirted, and
wandered about, as you can see here.
Dogs ran freely on the ground floor and
armed guards roamed the theater
to maintain some sense of order.
At the blue arrow there,
you can see someone selling wine and
at the blue arrow to the right
they're selling fruit.
Several of the people aren't
even looking at the stage, but
they're turned around talking
to the people behind them.
This was sort of like going to
a football game, or a wrestling match.
Of course, this sometimes infuriated
Mozart when the audiences didn't listen,
and once he had a hissy fit in Paris,
in a high end salon when this happened.
But even Mozart wrote pop music,
entertainment music.
Not only in his operas but
also in his music for music boxes.
The sort of thing where you open
up the lid and the music plays.
This was actually the only recorded music,
the only kind of recorded music
that they had in those days.
He also wrote music, for a music box,
it was again to be played here
in a wax museum, sort of amusement park,
amusement house.
Bach, even Mozart too, wrote music to
played in coffee houses and cafe's.
Here in downtown Vienna we
see the Frauenhuber Cafe.
It's actually the oldest surviving in
Vienna and it dates from the 18th century.
Both, Mozart and Beethoven ate here from
time to time as the plaque on the front,
let me see if I can point to it here.
Here we go underneath the sign and
here's the street sign,
Gosse and here is the plaque.
It says that both, Mozart and
Beethoven had their music performed here.
Now when we go inside,
you can see that this by our
standards is a rather smallish cafe.
Well, by the standards of
the 18th century, it's not.
Another place for music where the general
public could go was the court theater.
Here of course, to hear opera, but
also symphonies and concertos.
But the middle class was allowed
to go here too, not just nobility.
As long as you were properly dressed and
could pay the admission fee, in you went.
There were also newly emergent
music only concert halls.
Halls just for music, no theatre.
We've seen one of the earliest of these
in London, the Hanover Square Rooms,
actually one large room.
Here again,
we see the Hanover Square Rooms,
from the outside as it was
in the 18th century, and
then as we go inside the Hanover Square
Room, as it looked in the 19th century.
Today much pop music is
performed in casinos.
Garth Brooks,
Celine Dion in Las Vegas casinos.
I've heard Sting sing at
the Mohican Sons Casino in Connecticut.
Why the casino?
Well that's where
the people with money are.
And as Willy Sutton once famously said,
that's where the money is.
And that was true from Mozart's day too.
Here's the casino as it
looked in the 18th century.
It's called the Mehlgroube,
in a painting by Canaletto.
Mozart premiered some of his most
famous compositions in this casino.
Now, here's how it looks today.
It survives as the Ambassador Hotel.
You can stay there and this is
the way the central room looks today.
It's not large, but
Mozart would hire this hall.
He'd hire the orchestra, write all the
music, have his piano carried over there,
sell tickets.
Anyone with the money to buy
a subscription series could go in and
hear Mozart's music in this casino.
And don't forget,
music was also performed in private homes.
Chamber music, of course, ti was called.
Here we see the outside of
Mozart's apartment from the 1780s.
Now as we go inside,
this is the room in which Mozart and
Haydn played string quartets together.
Again, this very room in the year 1785.
Now you have to visualize here Mozart and
Haydn and
Ditters playing Mozart's string
quartets in this very room.
Now that's of course not really Haydn and
Mozart there.
But you have to use your imagination and
if you do so, you get the idea.
So the era of Haydn and Mozart and
Beethoven, around 1800,
is important because
things begin to change.
Music was becoming more middle class,
more public.
And a Canon of Music was developing.
A select repertoire of
pieces began to emerge.
Our favorites of Bach and Handel and
Haydn and Mozart and Beethoven and
early Schubert.
Our earliest musical museum
of the classics played in
room such as we just saw.
Listeners entering this early
music museum, theater or
public concert hall increasingly
came in order to hear the classics.
Tried and true favorites and they brought
with them certain expectations as to how
music ought to sound.
They had expectations
with regard to genre,
what type of piece they were hearing and
the form that it would follow.
Let's see how this plays out.