[MUSIC]
When you go to a concert, where do you go?
A bar?
Football stadium for a rock concert?
An opera house?
Where you go, the venue,
determines what you hear.
Blues, grunge, rock?
Hip hop.
Beethoven.
Tchaikovsky.
Wagner.
In the classical era, as we saw,
you'd go to a private home
to hear a string quartet, but usually to a
theatre to hear a symphony or a concerto.
Let's look now at some of these genres,
in terms of musical forms,
mood, and even tempo.
So we're gonna start, again, with genres.
As you can see,
we've got the genre of the symphony.
It's played by a symphony orchestra.
Actually, that's why we call it
a symphony orchestra, because this thing,
this performing group, the orchestra, most
frequently played a thing called, a genre,
called a symphony.
So we call it a symphony orchestra.
The performing group of a string quartet,
well,
it played this thing called a string
quartet, a genre called a string quartet.
Of course,
a concerto is played by an orchestra, and
usually a soloist fronting that orchestra.
Sonata?
Well, sonata could be writing for
piano, or for
another instrument such as the cello or
violin accompanied by a piano.
Now, the four previous genres that
we've looked at here, of course,
are all instrumental.
There was a fifth, opera, and
we'll discuss that as we proceed.
So let's move on now.
We're going to look at how this works,
starting with the classical symphony and
the string quartet, beginning with,
well, let's get down to the bottom.
We'll start with tempo.
Notice that we have,
with the symphony and the string quartet,
four movements, fast, slow,
lively, and then fast at the end.
As to mood, well,
the first movement's serious, substantive,
yet also at a fast tempo.
Second is a contrasting movement.
It is oftentimes lyrical and tender.
Third is a bit lighter,
more elegant, sometimes spirited
if it's a case of a scherzo.
But more normally dense like
in the spirit of a minuet.
And then, finally, a bright lighthearted,
sometimes humorous farewell.
A finale, the last movement.
As to form, we see that the first movement
is almost always written in a form that
we'll spend a great deal of time on,
the sonata-allegro form.
Second movement can be in ternary form,
sometimes in theme and variation form,
sometimes in rondo form.
Third movement, a minuet or a scherzo,
is almost always in ternary form.
And the finale can be sonata-allegro,
theme and
variations, rondo,
occasionally even in fugal form.
So those are our form, mood and tempos for
the symphony and the string quartet.
Let's go on now to look at
the concerto and the sonata.
Here, as you can see,
that sort of middle-ish
dance movement has been removed leaving
us with tempos of fast, slow, fast.
The moods, however, remain the same.
Sort of serious for the first movement.
Lyrical and tender for the second.
Bright, uplifting, happy for
the third and final movement.
As to form,
we're keeping our same forms here.
First movement sonata allegro form.
Second movement can be any one of several.
You can read those there.
Same thing with the third movement,
the finale.
Any one of several.
All right.
Let's look now at a couple of real
examples here, and
we're going to turn to a slide
that foregrounds Mozart's famous
Eine kleine Nachtmuzik and
Haydn's Symphony Number 94,
written in 1791 but premiered in 1792.
The surprise symphony.
And again, you can see the tempos
of the four movements for
the Eine kleine Nachtmusik,
the four surviving movements for this.
Sonata-allegro, always the first here.
Then rondo happens to be the form,
slow rondo happens to be
the form of the second movement.
Ternary form for the third movement.
And rondo, but
this time a fast rondo for the finale.
The surprise symphony, again,
sonata-allegro in primary position there.
Theme and variations.
We'll hear that in just a moment.
The famous slow movement
of the surprise symphony.
We have a minuet and trio in ternary form.
And, finally, the finale.
This time, also in sonata-allegro form.
And now, for a review of terms.
High art music.
Well, as we said,
something that is written and studied and
usually involves a degree of music theory,
it is learned music as we had indicated.
Venue.
Very simple idea here.
Simply the place of performance.
Canon.
Well, a canon is a standard repertoire.
You can have canon in literature.
You can have a canon in art.
You can have a canon in music.
A standard cohort.
A publicly accepted works of art.
Genre.
Well, that's a very simple idea.
Simply means type or kind of music.
Form.
Well,
that's a little more difficult to define,
but a sequence of auditory units
that can be identified and
separated in terms of the thing itself,
a repetition of the thing itself,
a variation of the thing itself,
a contrast with the thing itself, and
perhaps a return to the thing itself.
All of these auditorially create
musical form just the way
that items in space visually can
create form in architecture.
Okay.
Let's turn to some music now,
music that demonstrates
what we've just learned.
[MUSIC]