[MUSIC]
Now let's work through some of
this classical musical forms.
Starting with ternary form, which we first
met I gave an example with Beethoven,
in our introductory
session on musical form.
Remember Beethoven's Fur Elise?
Ternary form has been around
ever since music, really.
Ever since recorded musical time.
At least since the 9th century.
It produces A, B, A musical form,
or home, away, home.
Here's a Mozart sonata
that uses ternary form.
The middle movement of K545.
K stands for Ludwig von Kochel,
who was a 19th century German
musicologist who gave us a chronologically
list of the pieces of Mozart.
This sonata in principle is
the 545th piece the Mozart wrote.
And this one was written
by piano teacher Mozart.
He composed it for his beginning students.
You know the first movement,
which is written in sonata allegro form,
by the way.
But let me remind you how it goes.
[MUSIC]
And so we're going to turn
to the second movement here.
And I'll just talk off the music for
awhile.
So, here's the slow
contrasting second movement.
It happens to begin in ternary form.
[MUSIC]
That's the opening.
Notice in the second movement,
both here in the second
movement [SOUND] and
in the first movement [SOUND].
That's called Alberti bass.
Just a little decoration.
It's a kind of fingerprint of the music of
the classical period because it only comes
in during the classical period and
disappears with the classical period.
So we have our opening theme
here with the Alberti base.
You just take [SOUND] a chord and
turn it into a [SOUND] triad, like that.
It's kind of a funk base
[MUSIC]
Of the 18th century.
Easy, simple way of making things sound
more complex than they actually are.
In any event, here we are,
ternary form, beginning.
[MUSIC]
That's our opening idea, A.
[SOUND] And, it ends here.
Now, at the end, of A,
suddenly he picks it up and goes here.
[MUSIC]
Well, that's a different key.
We were here [SOUND].
Now we're up here [SOUND],
and we have a different idea.
[SOUND] Eventually,
he works his way back here.
[SOUND] And we're back in.
[MUSIC]
All right, so let's take a look
at what we've seen so far.
Let's go on to the next slide.
So, here we are in the B section again
where you picked it up and moved.
[SOUND] And here's our contrasting
B that you see on the screen there.
[MUSIC]
And eventually he works his way back
[SOUND] to the large A that you see.
[MUSIC]
A couple of things I want to
call your attention to there.
Did you notice there, the bottom system,
at the first blue arrow
where we have this.
[MUSIC]
Did Mozart do there?
[SOUND] What kind of scale is that?
[SOUND] Just to give it
a little bit of extra zest.
Yes, it is in fact a chromatic scale.
[MUSIC]
Every note of the scale
is being used there.
Then we're over here at the star.
[MUSIC]
That's a particularly
poignant moment there.
[MUSIC]
He could've done that.
Could've written it that way or
could've written it.
[MUSIC]
But he chose to do this.
That chromatic inflection again.
So it's sort of typical of Mozart.
To, give a little bit of extra
spice to his music by means of
chromatic inflection.
But the main point here,
of course, is ternary form.
A, B, and A slightly varied here,
or home, away, home.
So, that's a quick review
of ternary reform.
Ternary reform is much
like the more expansive
sonata allegro form
that we'll now explore.