[MUSIC]
All right now we come to the mother lode
of musical form, the big ticket item,
the King Kong of musical form, whatever
you want to call it, sonata allegro form.
Why is it so important?
Well because it's the most
frequently used of the classical and
romantic era forms and it opens most
multi-movement classical genres.
It's the form that begins a symphony,
a string quartet, a concerto or a sonata.
Indeed we get our term sonata
allegro form from the sonata.
Let's go back to the slide of
the concerto and the sonata.
Sonatas begin with
movements that are fast.
So the term sonata-allegro
is taken from this process.
First movements in sonatas went this way.
They were fast and
they went according to this form, so
we call it sonata-allegro form.
Sonata-allegro form has much in common
with ternary form as you'll remember from
our previous segment,
ternary form is A B A, home away home.
But now, let's see how it's fleshed out,
how it's expanded into
sonata-allegro form.
Sonata-allegro form as you can see,
like ternary form has three parts,
exposition, development, recap.
Home, away, home.
First theme in the exposition.
Within that exposition
the first theme then moves
by means of a transition that
modulates to a new second theme and
then ultimately a closing theme,
that exposition can be repeated.
Then we go on to the development section.
In the development sections,
almost anything goes.
The theme can be varied.
It can be taken apart,
decomposed, if you will.
It can be reassembled in
imaginative sorts of ways.
Generally speaking with regard to texture,
we'll have more polyphony
than anything else in the development
section as the music is heard, and
heard against itself in imitations.
And it frequently moves through many
different keys by means of modulation.
Ultimately, as you can see almost in
the middle of our diagram there, and
I suppose we should point out in passing
that it's in this middle of the diagram,
in the middle of the development section,
that most of the most intense
tension is experienced.
But that gradually resolves itself
into this portion of the form called
the retransition,
which leads us back to the recapitulation.
Now the recapitulation is
a very simple concept.
We come back to the tonic key.
We come back to the first theme.
So we're back home.
Home, away, home and thereafter
the themes return in the same sequence
as they did in the exposition except
now the key remains in the tonic key.
As you can see also, there are two
optional parts of sonata-allegro form.
There's an introduction.
And generally speaking,
introductions are slow.
They sort of give us a question,
in essence.
We have a slow introduction
with puzzling chords.
Where is this going?
This mysterious loop beginning.
What sort of journey am I,
the listener, going to pursue?
How will all this play out?
And the second optional part is the coda.
Now the word comes from Italian, tail.
Codas can be long or short.
Beethoven liked to write long codas
because he liked to continue to vary
the material there.
Mozart tended to write shorter ones.
But generally speaking, what a coda
does is throw out a harmonic anchor.
It engages only very simple harmonic
progressions, usually just tonic dominant.
Bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum, bum.
As if to say we are at the end.
So this a general template.
It's a very useful template but almost no
piece follows sonata-allegro form exactly.
This diagram is an ideal, but
let's hear a real example now.
The opening, the first movement
of Mozart's famous serenade.
Eine kleine Nachtmusik, or A Little Night
Music, again the first movement, and
of course it's written
in sonata-allegro form.
All right.
So let's listen to the first theme
of Mozart's Eine Kleine Nachtmusik.
[MUSIC]
A little syncopation there.
And it's sort of counterpoint to this so
maybe we've got a couple little
ideas in here, A, B and C.
[MUSIC]
Agitation.
Movement.
[MUSIC]
Here comes the bass.
Pause.
So we had a cadence there.
De de de de.
That would be the end of
the musical phrase, a cadence, and
the music actually stopped.
I like to think of this in
terms of almost a drama.
We've got a change of scene here,
there are some characters have gone off.
The stage is now clear and
other characters are gonna come on.
So, what character is gonna come on?
Well a more lyrical second theme.
I'm gonna play just a bit of it for you.
[MUSIC]
What about this?
Is this a conjunct melody?
Obviously it's descending.
Conjunct or disjunct?
Very conjunct.
Actually, it's just
running down the scale.
Now we don't have time because
this music is going by so fast.
We've got our skippy opening
theme going around like that.
We don't have time to sort
of write down all those X's.
So maybe just yeah.
[MUSIC]
And maybe something like that.
So this is our first skippy theme.
Our second theme, [SOUND],
has a nice sort of fall to it.
Okay, here's the second theme.
[MUSIC]
Repeat.
Now, closing theme already.
[MUSIC]
Okay let's just pause it here for
a second.
[MUSIC]
What's the most noteworthy
aspect of that theme?
[MUSIC]
What do you think?
What would you remember about that?
How would you graph that?
Yeah.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Okay, yeah, it starts out with
[MUSIC]
and then it's really conjunct, right?
Because it's just staying on one pitch
level, sort of the ultimate conjunct
joined to the point that it's a unison
pitch, da, ti, ti, ti, ti, ti.
So I'd remember that just like this idea.
So our closing theme, da, di,
di, di, da, da, turn, da, da, da,
da, almost the woodpecker idea, sorry.
But think of that kind of,
da, da, da, da, da, da.
Or maybe a machine gun, whatever sort of
silly analogy you want to construct
to help you remember that.
Okay, so here we are,
almost at the end of the exposition.
Let's listen now to the end of
the exposition and then we'll stop.
[MUSIC]
Okay, so we're gonna stop there.
Now, on this recording what do you think?
Well, I think reasons for
time, let's go ahead and
we'll advance it up to the beginning
of the development section.
So now we should listen to
this whole complex once again.
We're not gonna do that,
we're gonna proceed here.
We're gonna go into
the development section and
it's kind of fun the way Mozart
starts the development section here.
[MUSIC]
Let me ask you this, we started here.
The development begins higher or lower?
[MUSIC]
Yeah?
>> Lower.
So, he's dropped down to the dominant.
He's now in the dominant.
[MUSIC]
And if he continued as he had,
That's what he would have done.
That's not what he does, however.
[MUSIC]
He's sitting here.
And he ends up there.
So we get this sort of dissonant shift,
and it's a signal.
It's like the composer holding up a sign,
development, time for the development now.
Okay.
So something, we've shifted.
We were sort of slapped in the face,
telling us we're at
a new point in our form.
A new section in our form,
the development section.
So as we listen to this,
we'll hear Mozart move quickly
through some lots of different keys.
I wouldn't be able to tell
you what keys they are.
I really wouldn't.
But I do know that he moves
through different keys.
Then we will hear a re-transition start.
But here is my challenge to you, and why I
started putting all these things up here,
which theme does he
choose to develop here?
Kind of interesting.
Does he go with the first theme?
[SOUND] or the [SOUND] or
the [SOUND], so which one?
[MUSIC]
Okay, stop it right there.
Now he's all the way, first of all
what's the answer to the question?
Which theme did he use here?
We're now at the re-transition,
almost finished this short development,
which one did he use?
Who thinks they know?
Raise your hand.
Elizabeth?
>> The closing theme.
>> Used just the closing theme.
[SOUND] So nothing but the closing theme
in this short Development section.
Now we are at the re-transition.
And you're going to hear
the violins come down.
[MUSIC]
But if I could sing a harmony,
maybe we should all sing it together,
we'll be singing
[MUSIC].
It's the implied baseline.
[MUSIC]
And it's gonna go bum.
Back to the tonic.
And when it goes bum, then that first
theme is gonna come back in here.
So let's listen to Mozart write
a retransition and I'm going to sing
the implied or then sounded dominant
that's gonna lead to the tonic.
[MUSIC]
All the first theme material coming back.
Nothing new.
[MUSIC]
There goes our bridge now movement.
And he just cut it short.
The first time he went bum, bum bum bum.
Bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum, is what the bass did.
This time he just stops the thing and
stays in the tonic key.
And then the rest of the material
will come back in in the proper order
in the tonic key.
All right we need not hear that,
let's go on now to the coda and
we're just gonna listen generally
to what happens in a coda here.
Typical coda with Mozart.
[MUSIC]
Tonic.
Bum.
Bum Bum.
[MUSIC]
It's almost stereotypical right?
You could have written that.
Even I could have written that.
Not so hard but
as I say it's just a load of bricks
to bring this thing to a conclusion.
That's a wonderful piece, so elegant,
so succinct, and so pleasing
in the sense that it conforms to
sonata-allegro form in all particulars.
Hooray!
It does exactly what our diagram,
our model, says should happen.
But here again we listeners can
experience the music in two ways,
for form and for emotion.
We mustn't forget, as we focus on form,
that the real message here is in
the emotional content of the music.
Balance, elegance, grace, harmony,
these are just a few of the sensations
that Mozart leaves with us
by the end of this movement.
This piece is a staple at Starbucks.
It's popular, and for good reason.