[MUSIC]
Introduction to Classical Music,
Session 13.5.
Theme and Variation Form,
A surprise From Haydn.
>> We've already talked about how
Josef Haydn spent most of his
professional life working in and around
Vienna for the wealthy Esterhazy family.
And how, while in semi-retirement he
went to London, where between 1791 and
1795 he created and
performed his last, and
most would say, his best symphonies,
the 12 London symphonies.
Actually, Haydn wasn't alone in this.
Mozart and Beethoven also had negotiations
with musical entrepreneurs in London,
to go to London.
But none of these actually
came to fruition.
But Haydn did go to London, and
as we have seen, his concer, concerts were
performed in the Hanover Square rooms.
And Haydn, like Mozart in Vienna,
sold tickets from his apartment.
Here we have, remarkably, a surviving
ticket from one of those concerts.
How many of you keep your concert tickets?
As you can see,
the concert was given in the Hanover
Square rooms on the 3rd of May, 1792.
The cost was a half guinea, which by my
rough calculation is about $60 of today.
But compared to good tickets of say,
the New York Philharmonic or
the Chicago Symphony Orchestra,
that's about the same, oddly.
I looked it up, and
the top ticket prices for
the New York Philharmonic
ranged from $65 to $118 each.
Now if you wanted to buy a ticket in
London for one of Haydn's concerts,
you'd have to go to Haydn's house on
Great Street, which still exists.
Notice that this ticket was numbered 280,
and
that Haydn himself had signed it, as you
can see down there by the bottom right.
For some of these concerts,
he'd sold as many as 1,500 tickets.
One of the 12 symphonies
Haydn premiered in London
was his symphony number 94
called the Surprise Symphony.
Why?
Because there is a surprise baked
inside the second slow movement of
this four movement symphony.
Let me play the theme on the keyboard.
[MUSIC]
Well just funning you there.
[LAUGH] You know how it goes.
[MUSIC]
On the tonic.
Then, it proceeds, this fashion.
[MUSIC]
So we have a very simple melody.
It's triadic.
It goes this way.
[MUSIC]
And then the dominant chord.
And then.
The crashing down
the chord in that fashion.
So we have a simple melody and then the
crashing dominant chord and because this
is, this particular theme is binary, we
have the a section and then the b section.
[MUSIC]
Which we just played.
So, two very simple ideas.
So that's the theme that Haydn created.
Very straightforward.
But very straightforward themes lend
themselves very well to theme and
variation's form.
The simpler the musical model, the more
you can dress it up as Hayden does here.
But, the most famous moment of
this tune is that crashing chord.
Why did Hayden do this?
Add this surprise chord at the beginning
of this, this lovely theme here.
He did so, he tells us,
in his memoirs, written in the last
year of his life, 1809, he did so.
So it was to execute, in effect,
to bring off a publicity stunt.
As he said, quote, to make a debut
in London in a brilliant manner.
So we're going to listen now, indeed,
we're going to watch
this surprising movement.
What you'll see is a collaboration
between Stephen Malinowski,
a music animation machine and myself.
Actually Steven does
most of the work here.
He's the real brains behind the operation.
But I asked him to take this movement and
create visual symbols that made it easy
for us listeners to track
the whereabouts of the theme.
And alterations of that theme,
and add markers that allow us to see
where we are in the musical form.
Hope you like what we've created.
Okay, so I've asked Stephen to, every
time the theme appears, the basic theme,
that's always going to
be color-coded in red.
And you'll have different size
symbols indicate duration.
Starts very quietly.
texture, we have a melody and simple
chords in the bass parts underneath.
Repeat, of course, and here we are.
Binary form repeat of the a part.
[MUSIC]
You can see what's going to happen
where a bright light coming your way,.
[MUSIC]
Yeah, a binary form we go to the second
and final part the b section.
[MUSIC]
Melody in the violins.
Now repeat.
The repeat is varied, because as
you can see in the blue up above,
we have woodwinds added.
[MUSIC]
Now they're playing in unison,
it's a violin.
[MUSIC]
First variation.
And it's a counter point.
[MUSIC]
Up above now it kind of
brings in the flute.
[MUSIC]
Now this is an exact replication
counter point violin.
[MUSIC]
Melody in the lower strings but
counterpoint.
[MUSIC]
in flutes.
Violin [INAUDIBLE].
B section.
[MUSIC]
First violins play counterpoint,
second violins, melody.
[MUSIC]
B is repeated,
[INAUDIBLE]
violins.
[INAUDIBLE] And now, unison,
monophonic texture, everything together.
And, of course, surprising.
It's not in minor.
A sudden harmonic shift.
That was neat.
[MUSIC]
Now here's a again, now in the minor.
Harmonic again.
[MUSIC]
Now like development in the development
section of the symphony,
it's not an allegro, it really has
a development section stuffed in
the middle of this piece in binary form.
[MUSIC]
See how complex it is.
Lot of things going on.
Now this is close to a re-transition,
with the aim to simplify things,
clear it out and
get you ready for something.
And we're led back to.
[MUSIC]
Our a theme is the note
values being doubled.
You can hear them up
there in the woodwinds.
[MUSIC]
A is repeated.
Woodwinds alone here, at least
woodwinds being featured up above.
The theme is quietly underneath.
[MUSIC]
New rewriting of b,
melody sneaking up in the violins.
[MUSIC]
Same material, but now the texture
is enhanced by means of supporting
accompaniment underneath, that you
see there in the green and yellow.
[MUSIC]
Okay, full texture here.
Still homophonic texture but
notice how many parts we have playing but
notice all the verticality,
indicating chords.
Homophonic texture.
[MUSIC]
Now, part of the tune is all
the way down in the basses.
[MUSIC]
Simply playing with the b theme.
Well, we can see that something's
going to happen here.
It's probably going to be loud and full.
[MUSIC]
Not much theme here.
More fanfare than theme.
Now the theme comes back [INAUDIBLE]
parts.
Now a transition, again, as you would
have in the Sonata, Allegro Four.
It's just heading to a point of stasis,
rival.
But with a rival like that,
it's unstable, it wants to go somewhere.
[MUSIC]
It goes back to just snippets of
our theme in the form of a coda.
[MUSIC]
Reminiscences of our theme.
Notice here, all, all, all tonic.
Whoops, haven't quite got there yet.
Here we go with all tonic.
Here's all tonic.
[MUSIC]
Wow, very instructive.
Very clever, if I do say so myself.