[MUSIC]
In case you haven't noticed,
among the classical composers,
my favorite is Mozart.
Admittedly, Beethoven powerfully
affects me, as he does almost everyone,
but to me Mozart is special,
as a composer and as a human being.
So that's why I've chosen to devote this
session to three classical masterpieces,
all by Mozart.
Why Mozart, what's special about Mozart?
What makes his music extraordinary?
Well we'll talk about that,
we'll even conclude with that by way of
a review at the end of today's session.
But having decided that Mozart alone is
worthy of an entire session in our course,
which Mozart to choose?
Well of course I said to myself Craig,
what are your favorites?
So, I mulled that over for a while,
and distilled the list to three.
The D Minor Piano Concerto, the opera
Don Giovanni, although Figaro is oh,
oh, oh so good, and
finally, the Requiem Mass.
And then I realized something,
hey, you know what?
All three of these works
are in a minor key, indeed,
they are in the same minor key.
Now even in Mozart's day,
all keys did not sound exactly the same,
ee hadn't quite arrived yet
at equal temperament.
C minor had a slightly different
sound to it than D minor,
which had a slightly different
feeling to it than E minor, and so on.
Again, this had to do with the way
instruments were tuned in Mozart's day.
So all these pieces do have
a particular character to them.
They're not only in minor, which has
a somber feeling to it already, but
in D minor, which was for Mozart,
was the demonic key, a key of evil,
the key of Hell.
So today, we're going to visit
through our three masterpieces,
the dark side of Mozart.
Our first piece is the piano
concerto in D minor, K466.
Now, remember K with Mozart
just stands for Kochel.
In 19th century, musicologists who
compiled this lists of pieces by Mozart in
chronological order,
K.466 dates from early 1785.
And don't forget that during the classical
period, the concerto grosso, a type of
concerto featuring a number of soloists,
we saw one by Vivaldi and one by Bach.
The concerto grosso is generally
replaced by the solo concerto,
a genre in which a single soloist
played harmoniously with, and
in competition against,
the full orchestra.
Mozart composed the D Minor Piano
Concerto, one of the 23 that he wrote,
for a series of concerts that he
was giving at the casino in Vienna.
Now you remember the casino,
here's Canaletto's painting of it,
at the blue arrow there, and
here's the inside again.
Remember, it was Mozart's job to organize
the concert, round up the performers,
conduct, sell tickets, service soloists,
have the piano forte brought over
there to the casino, everything.
The audience consisted,
really of only about 150 to 200, but
they were mostly aristocrats, so Mozart
could charge high prices, which he did.
At one concert alone
earlier on in his career,
he made four times his
father's annual salary.
In other words, he made about $120,000
in money of today, in just one night.
Actually, Mozart's father,
a stern looking Leopold that we see here.
Leopold Mozart happened to be in
town that February of 1785, and
he came to this concert in the casino, and
heard the piece that we're about to hear.
And he described it as, quote,
a new and very fine concerto.
So new in fact, that there wasn't
time to rehearse the finale.
The last of the three movements
the orchestra just had to sight read
the finale,
just wing it at the performance.
Mozart himself conducted the concert,
but conducted seated at the pianoforte,
which he of course played
as soloist in the concerto.
We'll listen to a performance
of this in a moment, but
first, this next slide makes
a couple of important points.
Notice first, the woman as soloist.
There were a number of female
keyboard virtuosos in Mozart's day,
maybe we should call them,
more correctly, virtuosas.
Mozart taught one of them, Barbara Ployer,
and he knew another one Victoire Jenamy,
and he wrote concertos for
both of these women.
So seeing a female keyboard virtuosa,
in this day, wasn't in any way unusual.
Notice also that the lid is taken
off entirely from the instrument,
that's simply for better resonance.
Notice also, that people are talking
while the performance is going on, and
that a dog is walking around the room.
Music here again isn't so
much art as it is, music as entertainment.
Now let's take a look at a slide
of Mozart's own piano, and
I hope you can appreciate from this photo
taken in the Geburtshaus in Salzburg,
that this instrument, as with all
pianos of this day, was very small.
Mozart's piano had only 61 keys on it,
not the 88 of today's keyboard.
It weighed exactly 187 pounds, not the
1200 pounds of our modern concert grand.
This again is not a replica
of Mozart's piano,
it is in fact Mozart's actual piano.
Which brings us to an interesting point,
which would you rather hear,
Mozart's music played on Mozart's piano,
or Mozart's music played on a big,
powerful, modern grand piano?
We'll give you a chance to
choose here in just a minute.
To do so, let's turn to a performance
by pianist Steven Lubin.
[MUSIC]
Now he's playing on a replica
of Mozart piano, and
you can see that his
touch is very light and
that the keyboard sound is rather smaller,
light keyboard action, light sound.
[MUSIC]
Mozart's music, Mozart's instrument,
rewards fast and light playing.
[MUSIC]
Of course variations of Twinkle,
Twinkle Little Star.
[MUSIC]
Okay, that's probably enough of that.
We're about to hear Mozart
on a modern grand piano, but
before we do, let's think about the piano
concerto as Mozart conceived it.
Just as Haydn was more or less the
inventor of the modern string quartet, so
Mozart was the father
of the piano concerto.
He set out the structural
framework of the piano concerto,
one that lasted into the romantic era,
here it is.
Mozart developed a stereotypical approach
to the first movement of the concerto.
It goes by several names, concerto form,
double exposition form
Are the two most common.
Double exposition form is a good name for
this form because there are as
you can see, two expositions.
We have one exposition as we had in
sonata-allegro form development,
recapitulation.
But now we have another exposition
added at the beginning.
The first exposition allows the orchestra
to present most of the themes by itself.
The pianist will add a couple later on,
and do so all in the tonic key.
Let's listen now to a performance of
this concerto where we played in a large
concert grand by Mitsuko Uchida, and
I'll talk through this as we go along.
You can see here the concert
hall the Mozarteum in Salzburg.
It seats about 1,000.
Here is Mitsuko Uchida.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Notice that she, too,
has taken the lid off the instrument.
But it is, of course,
a modern grand piano.
And it amuses me to see,
as you'll see a little bit closer here in
a moment, it is actually a Steinway grand.
So here's the first movement.
And as in Mozart's day,
she will rise and conduct.
[MUSIC]
Right off the bat you can notice the dark,
somber, almost ominous sound.
[MUSIC]
That's a D minor featuring
the low strings.
[MUSIC]
Obviously, woodwinds.
She's not so
much beating a beat pattern, but
simply moding the music to the orchestra.
And we're coming to the end,
the transition here in just a second.
[MUSIC]
It's gonna turn dark again.
Timpani.
[MUSIC]
End of transition.
Second theme.
Contrasting, lighter, more tender.
[MUSIC]
It rises up, melodic sequence,
step by step.
Easy way to remember that particular tune.
[MUSIC]
Now they're gonna charge to C.
So he's got a motive that's going down.
[MUSIC]
Comes up the scale.
And watch, he's gonna turn that motive
back the other way in just a second.
[MUSIC]
Watch this.
Small point, but really cool.
Okay, and
now just the little closing theme at
the end of the orchestral exposition.
[MUSIC]
[INAUDIBLE] blissful,
nostalgic, reminiscent.
[MUSIC]
And the D minor.
And the pianist comes in at this point.
She sits down,
no longer the conductor, but pianist.
All right, that gets us into
the second exposition here.
Let's pause for a moment.
[MUSIC]
So what did you think
about those two pianos?
Which would you prefer to hear?
Mozart's piece on the original Mozart
piano or Mozart's piece on a modern grand?
Which would Mozart have preferred?
Well I'd submit that he'd actually
preferred the modern grand because
Mozart loved when technology
could enhance musical sound.
A new and better clarinet for example,
which is what he experienced in Monheim in
1777, or the re-orchestrations that he
did of the oratorios of Hendel, including
Messiah, in order to take advantage of
the newest and best in sound capabilities.
Adding trumpets and drums and
other instruments to Messiah.
So I think Mozart would have
been very much pleased with
the sound of a larger orchestra and
the bigger piano.
But back now to our D
minor piano concerto.
We're now going to skip to the end of
the recapitulation where we'll hear again
Mozart's themes, but as we do so
he presents then in a varied fashion.
With ornamentation,
ornamentation that places more and
more technical demand on the pianist.
Watch how difficult it gets as
we drive toward the cadenza.
Now remember, a cadenza,
as we saw with Bach, is a showy passage
in which the soloist gets to demonstrate
his or her technical skills.
And reminisce a bit,
improvise a bit, riff on a bit,
the themes that have occurred
previously in a movement.
But here, the cadenza that you'll hear
is not by Mozart, but by Beethoven.
Why?
What's a cadenza by Beethoven doing in
the middle of a concerto by Mozart?
Well, Mozart rarely left
us any cadenzas for
the concertos that he
himself performed in public.
Again, why?
Well Mozart would need to write
down all the orchestral parts.
Stuff that others would need to know to be
able to play the piece, but Mozart didn't
need to write down what he had to play
because he already had it in his head.
And if he'd wrote it down someone
might steal his flashy cadenza.
Mozart thought about things like that.
So Mozart just sat there at the piano and
improvised like a jazz
performer might today.
Surely he never did it the same way twice.
And for this reason, we have no cadenza
here by Mozart from Mozart's own concerto.
However we do have one from Beethoven for
this piece because Beethoven also
played this concerto by Mozart and he,
Beethoven, has left us a cadenza
from the classical period.
So let's return to the end of
the recapitulation in our concerto and
push on to the cadenza.
[MUSIC]
More arpeggios.
Trill.
[MUSIC]
Dramatic movement in the bass.
That two note motive he's hammering home.
Dramatic rise.
Scalar rise from the left hand.
[MUSIC]
[INAUDIBLE].
Descending, arpeggio,
trill indicating [INAUDIBLE] end.
This section,
there's a hint of that first theme again,
and now we're going to end on
a chord that suspends the action,
and we want to hear more with
that suspenseful, in comes the.
[MUSIC]
Credenza, but again by Mozart,
excuse me, but again by Beethoven.
[MUSIC]
Beethoven.
[INAUDIBLE] understood exactly how
Mozart [INAUDIBLE] continued this,
but he didn't care.
This is Beethoven,
Beethoven pounding away.
Mozart wouldn't have pounded a reiterated
sequence of pitches quite like that.
So here's bringing back a new
theme that he introduced.
[MUSIC]
Taking it up to a higher pitch level.
So this is what we mean by simply playing
with themes, further developing themes.
So you're in the cadenza.
Hint of the ominous first theme.
Rises up by step.
[MUSIC]
There's that new theme again.
When you hear a trill in music,
about to hear one in a moment.
You know that that's like holding up
a sign for the rest of the performers.
Hey, pick up your instruments, get ready,
cuz you've gotta come back in and play.
So here's the pick up your instruments
signal, and there they go.
[MUSIC]
They're back in.
Back to all Mozart now.
[MUSIC]
There's that downward motion.
Tremolo.
[MUSIC]
Going the other way.
And a little toss off as a closing theme.
[MUSIC]
The hint of the first theme.
All in dark D minor.
[MUSIC]
Well I hope you'll share with me my
beliefs that this is an extraordinary
movement, and how different from
the ethos or the feeling of a Baroque
concerto of the sort that we
experienced with Bach and Vivaldi.
Baroque concertos usually just
have one mood for a movement.
Mozart is full of many different moods.
And that helps make these classical
movements very exciting, very dramatic.
And with its D minor sound,
it's almost demonic.
You can watch the rest of
this by going to YouTube.
But before we do so,
let's review our Mozart concerto by
revisiting these particular points.
Kochel number, well we talked about
that before, almost ad nauseum here.
A catalog of Mozart's works.
Solo concerto, obviously we've moved
away here in the classical period from
the predominant tradition of concerto
grosso to the solo concerto.
The most commonly experienced solo
concerto is the piano concerto.
We get our word piano, of course,
from the term pianoforte around 1770,
particularly with Mozart,
the pianoforte began to replace
the harpsichord and eventually the second
half of that term pianoforte was dropped
leaving us with the expression piano.
We talked about the double
exposition form,
it's something particular to concerto.
We can also call this concerto form but
there are two expositions here.
One for the orchestra and then one for
the soloist accompanied by the orchestra.
And finally the idea of the cadenza,
which is simply a fast,
flashy passage toward
the end of the movement
that gives the soloist,
whether him or her,
the opportunity to showcase his or
her technical virtuosity.