[MUSIC]
Mozart is often called the most
universal of all composers.
That's the way the Oxford Dictionary music
opens it's definitive article on Mozart.
And he is universal, of course, because
he wrote in all genres, including opera.
Most composers were either or
composers, in the sense that they
were either great instrumental
composers or great opera composer.
Wagner, Verdi, Puccini, almost nothing but
operas, Bach, Beethoven, Haydn.
Well, Bach wrote no operas,
Beethoven, one.
Haydn wrote many but he didn't have
the success of those of Mozart.
And I'm embarrassed to say I
couldn't even identify it for you.
I'd be hard pressed to name
a single opera by Haydn.
But Mozart was a spectacular opera
composer, certainly among the two or
three best ever.
Maybe the best.
Composing opera was
Mozart's favorite activity.
That's what he lived for.
What operas did he write?
Well, he wrote his first
remarkably enough at age 12.
Thereafter, he wrote many opera Serail,
these large and
imposing and somewhat static operas of
the Baroque early classical period.
Then he turned to comic opera or
a blend of comic opera and
serious in a new combination style
opera that Mozart himself created.
We'll see this half-serious half-comic
style in Mozart's Don Giovanni.
Mozart's three greatest
operas are these three.
Marriage of Figaro, Don Giovanni, and
the Magic Flute,
which is the greatest opera every written?
Well maybe Figaro or maybe Don Giovanni or
possibly the Magic Flute.
Now, the Marriage of Figaro and
Don Giovanni have something in common,
a theater.
Figaro, as we said,
was premiered here at the Burgtheater.
Now here's another view
of that same theater.
Figaro was a success here so
Mozart received and
accepted an invitation to go to Prague
to have Figaro performed there.
So Mozart made the two day
coach journey as you can see
up from Vienna to
the beautiful city of Prague.
Now, Prague fortunately has escaped
bombing during the Second World War,
so its architecture is
remarkably well preserved.
Here's the Estates Theater in the center
of the city, constructed in 1783.
The Estates Theater in Prague was
where Mozart's Figaro was performed.
Figaro was so popular in Prague that
Mozart was asked to compose a new opera
for the city, which he did, Don Giovanni,
and which was premiered here
in October of 1787, again in this theater.
You can see that when I was there,
Don Giovanni was actually playing.
So needless to say,
I didn't miss that chance.
And I went and took a few pictures.
It was in this theater inside
of which you see here of course.
It was in this theater that all the opera
scenes for the film Amadeus were created.
Amadeus was filmed in Prague
because there was, and as we said,
more authentic architecture here in
Prague than there was and is in Vienna.
Let's watch a scene now from Amadeus that
we can see Mozart's theater in action.
>> It was terrifying and
wonderful to watch.
[MUSIC]
>> So this of course is
the personification of Antonio Salieri,
Mozart's proposed archenemy.
Here's Mozart conducting
Don Giovanni in this theater.
It still exists, and they tried to make
it as close to the original as possible.
[MUSIC]
What we're watching is the Return of
the Commendatore to exact
revenge on Don Giovanni,
it's terrifying music all in D-minor.
[MUSIC]
It's Leporello who we'll meet in a moment.
Leporello under the table.
[MUSIC]
Don Giovanni in front of him now.
Okay, I cut it off there, aha.
Did it on purpose,
leaving you to want more.
And we'll get to that.
But to the beginning of this opera,
Don Giovanni, what's it about?
Well let's review.
What's opera about?
Mozart wrote three great operas.
Marriage of Figaro,
Don Giovanni, The Magic Flute.
And we're now gonna segue over
to the discussion of opera.
What's opera?
Musically heightened drama.
Music is there behind the drama,
and it reinforces it.
It does the same thing in film.
Ever think about horror films?
What's the scariest horror
film you've ever seen?
AJ?
Chucky?
>> [LAUGH]
>> Okay.
There's one I don't know about.
But, Shining, something like that,
I don't know.
Think of something.
I don't get scared when watching
a movie until what happens?
I see some really scary visual.
Come on.
What scares you in movies.
Supposing they took the sound,
the sound track out of these horror films.
You wouldn't be frightened at all.
I think we have a much more visceral
response to sound than we do to
visual images.
And that's what's going
on globally in opera.
And opera, as you know, is made up of
an introductory overture, and then these
numbers, such as recitatives, where
the composer tells you what's going on.
You remember the Bugs Bunny, or
I guess it's Warner Brothers cartoon,
[SOUND] be very quiet, I am hunting
rabbit, [SOUND] that kind of thing?
So that's a recitative, what's going on.
Then somebody will come out and sing about
how they felt about what just happened.
That's what goes on in an aria.
And arias will tend to repeat words and on
and on it goes to give a sense of emotion.
And there are choruses involved
in it from time to time too.
Now as we mentioned Mozart wrote
three wonderful operas two of them
by Labredus Lorenzo Da Ponte.
Read in your textbook there's
a box on Lorenzo Da Ponte.
Absolutely fascinating life far more
fascinating than fiction could ever
make it.
But we're going to talk
now about Don Giovanni.
What music is this?
Linda, could we have
the next piece of music?
[MUSIC]
What's that?
Nice and loud,
somebody's got it out there.
Overture to Don Giovanni.
Mozart wrote them right here
at this estate outside of
Prague in the wee hours 28 October, 1787.
He wrote the whole thing right here
at this estate between midnight and
7:00 in the morning.
An extraordinary creative act.
Act of procrastination, I suppose.
An act of self confidence
that he could get it done.
It's this overture that opens the opera,
of course, Don Giovanni,
and it was turned into something of
a signature tune for the film Amadeus.
Let's take a listen here.
[MUSIC]
This can be very scary because
of the D minor tonality,
sudden fortissimo, and minor chords.
There's a major dominant chord,
which he'll come back to that
tonic minor in just a second.
[MUSIC]
In some ways, this is a comic opera,
and in others, it's a tragic opera.
And with Mozart, that's typical.
With Mozart,
you never know whether to laugh or to cry.
Let's phase it out here.
What's this story about?
Well, it's an old one based
on the Don Juan legend.
Don Giovanni is simply the Italian for
the Spanish Don Juan.
So it's the story of a Don Juan,
misogynist, a woman hater who seduces,
often rapes,
every woman who comes into view simply for
the sadistic pleasure of conquest and
control.
Don Giovanni is also the leading
nobleman of the town.
Here the upper crust of our high end art,
high end society, is the evil villain, and
the heroes are the peasants who work to
unmask Don Juan and restore social order.
When Mozart and Lorenzo de Ponte created
this version of the Don Juan tale,
they wrote about social tension.
This was dangerous stuff.
This was incendiary stuff,
revolutionary stuff.
The French Revolution came only
two years after Don Giovanni,
opera, 1787, revolution, 1789.
The tension and conflict here
between the noblemen on one side and
the peasants on the other, occurs right
in the first scene when the servant,
or butler Leporello, complains about
his life, complains about working for
Don Giovanni,
complains about working for the man.
In this scene, he's keeping watch for
his master while
master Don Giovanni attempts
another conquest upstairs.
But this time,
the seduction has gone tragically awry.
The lady in question does not succumb.
She fights off the masked assailant and
calls for help from her father,
the aging Commendatore, or
Commander, an old military man.
The commander confronts Don Giovanni and
challenges him to a duel.
At first, Don Giovanni refuses.
I don't fight with old men, he says.
But then the two go at it.
Well, how do you write
a sword fight in music?
Mozart shows us how.
Plenty of fast, rising scales,
music that goes up course in
melodic sequences, melodic symbol,
of course, for building tension.
And it's always in minor, of course,
and it's full of diminished chords.
Now, let me play a little bit of this for
you.
[SOUND] And by coincidence,
we start on our D minor chord.
[MUSIC]
[SOUND] And right there you know that
the Commendatore gets it in the stomach.
We have this.
[MUSIC]
Diminished chord fraught with
tension made up of nothing but
minor thirds, and
that's how you signify tension in music.
Now, we could watch The Metropolitan Opera
perform this scene from Don Giovanni,
but I've chosen, instead, a class video,
because I think it's very good.
Not because my voice is any good.
Actually, it's bad.
[LAUGH] But because the block of
this scene, I think, is quite good.
And I'm helped out here by some students
and my dear friend and colleague,
Professor Richard Lolly, playing
the role of the villainous Don Giovanni.
[MUSIC]
>> Where is the villain?
>> And fight me.
>> Try to forgive me,
to fight with old men.
>> Departed coward, I challenge thee.
>> My crime forgives me.
>> Get out of here.
>> No.
>> Departed coward, I challenge thee.
>> Tempt me not.
>> Draw I say.
>> Old man, come on then.
Your death is near.
>> Ah-ha!
>> [LAUGH]
[MUSIC]
>> [SOUND]
>> [LAUGH]
>> Now we're going to go on to a trio,
a very short one, that's an excellent
example of a vocal ensemble by Mozart.
What's a vocal ensemble?
Well, obviously, it's a group of singers.
But in the case of Mozart, it's a very
special kind of ensemble, three, four,
five, even six soloists, each of
whom has a different point of view.
They don't speak their emotions in
succession as they would in an older
Baroque opera seria, but
all together vocal counterpoint here.
Using a vocal ensemble,
Mozart can move the drama along faster.
Mozart's kind of opera is more fluid,
faster paced, and more realistic.
Here's how this little
vocal ensemble plays out.
>> Don Giovanni is over top of him.
Mozart wrote this
exquisite little trio here.
It goes by very quickly.
No body ever noticed it, but
it's some of the most beautiful
music that he ever wrote.
We ended up on a diminished chord.
Santana, play that diminished chord again,
at the top of that line,
where he gets stabbed.
>> Yep.
[SOUND]
>> Okay, and
then we have this little trio.
Leporello, are you back there, Leporello?
>> I am.
>> Okay.
He is just cowering.
He just wants to get out of here.
This is the worst thing he's ever seen.
Don Giovanni is a bit surprised but
says, you had it coming to you, and
the Commendatore is about
to buy the farm here.
He's on his way out.
So, it says this little, oh,
I don't know, 10, 12 measures or so
of exquisitely beautiful music.
And we'll do it nice and slowly for you.
[MUSIC].
Are
you
there?
Let I then look.
>> Well great fun.
And actually great,
indeed extraordinary, music.
Some of the most beautiful music
as you saw there in the film.
Some fo the most beautiful
music Mozart ever wrote.
And it goes by so quickly.
But let's see how all of this turns out.
We're gonna turn now to
the end of the opera,
where the deceased Commendatore
comes back to life,
exacts retribution from Don Giovanni,
and drags him down to hell.
[MUSIC]
Give me you hand as a pledge,
the commendatory says.
Here it is.
[MUSIC]
In repent.
Repent yourself.
[MUSIC]
Repent again.
no, no, no.
[MUSIC]
Your time is up.
Earth is trembling.
Spirits assail me.
[MUSIC]
I'm swallowed up in vortices.
World.
[MUSIC]
Consumed by horrible fires,
that burn because of the fuel.
Etc.
[MUSIC]
So that's a film version of Don Giovanni.
And that final scene or next to
last scene is very difficult to do,
needless to say,
onstage without burning the place down.
Now whenever you think of the villanous
Don Giovanni as he goes down to hell here
at least you've got to admit that
he's a man of resolute principle.
No no no.
I will not repent.
As to hell he goes.
We used to think of Mozart and
his music as light.
Fast.
Zany sometimes.
But with the great opera Don Giovanni
we see the other side of Mozart,
the demonic Mozart, the dark, and
of course, the minor side of Mozart.