[MUSIC]
Most of us have heard the story
about Mozart's death.
That he died young and suddenly and
unappreciated and poor.
Even thrown in a pauper's grave.
And that, possibly,
he was poisoned by the composer,
his supposed arch-rival, Antonio Salieri.
Well the only thing that's true about all
of this is that Mozart died young, age 35.
But oddly, what's surprising is
not that Mozart died young but
that he lived [LAUGH] as long as he did.
Of course,
these were the days before antibiotics and
he had a frail constitution to begin with.
And he had small pox as a child,
which he survived.
And he has rheumatic fever,
which damaged his heart.
And this was the 18th century,
so the custom was, and
as Mozart observed it, that when
a family member got seriously ill, he or
she was bled, to drain off the bad humors,
medical superstition.
So again, it's a wonder that
he lived as long as he did.
As to the truth of the situation,
in his last year, when he was suddenly
taken ill, Mozart was doing rather well.
Granted the years 1788 through 1790
had been tough, as it was then for
all entertainers in Vienna, and Mozart
was an entertainer as well as an artist.
The Austrian emperor, the boss,
was at war with the Turks.
The aristocracy had fled Vienna,
and the economy collapsed.
But by 1791 both the emperor and
Mozart were on the rebound.
He had written a highly successful opera,
The Magic Flute, that was playing,
in effect, off-broadway in a Vienna
theater, raking in the money.
And he had received and executed
a commission for an opera seria for
the emperor as well as a commission for
a requiem mass.
So Mozart wasn't exactly poverty stricken.
And he'd been promised the position of
music director at the Cathedral of St.
Stephen's when the incumbent died,
that was soon expected.
So here we are, again, in the center of
Vienna, you can see the map up there as it
was in the late 18th century, and as it
is today, the St. Stephen's Cathedral.
And, as evidence of his greatly
improved economic fortunes,
Mozart had moved from
the suburb back into town and
into an expensive apartment on
Wallenstein Gasa here as the map
shows us right behind the cathedral
at the blue arrow that we can see.
And here's how the apartment
looked in Mozart's day.
The Mozarts were on the second floor.
Let me see if my pointer is working here.
The pointer is showing this window here,
and this window over here, and
this window over here,
all on the second floor.
Now here's a diagram of that apartment,
made at the time of Mozart's death,
when his possessions had to
go through probate court.
There are three windows and
these are the three windows that we
just looked at here, here and here.
Here we see Mozart's composing room at M.
Here we see his piano, which we
have already seen the actual piano.
And here around these two windows
his desk and some chairs and
a sofa for
his friends when they came to visit.
Here is Mozart's bedroom
with the bed itself and
a billiard table over here which Mozart
obviously did have in his bedroom but
that's, [LAUGH] that's another story.
So as I say, Mozart was doing quite well,
thank you very much,
in what proved to be his last year, 1791.
But late in November 1791,
Mozart was taken ill.
And within two weeks,
despite the doctor's best,
or inadvertently the doctor's
worst efforts, he died.
We can't be sure of what he died from.
Kidney failure with an adverse
effect on an already damaged heart
is the most likely cause.
Anyway, Mozart's death has
often been romanticized.
Here are a couple of 19th century
romantic paintings of that final scene.
Painting one, you can see the music
around the bed there and then, image two,
same sort of thing, music on the bed with
a group of singers off to the right.
Now, there is some truth to this scene
because while lying on what
was to prove his death bed,
Mozart Rehearsed the vocal parts of some
of the Requiem, and he sang the tenor.
And there's an account of
Mozart's last moments recorded
by his sister-in-law, Sophie Haibel.
So let me read that to you
out of the Mozart documents.
By Otto Erik Deutsch Sussmayr,
now Sussmayr is a pupil of Mozart.
Sussmayr was there at
Mozart's bed side and
the well known requiem
lay on the cover left.
Then Mozart explaining to him
how he thought, he Sussmayr,
should finish it after his death and
the little slightly later.
There was a long search for Dr.
Close, who was found in the theater, but
he had to wait until the play was over.
[LAUGH] Mozart was dying,
And the Doctor came and prescribed cold
compresses on his burning forehead.
And this gave him such a shock that
he did not regain consciousness
before he passed away.
The last thing he did was to try and meld
the sound of the timpani in his requiem.
So a pretty graphic description
of Mozart's last moments.
Well, Mozart.
He didn't finish the Requiem but, with
the help of one of his students as we saw
there, particularly Franz Xaver Sussmayr,
it was completed and Mozart's widow
ultimately collected the remaining half
of the commission the composer was owed.
We'll take a look at this Requiem
manuscript in just a moment, but
first of all, what's a requiem?
What's a requiem mass?
Well as you can see by the slide here,
on the left we have the standard portions
of a mass, we've looked at
this already in our course.
And on the right,
the more specific mass for
the burial of a Catholic Christian,
which Mozart was.
So, as you can see, from the standard
mass, the Gloria has been removed.
This, of course,
is not a happy celebratory moment.
And an important other chant has
been inserted, the Dies irae.
Day of rest, day of judgement,
the last judgement.
So the Dies irae is an extremely
vivid text and chant.
And, indeed, sometimes frightening.
But let's start at the beginning of
the Mozart requiem with the entry of
the clergy and the Introit,
as, in a performance done in
1991 to commemorate the 200th
anniversary of Mozart;s death.
The commemoration took place
in the Cathedral of St.
Steven with the Vienna Philharmonic and
Sir Georg Solti conducting.
Here we are in the cathedral.
The alter is behind us.
[MUSIC]
Beginning in D minor.
Slow
[MUSIC]
and somber.
Hear the clarinet.
[MUSIC]
Bassoon.
Look at those clarinets.
We'll come back Then there's special kind
of low clarinets called basset horns.
They give this mournful quality to it.
There you see trombones.
We haven't had trombones
in symphonies yet.
But there still part of
the religious music of this period.
So masses going back all the way into the
15th century were already using trombones.
[MUSIC]
Where the actual test requiem.
Now we're looking at
the west end of the church.
[MUSIC]
Requiem mater, may he have eternal rest.
It looks perpetual may eternal life shine
upon you on this moment of judgement.
[FOREIGN] May it shine.
Big crescendo.
[MUSIC]
And then, once again, the mournful
somber sound of the basset horns and
as we go into the next section of
the intro it will fade it out here.
Okay let's move on now.
We're going to move on following
our slide to the Dies irae.
Dies irae, of course,
is that vivid section of the Requiem.
And the last two parts of it
are the Confutatis and the Lacrimosa.
So let's look at the music
of the Confutatis.
Here we have down below, starting with
the basses and tenors, this sort of sound.
[MUSIC]
Very low, very agitated, very minor.
[MUSIC].
The voices enter, I think let's
see what comes in first here,
looks like the tenor voice.
[MUSIC]
Maybe the bass voice.
[MUSIC.
That interval there is an extremely
difficult and dissonant one.
So we have, actually it's
called the diabolus in music.
So we've got the devil baked
into this hellish scene here.
All down in minor.
Coming up step by step.
[MUSIC]
Then the upper voices come in,
the female voices, very high.
[MUSIC]
[FOREIGN] call me.
Call me with the blessed.
It's all high.
It's all consonant.
It's all major.
So it's a very different sort of sound.
So he's separating out here the two
textures and the two styles.
The hellish and the elect.
And this is part of an old
Christian tradition.
Let's look at here in our next slide
an altarpiece of Hans Memling,
where the damned are thrust into Hell.
And they're on the left side of God,
the sinister side.
And the left are on the right side of God.
So let's go back now and hear a bit of
this following the arrows on the screen.
[MUSIC]
From the agitated bases.
Very quick modulation, C Major.
[MUSIC]
Back to the low sounds, the agitated
sounds, the minor sounds, the painful,
tortured sounds of those in Hell.
[MUSIC]
Okay, and then back up to the high sound
square I'd like to leave this within.
We'll fade out there.
Now we come to the last
movement of the dies irae.
And the last music that Mozart wrote.
Music finished often orchestrated,
as we saw, by his pupil Süssmayr.
Lets take a look at this last image here.
Here we have the next to last piece
of paper that Mozart ever wrote on.
It's the Lacrimosa and
you can see up at the top there
we have the three string part.
Three stringed parts, first violin,
second violins, violas,
and then the basses of the orchestra
are actually down here underneath.
And then the four choral parts,
soprano, alto, tenor, and bass.
At the text and this is a particularly
important text, qual ray surgen.
Notice that ascending
scale that is going up
[MUSIC]
Then we go across the page and
that scale continues and
indeed it becomes even more chromatic.
[MUSIC]
And more intense as it goes.
That's why I color-coded that with a red.
And that's where Mozart's
music broke off and
that little snippet that you see
following it is in the hand of Sussymr.
So let's focus on this extraordinary
passage here in our next line.
So here's a modern edition
of it with the words
(foreign) fa-vil-la ju-di
can-dus ho-mo re-us.
On that day in which out of the ashes
will rise the just person to be judged.
So it's starting down very low.
[MUSIC]
And now it gets even more
intense with the chromaticism.
[MUSIC]
With the top part.
All the way up to the,
[MUSIC]
The triumphant peak at the top of this.
Okay, let's go on now to here,
this extraordinary movement.
But before we do so, let's work through
a couple of initial slides here.
It starts out with what I like to think
of as a funeral quartet sounding this way.
[MUSIC]
And then we have the scalar passage that
we've already studied just a moment ago.
That's the B material rising up.
Then at A the funeral quartet comes back.
Over on the next page, we can see that
once again the extraordinary ascent is
built into this, but
now it's occurring in the bass part.
[MUSIC]
And so on, so it's coming up again,
rising from the dead.
In the basses.
Then, in the next passage,
at C you can see that we have,
for the first time,
a reference to Christ here.
[FOREIGN].
I'm having a little
trouble reading the text,
but [FOREIGN] save me Lord.
[FOREIGN].
So, at that point,
the text starts referring to or
is referring to [FOREIGN],
pious, merciful Jesus.
And there's a modulation for
the first time out of the somber
D-minor to a major key.
And then as we go across,
we'll hear the sound of the clarinet.
And a modulation will take us back
from the sweet sound of the major,
back to the demonic sound of the minor.
The funeral cortege comes
back with the letter A there.
And at B, we have our ascent, but this
time our ascent's turning the other way.
It's all going down, and
it's going down in polyphonic texture,
starting with the basses,
picked up with the sopranos.
And down, down, down it goes.
And at the very end we will
have there a very somber
sort of Amen cadence
that is very powerfully
affected either by Mozart or by Sussmayr.
So the last music that Mozart ever wrote.
Let's go back to the beginning and we'll
listen and I'll comment as we proceed.
[MUSIC]
So here we go with the funeral cortege or
at least as I like to hear it,
a funeral cortege.
The conductor here is Neville Marriner,
who's chosen a very slow tempo,
but that has the virtue of letting the
beauty of the music stand out even more.
[MUSIC]
Okay, now here comes our rise.
And as the ashes, purgatory.
[MUSIC]
Now, a scale turns into
a climatic scale as the music
crescendoed, Mozart himself wrote this in.
[MUSIC]
Back to the initial
swinging funeral cortege.
So here we go across the page.
[MUSIC]
Mozart has re-orchestrated this
in a way that the chromatic
ascent is now in the bass line,
at the ascending red arrow.
It's a climatic ascent, hence the red.
Basses are rising, but
now breaking up the rise in octaves.
[MUSIC]
Now here's the text,
therefore save us, [FOREIGN].
[FOREIGN], spare us.
[MUSIC]
[FOREIGN] here comes
the modulation from the major,
appropriate for the text.
[MUSIC]
Landing in a peaceful,
even Arcadian F major.
And as we go across the page,
the modulation will begin again
with our mournful clarinet.
[MUSIC]
Here it comes, the crescendo,
back to the minor, to the original music.
[MUSIC]
Hear the ascent, of course it's
turned in the opposite direction.
[MUSIC]
Emphasizing not triumph, but resolution.
One last cry from the orchestra.
[MUSIC]
And it ended there on a hopeful note,
with the final turn to major.
[MUSIC]
So this is extraordinary music,
that ascent in particular.
Starting low and in despair and
rising high to a feeling of triumph and
exaltation.
Well this can be applied to many
aspects of human existence.
Many aspects of everyday mundane
existence, as the next slide suggests.
>> The last four hours have seen
one child fail to get to the air
sickness bag in time.
>> So in the background in this
TV commercial for Bookings.com,
you hear the Mozart Requiem
beginning with the funeral cortege.
But already, he's cut to the ascent.
>> Until now.
>> Coming up, now as we open the room,
we hit the climactic ascent.
We're getting higher and
higher, toward exultation.
>> Booking.com.
Booking.yeah.
>> Well, Mozart's a genius.
What's a genius?
Somebody that has staying power over
the centuries and across cultures.
In any event,
that's the end of the Requiem and
that actually the end of Mozart's music.
And that's the end of
our session on Mozart.
But before we leave him,
let's review in simple terms
not just what makes Mozart great, but what
makes him extraordinary, surely unique.
What makes Mozart great?
Well universality, we talked about that.
He wrote in all genres,
particularly opera.
Writing symphonies, concertos, string
quartets, and operas is exceptional.
Perfect balance and perfect proportions.
Both Albert Einstein and
George Bernard Shaw commented on this.
I think it was Shaw who
said that Mozart's music
would not sound out of
place in the voice of God.
And this sense of the balance and
proportion is particularly important,
I think, in his music.
This capacity for the endless and
effortless supply of melodies,
we've already heard
a great number of them.
The greatest beauty from
the simplest of ideas.
We could go back to
the C Major piano concerto, but
here's a little reminder of that capacity.
[MUSIC]
I'll pause it right there.
Greatest beauty from
the simplest of ideas.
Great beauty from even that sort of
nursery rhyme of a melody that he created.
And then finally, the fullest range
of musical and human emotions.
And we saw that right there with
the arising ascent in the Requiem,
where we go from the depths of
despair to the heights of triumph.
Well, these are some of the things that
make Mozart's music extraordinary.
And if you like our visit with Mozart and
thought his music exceptional,
I'll leave you with a list of my favorite
pieces by Mozart and books about him.
[MUSIC]