[MUSIC]
Beethoven is a well known figure,
not just in music, but in western culture.
I'm holding here a copy of
a Charles Schultz Peanuts cartoon.
I won't put it up for long,
because likely it's being
governed by rigid copyright laws.
But it shows Linus and
Lucy at a grand piano.
And on top of it sits a bust of Beethoven.
There were lots of busts of
Beethoven from the 19th century on.
And here I have an action
figure of Beethoven.
Now I don't know what action he's up to,
but surely he's up to something powerful.
And indeed, prior to the film Amadeus,
which centered on Mozart, when the average
educated listener thought of classical
music, the go-to guy for classical music,
who thought of a musical motive from
classical musical such as this.
[MUSIC]
Thought of Beethoven and his music.
After Amadeus, however,
public consciousness about classical
music begins to shift a bit to Mozart.
So these two figures,
Mozart and Beethoven,
stand at the heart of western classical
music, chronologically and culturally.
So let's compare them.
And let's pursue this by means of a quiz.
So here we have on our screen
a series of questions.
Which composer was a child
prodigy on the keyboard?
Which would you imagine?
Well they both actually were.
Which composer had
a father in the business,
who was also a professional musician?
Well, again, they both did.
Leopold was a violinist,
Johann van Beethoven,
he was a tenor in the choir
at the Court of Bonn.
Which composer had an abusive father
who locked him in the basement
if he didn't practice?
That may be a slight exaggeration but
not much of one.
Well, in this case, it's Beethoven,
because father Leopold Mozart,
provided a very enlightened education and
upbringing for his son.
Four, which composer had
a father who passed him off
a year younger than he really was?
Well, again, both fathers did this.
Father Beethoven sometimes tried
to pass him off as being two years
younger than he really was.
Both of these gentlemen were short,
so it was feasible.
And Beethoven went through his entire
life, imagine that, went through his
entire life thinking he was actually
two years younger than he really was.
When he died in 1827,
Beethoven believed that he was 55, not 57.
Which composer was skilled on the violin
and organ as well as the piano?
Well, both of them were.
Which composer was short and
had a pockmarked face?
Well, Beethoven from birth and
Mozart also from his experience,
as we mentioned before, with smallpox.
Which composer had absolute pitch,
or perfect pitch?
Well, we know for sure that Mozart did and
undoubtedly Beethoven as well.
Let's go onto our next sequences.
Which composer moved from a much
smaller town to Vienna, so
as to test his performing and
compositional skills
against the very best?
Well as you undoubtedly know,
they both did.
Mozart and Beethoven.
Mozart moving from Salzburg,
Beethoven moving from Bonn.
Which composer enjoyed a lucrative
position as a court composer
to the Holy Roman Emperor in Vienna?
Well here, lucrative is the key word, and
it was really only Mozart who enjoyed
a position here of really any sort.
Beethoven had an annuity
from the Arch Duke, but
it was not directly from
the Holy Roman Emperor himself.
Which composer studied either directly or
indirectly with the older
master Joseph Haydn?
Well, they both did, in the sense that
Mozart studied Haydn's scores and
was a good personal friend of Haydn.
And Beethoven studied as a pupil with
the older man, his teach Joseph Haydn.
Which composer regularly worked,
regularly composed away from the piano.
Away from the piano, not at the piano.
Well, unlike Haydn who worked
at the piano, both Mozart and
Beethoven regularly simply composed at
a composing desk of one sort or another.
They had the music in their ears,
they didn't need to get inspiration
from a keyboard instrument of any kind.
Okay, and
now to the personal qualities of this.
They were very different sorts of people.
Which composer was puctilliously
attentive to his dress?
Well, Mozart and
you can see how Mozart loved those
red coats with the gold buttons.
Here on the right we see Beethoven.
Actually Beethoven all gussied out.
All ready to go.
This is, in a sense better
than Beethoven ever looked.
In terms of his attire,
he was rather messy.
Which composer, following this line along,
which composer was on
more than one occasion, arrested because
he looked like a derelict or a vagrant?
And that was Beethoven,
wandering around the streets of Vienna.
Which composer got all
tidied up by history?
Well, they both did as we'll see
in the portraits of Beethoven.
He always looked better in his
portraits than he did in reality.
And by Mozart, look at Mozart in
the actual portrait about 1779 or so.
And how history has taken that
image out of that portrait and
refined it or prettied it up if you will.
Which composer was
a prodigy as a composer?
Well here, really only Mozart.
Beethoven didn't write anything really
of significance that we play today
until his mid 20s, Mozart,
much earlier, a good decade earlier.
Which composer wrote nearly
finished manuscripts, and
which composer labored
mightily on his scores?
Well, to answer this,
let's look at some autographs.
Here's the autographs,
as you can see by the title up there,
of what proved to be
Mozart's last symphony.
The Symphony Number 41.
As you can see, it's neat.
It's a tidy score.
The violins are at the top.
There may be a correction
in the upper left there,
in the second violin part at the arrow.
But the fact that you can tell what
the instruments are tells us something.
This is a very legible score.
And if you're familiar
with Mozart's autographs,
you can tell that he is moving
through this at lightning speed.
It has to do with the angle of the note
heads and the density of the ink.
So he's just pouring this out
straight out of his head.
Now, by comparison let's go over and we'll
see an image of a symphony by Beethoven.
Now, when I saw this the title
said Symphony Number 9, and
I had to think about, well where
the heck in Symphony Number 9 are we?
And I got out a full score and
rooted around a bit, and
was able to figure out that we're
in the first movement of this,
what also proved to be the last symphony
of Beethoven, his Symphony Number 9.
But what a difference
compared to the Mozart here,
we see correction piled upon correction,
one on top of the other,
something of a musical train wreck.
Well here, a picture is indeed
worth a thousand words.
The picture Mozart flying by and that of
Beethoven laboring mightily, struggling.
And that sense of labor and
struggle oddly, is something that we hear
in the music of Beethoven and
each of us can personally relate to.
So let's explore now the messy Beethoven,
and
how this unusual person became
something of a poster boy, an icon for
the creative artist generally
in the early 19th century.