[MUSIC]
This image of the disheveled,
disorganized,
oblivious to the world around him
Beethoven, the isolated genius,
was a concept created
during the 19th century.
The classical period in music
spans the 18th and 19th centuries,
and Beethoven spans the classical and
romantic eras.
During the first decades
of the 19th century,
the very notion of the genius as we think
of him or her today comes into being.
Isolated, misunderstood,
struggling, suffering for his art.
No artist or creator better represented or
personified this
development then Beethoven.
Here is contemporary image of
Beethoven composing imaginary or not.
But it doesn't seem to be a happy process.
On the contrary, it's wild and
chaotic at least compared to the image
of the creating artist of
the preceding century.
Namely, Beethoven's teacher, Haydn.
Here's Haydn, neat and tidy,
working at a keyboard.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
And here's the image of Beethoven.
[MUSIC]
Again, I exaggerate, but this image of
the spontaneous, disorganized Beethoven,
the notion of the wild creator crying
in the wilderness, raging with and
against nature, well, that's part
of the growing Romantic aesthetic.
As we see here in this very large canvas
by the English painter John Martin.
The image of the isolated,
struggling artist, poet, or
composer became a stereotype.
One fostered by Beethoven himself.
Now here is Beethoven as poet,
Beethoven the bard.
Beethoven struggling against
the forces of nature and against fate.
There was also, as we'll see in
our next session, a tendency to
think of Beethoven as an unstable
personality, a real oddball.
Part of this was occasion
by an unsympathetic public
dealing with disability,
Beethoven's growing deafness.
Here on the screen is an account of
Beethoven during the performance of his
Ninth Symphony.
Beethoven is called a madman.
When Beethoven himself conducted, he
stood in front of a conductor's stand and
threw himself back and
forth like a madman.
At one point he stretched to his full
height, then next he crouched down to
the floor and
he flailed about with his hands and feet.
Well this notion of the slightly
deranged but brilliant genius
arrives during the early 19th and
into the 20th century when
it was created by figures
such as Mary Shelly as you can see here
with Frankenstein and Victor Hugo with
the Hunchback of Notre Dame and Gaston
Leroux with the Phantom of the Opera.
Well in many ways,
it all began with Beethoven.
And here's an image of Beethoven
as he looked at age 48.
Again, Beethoven somewhat tidied up here.
And look now,
the genius of the 20th century.
Well it comes to resemble Beethoven.
Einstein aping Beethoven if you will.
Young Beethoven, as the years went by,
helped create this image of
Beethoven the archetype of genius.
Indeed Beethoven himself promoted it,
this notion that we still have with
us today of the artist as genius.
As we'll see from the following quotes
embedded in a couple of slides here.
So this is one about how
the artist suffers for his art.
Quote, the undersigned Beethoven,
and this is Beethoven talking.
The undersigned Beethoven has
been concerned not merely
with earning his daily bread,
but rather, with his art.
With the ennoblement of taste, and
the impulse of his genius, in order
to rise to greater heights searching for
the ideal and for perfection.
Consequently he has had to sacrifice
his material gains to his
music to his art to his muse.
The artist, again,
who is something above the common herd,
who's cut from a cloth different
from others, Beethoven certainly
held himself in very high esteem
here in 1798 at the age of 28.
Nobody's had ever heard of
Beethoven at this time.
He compares himself already
to the famous von and
the equally famous Frederick Handel.
No lack of self confidence there.
1803 he refuses to play for
the King of Prussia, a year or
two later he refused an invitation
to play for the empress in Vienna.
He sent her a note back saying I'm busy
today but I might stop by tomorrow.
1804, he says to Prince Carl Lichnowsky,
Prince, what you are you
are by accident of birth.
What I am I am through myself.
There have been and
still will be thousands of princes.
There's only one Beethoven.
But Beethoven didn't realize,
I think, that he owed his talents and
his accomplishments to natural gifts.
Just like the Prince, to genetics.
Beethoven came from
a long line of musicians.
He was just as much a product of
his birth as was Prince Lichnowsky.
Beethoven was born with absolute pitch and
exceptional musical memory.
He was a child prodigy in Bonn, Germany.
So let's go visit now Beethoven
in Bonn in his youth.