[MUSIC]
Like Mozart and Haydn before him,
Beethoven was not a native of Vienna but
was drawn to the city
because of patronage,
the patronage that Vienna
offered creative musicians.
The aristocracy had
money to spend on music.
And thus many great composers were
lured there, not only for the money but
to test themselves
against the very best and
to learn the latest in
cutting edge high art music.
Beethoven was actually born far
from Vienna in Bonn, Germany,
the other end of the German-speaking
world, as you can see by this map here.
Bonn, then with a population of about
20,000, a tenth of that in Vienna,
was then the seat of the elector of Bonn,
one of the nine individuals who go to
vote for,
who got to choose the Holy Roman Emperor.
And the elector of Bonn was actually
a close relative of the emperor back
in Vienna.
But Bonn,
although linked to Vienna by blood,
was actually no closer to
Vienna than was Paris.
Beethoven was the son and
grandson of a musician.
His father had come to Bonn
from the low countries.
The family name was van Beethoven,
Flemish and
not von Beethoven, German,
so Flemish not German.
Beethoven always thought
well of his grandfather and
carried this portrait of him
until the end of his days.
In Bonn the Beethovens were employed
as musicians at the Court of Bonn.
And they lived in this house, a quite
respectable, here you see on the left,
the back courtyard, and on the right,
the front of the house as it exists today.
A very respectable dwelling for someone
of the 18th century, today it serves
also as a museum and a research center for
the life and music of Beethoven's.
Beethoven's father, however,
seems to have been something of a tyrant.
As we saw, he forced young Beethoven
to practice at all hours of the day,
and the father was something
of disreputable drunkard.
So, Beethoven left.
First he went off to Vienna in 1787,
but was called
back immediately to Bonn by a family
crisis, indeed the death of his mother.
And only later, five years later
in 1792 did the aristocrats of
Bonn put together a purse large enough
to send Beethoven back to Vienna.
As one patron said, quote, in fulfillment
of a wish that has long been frustrated.
Although Mozart's genius
is still in mourning,
you will receive the spirit of
Mozart from the hands of Haydn.
So off he goes.
And Beethoven did study with Haydn, but
Beethoven and
Haydn were temperamentally different.
Beethoven was probably
temperamentally from everyone.
And Haydn, who was most often in these
years in London, was not a diligent tutor.
So Haydn and Beethoven had a very rough,
bumpy teacher-student relationship.
But within a few years,
Beethoven had begun to make it on his own,
make a name for
himself among the well-to-do of Vienna.
Essentially, he earned his living from
the sale of his musical compositions.
Quote, I state my price and they,
the publishers, they pay, he said proudly.
And he earned money from
giving a few piano lessons
in the homes of the aristocracy.
But mainly he earned his livelihood from
playing, when invited, at the soirees,
the musical parties in
the homes of the aristocracy.
So, it was mainly in the guise
of a piano virtuoso that
Beethoven made his mark in Vienna.
As a magazine of the day
said of Beethoven in 1794,
quote, Beethoven, a musical genius,
has chosen Vienna as his residence for
the past two years.
He is widely admired for
the unusual velocity of his playing, and
is astounding in the way
he masters the most
formidable difficulties
with the greatest of ease.
And that brings us to Beethoven and
his style of piano playing.
Contemporaries said that his
playing moved listeners to cry,
even sob, but
also that it was loud and bombastic.
And he sometimes missed notes and
sometimes broke strings as we learned
from a contemporary musician,
Ignaz Pleyel.
As Pleyel said, and we use as
a backdrop here this this 20th century,
imagine you've seen Beethoven
in the midst of his chaos.
Quote, his playing is NOT clean.
He has much fire, but
he pounds a bit too much.
He overcomes diabolical difficulties,
but he does not do so neatly.
He does not do so neatly.
Well, what might this have sounded like,
Beethoven crashing and
thrashing the piano?
Let's look at Beethoven's
Pathetique Sonata, written in 1797.
Okay, so
here I am back at the keyboard and
will play a bit of this,
the Pathetique Sonata.
Note here the presence of the Latin
word Opus, abbreviated as Op.
Op 13, you see at the top of the image,
under Sonate.
With a composer,
that means the 13th published work
by that particular composer, work 13.
The term pathetique here,
derives from pathos, with intense feeling.
And this is one of the few
titles that Beethoven himself
gave to one of his works.
So here we are at the keyboard and
notice in particular here
the extraordinary difference
between the louds and the softs.
[MUSIC]
So we'll stop there.
And you get the point.
All this pounding that we hear here in
the Pathetique Sonata, could it in any way
have been caused by the fact that
Beethoven was having trouble hearing,
that he was going deaf?
Or was this simply his artistic vision?
This is a question worth exploring.