[MUSIC]
What an odd thought.
A deaf musician.
Of course, there have been many
blind musicians, Francesco Landini,
Stevie Wonder, Ray Charles,
Blind Tom Wiggins.
But a deaf composer?
That would be like a blind painter.
Of course, Beethoven wasn't born deaf.
It was an illness that came upon him
gradually, beginning about 1798,
at the age of 28.
Perhaps, even earlier as we'll see.
But for really gifted musicians, this may
not have been quite as fatal as it sounds.
The best musicians can hear
with an inner ear, and
don't need to play on
a keyboard to get inspiration.
They just sit back, and hear, and write.
And that's what Beethoven did.
He could compose anywhere.
But deafness affected Beethoven's social
life and also his career as a performer.
He couldn't hear how loud he was playing,
and
eventually he stopped playing
in public all together.
As he said to a friend in 1801, I must
confess that I lead a miserable life.
For almost two years now I have ceased to
attend any social function just because
I find it impossible to say to people,
I am deaf.
If I had any other profession I might
be able to cope with my infirmity, but
in my profession it is
a terrible handicap.
A year later, Beethoven commented again
on his deafness in an extraordinary
document called
the Heiligenstadt Testament.
Part last will and testament,
part a cry for understanding.
The Heiligenstadt Testament is so
called because it was written in
the suburb of Vienna of that name,
Heiligenstadt.
You can take a tram out there,
streetcar, go there today.
And here's that very pleasant looking
abode where Beethoven, tortured by
his sense of growing deafness, was staying
in the late summer, early fall of 1802.
Now here on the screen,
you see the actual document of
the Heiligenstadt Testament
in Beethoven's own hand.
And I'll read an English
translation of this segment of it.
I have always been disposed
to accomplish great deeds.
Well, again, not lacking for
self confidence, our friend Beethoven.
Yet only consider that for 6 years I have
been suffering an incurable affliction.
Well that pushes this all the way
back to about 1796, or so.
Aggravated by imprudent physicians.
Beethoven never thought
much of his doctors.
Year after year deceived
by the hope of improvement.
Finally forced to contemplate
the prospect of lasting illness.
And then later on further
on into the document,
I would have ended my life,
it was only my art that held me back.
So, perhaps it was more personal
catharsis than anything else,
because Beethoven never actually
published or made public this document.
It was only discovered among his
effects upon his death in 1827.
What caused Beethoven's death?
Well, I'm really in no position to say,
and
even professional audiologists
can't say with certainty.
We have only the autopsy to go on, and
yes, they did an autopsy on Beethoven.
But the autopsy, of course,
shows the result, not the cause.
Well let's take a look at this,
by means of a slide here.
Here you see the external ear on
the left and this critical, for
Beethoven, center area.
He suffered from tinnitus and
a distended inner ear,
middle ear here,
that had ossified over time.
As the autopsy suggests.
He lost his capacity to hear high
sounds first about 1812 or so, and
then more or
less completely deaf by 1812,13, 14.
And what's in question here is the small
bones, the malleus and the incus,
that send the sound over to the cochlea
and the basilar membrane inside.
But more importantly,
how did this affect the music?
Well, difficult to know.
But one aspect of the music that we can
still absorb is Beethoven's consistent,
almost obsessive desire to repeat pitches.
Say it again, say it again, again,
again, again, again, and sometimes,
this process as music is not pretty or
pleasant.
Here's an example from Beethoven's
Fidelio, overture to that opera.
One of the, indeed the only opera
that he wrote of that name, Fidelio.
Let's listen to again,
a part of the overture to Fidelio.
[MUSIC]
Well, as I say, that's not pretty.
At least it doesn't seem pretty to me.
It's more like someone
being put on a timpani and
being bludgeoned to death
with a timpani stick.
Was that Beethoven trying
to hear the music?
Make sure that everyone else didn't
miss the point of this crescendo here.
Don't mind my crescendo.
Don't, don't, don't miss it.
But this is largely
speculation on my part.
Perhaps Beethoven would have created
this reiterative style of music anyway.