[MUSIC]
Despite and possibly in some ways because
of his hearing difficulties, Beethoven
created some remarkable music during
the first decade of the 19th Century.
Let's take a look at
one well-known example,
the Moonlight Sonata, a sonata
written in 1801 and published in 1802,
one of Beethoven's 32 sonatas for piano.
Here's Beethoven working on
the first movement in 1801.
It's a pretty clean score
by Beethoven standards.
But compositionally or creatively,
it may be that in some ways,
this is not all that difficult a piece.
It's more like a song as opposed,
say, to dense counterpoint.
More like a song, a song without words.
So this is the slide of the autographed
of one page of the sketch and
you can see we're about
on into first ten or so
bars of the first movement here.
And here is the title page for
the sonata when it was ultimately
published the next year.
As you can see at the top of this slide,
we have the title there [FOREIGN].
Well that's interesting.
So they were still selling and
people were still playing the harpsichord.
In a mode of a fantasy for
the harpsichord or the piano forte.
So people had started access to
harpsichords in Beethoven's day.
What else it say here?
[FOREIGN].
Well that's the person whom,
the young lady to whom this sonata
was piano sonata was dedicated.
It was the daughter of one of his doctors.
Da, or by, Luigi Van Beethoven.
Luigi Van Beethoven,
Italian is still the dominate language, so
this is all published in Italian.
Opus 27 number two.
But notice that nowhere on this title
page is to be found the word moonlight.
Beethoven didn't give it this name.
A German Romantic poet did later
after he had heard the music and
thought that it reminded him of night
with moonlight shining across a lake.
Anyway, here's the score
of the first page.
Okay, so here we are now at the keyboard.
Let me play the first movement
of The Moonlight Sonata.
At least, the beginning.
>> [MUSIC]
We'll stop there.
Okay, what's happened here?
Well, we had almost
[MUSIC]
little intro, almost like a pop piece.
A little intro setting the tempo, setting
the mood, and then the melody comes in.
All of this is built of
course on triplet triads.
And finally the melody comes in,
beautiful melody up on top.
[MUSIC]
And notice we started here, but
up above that first star in blue.
We've already modulated to major.
We started with the first star in C minor.
We modulated by the second star
to the relative major, E major.
So that's of interest.
What else of interest here.
Right there, that first blue star and
the first red arrow.
Here we're sitting here.
[MUSIC]
Suddenly turns that to minor.
It's almost as if a cloud
came over the face of a moon.
And that's what Beethoven is doing in
this movement, playing off the light and
dark, the major against minor, constantly.
This is essentially a beautiful
melody built over top of
some very straightforward
supporting triads.
Now, are we hearing those triumphs.
Are you hearing those triumphs?
Well, let's see, let's turn now to a quiz.
So, we're going to go on,
we'll set up our quiz sheet here.
I'm going to strip this down to 8
triads that support the melody here.
And I'll call them out as we go.
And it's your job, and I'm gonna strip
them down to their essence, it's your job
to tell me whether they are a minor
triad or a major triad.
Minor, major.
May be a little harder then you think.
So let's start out here.
I'll play them.
Just the triads.
And here we go.
Chord one.
[SOUND] Two.
[MUSIC]
3.
4.
[MUSIC]
5.
6.
[MUSIC]
7.
8.
[MUSIC]
Okay, now the second set.
1.
[MUSIC]
2.
3.
[MUSIC]
4.
5.
1.
[MUSIC].
6.
7.
[MUSIC].
Again, 6.
[MUSIC]
Okay, well, how did you do?
Let's see by the next slide.
One is minor.
I'll just play along here.
Minor, minor, major, major.
Better check these myself.
[MUSIC]
Major, minor, major, minor.
All right, let's go on to the next.
We're gonna check those.
Now here comes major,
minor 2 is minor, 3 is minor.
4 is major.
5 is major.
6 is major.
And 7 is minor.
[MUSIC]
Okay.
All right,
now let's go on to the next page.
We're gonna move on here
in our Moonlight Sonata.
Pick it up oh, any old where.
[MUSIC]
And now across to the next page.
And we're just about at the.
[MUSIC]
Blue star.
Melody comes back in.
Yet another key.
[MUSIC]
And at this point, this is interesting,
he could have gone right back there.
Beethoven could have gone right back
to his tonic, he's sitting on it,
on that dominant and
he could have brought his, could
have brought his melody in.
But he didn't there.
This is the third system.
He continues to hold that
dominant note underneath,
dominant pedal point that
we've experience before.
Builds up tension, but it builds
up tension over a very long span.
[MUSIC]
Down an octave.
Up an octave.
[MUSIC]
Down an octave.
Now arpeggio.
[MUSIC]
First with a diminished triad,
minor triad, diminished,
more diminished,
all the way up to the top,
then it starts to come
down in unit sub two.
[MUSIC]
He's back.
He's got this little counterpoint.
Hear that in the inner voice?
[MUSIC]
But then.
He changes it.
Just one note.
[MUSIC]
We expect him to go, but he doesn't.
He goes here.
It's a beautiful surprise chord.
And then that forces him to extend.
[MUSIC]
And finally, plays back at his tonic.
And the melody comes in at that point.
Well it's a very beautiful piece.
It's one that I've been playing for
more years than I care to admit,
but centuries of people have been playing
this, and that's one of the things that
makes this a classic and makes classical
music art, the staying power of art.
Okay, well that was the first
movement of the Moonlight Sonata.
Hope you did well on that quiz.
Hope you got at least 50% [LAUGH].
But, this first movement by
Beethoven is a bit unusual here,
because it's written more like a second
movement, a sort of slow, dreamy
second movement, as we would expect the
second movement to be in a piano sonata.
This is one of Beethoven's
noble elegiac slow movements.
The kind of thing that
Beethoven loved to write and
the kind of thing that he was famous for.
But this first movement of
the Moonlight Sonata is not fast and
not in sonata allegro
form as we might expect.
For a fast sonata allegro form movement
in this sonata, we have to wait for
the exciting third and
last movement, the finale.
And it too is something special.
Here's the music for it.
There we go.
We're over to the Finale here.
[MUSIC]
And off it goes, and you can see
basically it's taking this triadic idea,
groups of that we've encountered in
the first movement, this triadic idea and
arpeggios, and extending them upwards,
but now at a lightning pace.
Breakneck pace.
So let's listen to a snippet
of this in a performance by
the pianist Vladimir Ashkenazy.
[MUSIC]
Okay, let's phase this down.
It was at that moment that I knew,
when I was 18 years old,
that I was never gonna
be a concert pianist.
I could never play this really up
to tempo the way it should go.
As we've heard here with Vladimir
Ashkenazy, the playing was very fast and
very clean.
But notice at once point,
he put in a little bit of retard to help
give the music a sense of definition and
form in his performance and
not all pianists do this.
They worry about
the technical aspect of this.
They have to wrestle so hard with
the technical and not the expressive.
Here's a very mechanical, sort of
unexpressive performance that you can find
on YouTube, but it's fun to
watch because of the animation.
[MUSIC]
So again here, the tempo is hugely fast,
but it's almost machine like.
And actually,
this movement's a good one to focus on
to discuss the issue of expression and
a performer's interpretation on
the music the composer has created.
Let's watch the beginning of another
performance of the same piece,
this one by Valentina Zitza.
The performance you'll about
to see has been viewed,
enjoyed by more than 7
million people worldwide.
Anyway, as you watch her performance,
what is she fore-grounding here?
Is it technique or expression, or both?
[MUSIC]
Syncopation.
Repeated
[MUSIC]
>> And the closing theme.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Lower.
Higher.
>> [MUSIC]
>> And this leads us back to
the repeat of exposition.
So, we're going to stop it there.
So, what'd you think of that?
Sure is fast.
Is this technique or expression and
how do we recognize expression?
How does a performer create expression.
Well, by louds and softs and
by diminuendo and crescendos and
especially by variation in tempo,
retards and accelerandos.
So again technique, just in a sense
how fast it goes, versus expression.
Expression being personal interpretation,
constantly tweaking the music,
if you will.
How does a performer play with our
expectations of the musical score?
That's a lot that's involved here.
How can our expectations be
brought into this and then be
extended in an exciting sort of way to
make the interpretation very personal.
Well, here's another performer,
American pianist Mark Solman,
what do you think here,
technique or expression?
[MUSIC]
>> There's a lot of pedal at this point,
[INAUDIBLE] perhaps
[MUSIC]
>> Nice, bringing out that second theme.
Tempo may have slowed down just a bit,
though.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Nice fast tempo here.
>> Syncopation.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Wow, really slowed it down there.
Much slower here.
[MUSIC]
>> He'll probably bring it back.
A lot of fortissimo there.
Hesitation there.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Here's our closing theme.
>> Very slow and very quiet.
>> [MUSIC]
>> And now we go back to
the beginning of the piece,
to the return exposition yet again.
Well, which did you like better?
They were very different.
I'll give you a moment to
think about it and tell me.
Now, it's my turn.
[INAUDIBLE] is playing with technically
dazzling and she kept the tempo right now
beat She gets through this exposition in
exactly one minute and thirty seconds.
But didn't allow for, that speed perhaps,
didn't allow for much opportunity for
interpretive freedom.
[INAUDIBLE] playing, on the other hand,
well maybe had a little bit too much pedal
at the beginning, at least for
my taste, a little bit muddy.
But you can't say that it wasn't creative.
He buried the tempos.
He actually takes 14 seconds longer to
get through the same music than did and
the dynamic's very abnormal, so
as to tell the listener what
he thought this piece was all about, what
he wanted us to feel about this piece.
His performance was a bit more romantic,
more freedom for the interpreter.
Well, how would Beethoven
have played his own creation?
Course we'll never know.
He'd might actually, however, have been
perhaps closer to Zelman's interpretation.
Given all that was said by
Beethoven's contemporaries about his
wild swings of emotion and
his crashing and thrashing at the piano.
But does it matter how
Beethoven played this movement?
Isn't the important thing
how we hear it in our mind?
How we want to hear it?
Which is more important,
the creator or you or
I, the listener is creativity and art.
Is it not about change and changing our
understanding of the human experience.
Maybe you, the listener,
are the most important thing here.
you can make of this whatever you wish.
That's one of the wonderful
things about art.
So now, to give us a chance to unwind
here at the end of our session,
after this exciting performance,
let me play on a good Stanley,
another example of the elegiac sound.
Much like the first movement
in the Moonlight Sonata,
the elegiac sound of Beethoven,
the sort of hymn-like sound of Beethoven.
This is from the beginning of the slow
movement of the Arch Duke Trio.
Which takes us into the music
of Beethoven's heroic period.
So, here's a little encore, the slow
movement of Beethoven's Archduke Trio.
We'll hear the beginning and
then fade out.
[MUSIC]