[MUSIC]
In the last session we explored
Beethoven's music primarily, from his so
called, early period,
up to 1803 with Beethoven working
very much within the classical style.
Today we'll engage Beethoven, as he begins
to create what we call his heroic music,
our earliest soundings of romantic music.
We'll also hear a bit of music
from Beethoven's late period.
But why these periods?
Or units of time with Beethoven,
early, middle and late?
Do we think that way in
terms of other composers?
Do we talk about the early period or
late period of Bach or Mozart or
Heiden or Wagner?
No, generally not.
So Beethoven stands out.
He's unusual in the history
of music in this regard.
But what specifically are these
periods with Beethoven?
Well as you can see,
it's very straight forward here.
Early period, from his first compositions.
1792 up until 1802, 1803 he writes the,
Heroic Symphony, as we will see continues
to 1812, culminating in the 7th symphony.
And then, in the late Period,
not as much composition from Beethoven but
again we come back to big pieces such as
the Missa solemnis and the Ninth Symphony
and most particularly, the late piano
sonatas and the late string quartets.
Let's review what Beethoven sounded
like in 1800 to set a benchmark, for
what a revolutionary transformation he
underwent in just three short years.
Let's listen to a bit of the first
movement of Beethoven's symphony
number one.
We'll watch a wonderful group
of young performers, Israeli and
Palestinian, making music together
under the organization and
baton of maestro Daniel Baronborn.
This will also give us a chance to
review Sonata allegro form, and
I'll comment as we go.
[MUSIC]
First theme.
First theme up a step.
[MUSIC]
Led out by the violins.
And back down to the of that first theme.
[MUSIC]
Transition.
Going up the scale.
[MUSIC]
Hayden's coming up right there.
Second theme played out by the woodwinds.
[MUSIC]
Now dialogue between strings, and
woodwinds with that second theme.
[MUSIC]
Okay, and that gives us an idea.
All this sounds very much like Mozart.
And keep in mind that Beethoven was no
prodigy as a composer of symphonies.
He was 30 when he wrote
this first symphony.
Mozart died when he was 35,
that's how brightly his star burned.
Now let's listen to an audio clip from the
finale of Beethoven's Symphony number 3
to hear just how quickly and radically
Beethoven's symphonic style changed.
Remember, only three years later
here is Symphony number 3.
But the sound is very different.
[MUSIC]
So you hear the brasses.
You hear the slow,
majestic unfolding of the theme.
[MUSIC]
Well that's the he, heroic sound of
Beethoven that we first hear here in
Symphony number 3,
subtitled now the Eroica.
And it does sound very heroic, big,
powerful, grand, and glorious.
In our next segment we'll explore how
the symphony got it's name Eroica and
how Beethoven created
this new heroic sound.