[MUSIC]
The story of the Eroica goes back as
you may know, to the Neopolianic wars.
In the 1790s young
Consul Napoleon Bonaparte had taken over
the French government, and built a huge
war machine that quickly overran Italy and
then the German speaking Rhineland.
Because in theory Napoleon represented
a continuation of the values of
the French Revolution, [FOREIGN].
Beethoven was much taken with
his libertarian young hero,
Napoleon, seen here in the famous
portrait by Jacque-Louis David.
Napoleon Crossing The Alps, and
they had both much in common.
Napoleon and Beethoven were,
revolutionary figures in that they
detested the aristocracy and it's power.
So in 1802-1803, Beethoven was working on
a new symphony with Napoleon in mind,
and pretty much had finished it.
But when word came that Napoleon
had given himself a promotion and
declared himself emperor, well,
here we see the newly crowned
emperor painted by Jean Auguste Ingres and
needless to say, Beethoven was not pleased
with this development in his mind,
one tyrannical ruler had
just replaced another.
So in a fit of rage, he took a knife
to the page of this third symphony and
scratched out Napoleon's
name from the title,
as you can see here originally it was,
[FOREIGN] Luigi van Beethoven.
But where Bonaparte was,
now, there is just a hole.
Eventually he retitled the symphony for
a fallen hero.
A hero had clearly fallen certainly
in Beethoven's estimation.
When the work was published in 1806
as we see here the word Eroica,
is prominent at the top.
[FOREIGN] Which grand man
at this point isn't clear.
And just to finish the story of Napoleon
and Beethoven, Napoleon did invade Austria
and captured Vienna twice during
Beethoven's time in 1805 and in 1809.
During most of these years Beethoven was
living here, at the Pasqualati House.
Which happened to be on
the ramparts of the old fortress.
So, when Napoleon unleashed his hundreds
of cannons at the old city fortresses,
well, Beethoven had a ringside seat.
And although he was nearly deaf,
he was terrified by the sound and
the destruction of the cannons.
Well anyway enough about Beethoven and
Napoleon let's get to the music.
To do so we'll start with the opening
sounds of the Aurora Symphony.
Let's see whats revolutionary about it
as we listen you Identify three things,
three ways that in which this music
differs from Mozart or Haydn.
What is Beethoven doing here, that
Mozart for example would not have done?
And here again we're going
to employ a video made by
Steve Malinowski two hammer strokes
right at the beginning, and
then the theme appears not in the first
violins we would expect but in the chello.
[MUSIC]
Now the woodwinds take over the theme.
Takes it up a step.
Up another step
[MUSIC]
Now we get ready for
some heavy handed syncopation
[MUSIC]
More syncopation.
Now everybody in full orchestra.
[MUSIC]
Well that's just a peek at the first
movement here, of the Eroica.
The second movement is unusual too,
it's a funeral march,
Marche Funebre, as the title says.
You can think of Napoleon here as
the person for whom we have a funeral, or
perhaps any of those who died in
battle during these Napoleonic Wars.
And the sound is indeed funereal,
it's in a plotting C minor let
me play a bit at the keyboard.
[MUSIC]
With the finale of this symphony,
we return to the triadic theme,
under a slightly different guise,
and here it is on the screen.
Melodies up on the top also the triad.
[MUSIC]
There's our major triad up there and
there's a baseline underneath.
[MUSIC]
So Beethoven has two
themes operating here,
he's got a double theme and variation.
Sometimes he bury, varies the base,
sometimes he varies the more
ingratiating melody up on top.
Eventually, Beethoven turns this
lovely melody into a version for
five woodwind parts,
that we've heard before.
Let's review this.
[MUSIC]
So here's the theme now and the woodwinds.
Mostly oboe playing the melody.
[MUSIC]
This seems the counter point.
Clarionets the filler in the middle.
[MUSIC]
Horn comes in.
And towards the end of this movement,
Beethoven expands his melody into a grand,
triumphant sound, again foregrounding the
sound of the triads played by the brasses.
In this case, the blaring French horn so
triads, loud volume,
full brasses, major key.
These are the things that make
Beethoven's music sound heroic.
[MUSIC]
And you can hear the brasses,
particularly French horns and
trumpets that you see here.
[MUSIC]
All unfolding majestically and
rather slowly.
[MUSIC]
Pulling up into the time
Very grand indeed.
So that's the triumphant climax of
the finale of the Eroica Symphony.
Let's review what's special,
indeed revolutionary about it and
the heroic style of Beethoven generally.
As you can see here, it begins with
some opening hammer strokes dum, dum.
Then a triadic theme at the beginning.
[MUSIC]
The orchestration is a bit unusual in
the sense that we have the main theme,
actually rather down low in the chello,
and
we don't hear much from the first violin.
Toward the end of that passage that we
heard, the brasses are foreground and
the full orchestra plays prominently.
The slow fashion which this unfolds,
generally extends the length of
the symphonic movements by Beethoven.
Here you can see that the total symphony
would take the eroi, it would take
about 45 minutes, compared to roughly
25 for a symphony of Haydn or Mozart.
All of this again is caused by
the slowing down of the presentation of
the melodic ideas but an uptick,
building up of the volume.
Well what we just heard
a moment ago was the end,
of toward the end of the Eroica
symphony of Beethoven.
But we're only here at
the beginning of our exploration of
Beethoven's heroic period.