[MUSIC]
Probably the most famous moment.
The motive in all classic music,
is the beginning of
Beethoven's Symphony Number Five.
[MUSIC]
Likely, the only thing that's
equivalent to it in western culture,
is the line, To be or not to be,
from Shakespeare's Hamlet.
And in the that is what symphony is about.
What is it to be or
not to be this symphony?
Beethoven is reputed
to have said about it,
well, it's fate [SOUND]
knocking at the door.
How did Beethoven respond to fate?
How did he act?
Well, aggressively and emphatically and
judging ultimately from the final
chords of this symphony triumphantly.
This symphony has the general feeling
of struggle, Beethoven's struggle,
the struggle of all of us,
against the forces of nature.
Maybe against the forces of human nature.
From an uncertain beginning
to a triumphant end.
Symphony number five was premiered
in Vienna on a bitterly cold night,
22nd of December 1808 along
with his sixth symphony and
other compositions in a concert
that lasted four hours.
Beethoven had organized it and
had the audience sit there freezing for
four hours in an unheated theater.
But in the sense Beethoven didn't
care much about audience comfort,
he just cared about the music.
Here's the outside of the theatre.
Beethoven actually lived upstairs
in this theatre for a while.
And here's the inside of it as it looks
today, and here's the theatre as it looks.
In Beethoven's day,
you can see down there at the bottom,
right at bottom left you can
see the orches, orchestral pit.
Immediately up above that is
the emperor's box, with the red curtains.
On the stage, well, lo and
behold, we see horses.
This was something akin to
Radio City Musical Hall in New York City.
It was an entertainment performance space.
Again, this is where Beethoven's famous
Symphony number 5 was premiered in 1808,
and here's the autograph of
the opening page of that symphony.
Now, I know it's difficult to see this,
but
if you look to,
let me see if I can use the pointer.
Here we go, here we've got some of
the the string parts up here and you
can see the three short values that you're
familiar with in and it goes over to here.
The long note with a fermata.
So you can see it's not a very
economical use of this space here.
All right, now,
we're going to examine this Symphony.
But first, just a bit of music theory.
We all know about the short, short,
short, long rhythmic motif,
that predominates here.
But there's something else,
a diminished triad.
Now in music of course, we have major
triads and we have minor triads.
There's also a third kind of a triad,
called a diminished triad.
It's made up of only minor thirds.
So let's play a major triad.
[SOUND] There's a major triad, now I'm
just going to lower the middle note there.
[SOUND] That makes a minor.
Triad but supposing I lower
both middle and top note?
[SOUND] Well, I get that.
And that's a diminished tri, triad.
I can e, add one more minor third up
there on top, I get a diminished seventh.
It's a tension building chord.
And we can take this when it comes in
rising sequence, it's full of tension.
Okay, talk now probably oh, I don't know,
five, six, seven minutes about this,
about this particular symphony.
And let me get my glasses on to do so.
So you know the beginning.
We start this way.
I'm working off of what's called just
a piano score of the full score.
Piano, two hand version of the full score.
[MUSIC]
We would expect it to go.
So it's an odd beginning.
[MUSIC]
Sort of that punch in the nose of that
theme, but it never gets resolved.
He moves away from it.
[MUSIC]
We have a pause there and
then it starts out again.
[MUSIC]
And then we have the descent.
Building, coming down, just on the
diminished chord again, diminished sound.
Then eventually he works that through,
builds up a little climax.
[MUSIC]
This is transition.
Top of that transition line.
[MUSIC]
Then this chord, major chord.
And then this chord,
which is another presentation of our.
[MUSIC]
Diminish chord until we reach.
Pause, and then we have our short,
short, short, long.
[MUSIC]
But then, he extends it by two notes.
And he uses that as a modulation
into the second theme.
[MUSIC]
Now the second theme,
as is usually the case,
is lyrical, sort of sweet,
tender sounding.
[MUSIC]
But did you ever notice, and it takes
a good conductor to make this come out,
what the basses are doing underneath?
[MUSIC]
So we have a little counterpoint,
it's like the Jaws theme,
every time you think it's safe to come
out of the water, lurking underneath.
[MUSIC]
Is that motif.
After the second theme he builds up
through rising melodic sequence.
[MUSIC]
Continues to build off of that
up until the point way up here.
[MUSIC]
And then finally, when he resolves that.
Concluding theme.
[MUSIC]
And that takes us to
the end of trhe exposition.
The development begins in a odd way,
but developments often do.
Begins this fashion.
[MUSIC]
A very dissonant interval
is encountered right there.
But it only gives us that at
the beginning of the development section.
It's like holding up a sign saying
disruption is coming our way.
We are in a new section.
And he works through this section.
[MUSIC]
And so on and
then takes us through a series of
modulations modulating to there and
then again.
[MUSIC]
To a new key here.
So we're moving along, modulating, and the
he starts to build up this sound again.
[MUSIC]
Well, that was a very strange moment.
Strange on a, on a number of counts.
Here we are right in the epicenter
of the entire movement.
Right in the dead middle of
the development section, and
we're sitting here playing
this kind of chord.
Almost as if we've been electrocuted by
the, the rhythmic energy of this piece.
But at the same time,
it's a compression of this energy.
We're doing to just one note,
instead of short, short long.
Maybe it's just short, short,
short, everything is short.
And of course the tension is cause
here by, we've got this chord,
diminished cord and then diminished chord.
This is a radically different sound.
Just 15 or so years earlier, we would have
heard from Mozart this sort of thing.
[MUSIC]
A.
That's what the audience expected and
instead of that they
get this sort of sound.
[MUSIC]
They must have thought Beethoven
was nuts at that particular,
at that particular moment.
Well, that's the epicenter
of the movement.
Then he begins to back off of it.
The music becomes quieter
becomes more consonant.
[MUSIC]
Just moving his motive
through different keys.
[MUSIC]
And now he reduces that transition motive.
Richard took four and
sometimes six pitches, down to just two.
One, two, one, two, one, two, one.
[MUSIC]
Now just down to one,
because it's just at the octave.
Here's a new one, but one, one, one.
So he's reduced the whole thing
really down to just one sound.
At this point the orchestra
wants to get back in.
[MUSIC]
But that one note won't
let it back into it.
It keeps repeating again and
again and again.
Finally.
[MUSIC]
The orchestra more or
less breaks down the door.
[MUSIC]
To get back in.
And it does get back in
with the main theme.
[MUSIC]
Now something very strange happens.
Right in the middle of all
this tension with this.
[MUSIC]
Lovely oboe solo.
An oboe cadenza, what's he doing?
I think what he's doing here is trying
to release all of this tension that
has been built up in the,
in the development section.
When I was a kid, my mother to cook on
something called a pressure cooker.
I don't know if they have anymore, but
you'd put all this meat in there and
you'd turn up the heat, and
there'd be this valve up on top.
And if you didn't loosen that valve,
that thing would blow up.
And one time it did blow up, it blew up
all over my mother's kitchen ceiling.
Because that release
valve wasn't turned on.
So this is a, a sort of musical moment.
[MUSIC]
Where Beethoven is just letting the
tension out and then he will pick it up.
[MUSIC]
[NOISE] With a chord below it, but
again it's that tension filled
diminished chord underneath.
Well, that's a bit of these first
movements, and of the ideas of
the first movement here of the fifth
symphony, it's filled with intensity.
It's filled with anxiety, because of
the diminished triad, because of the,
of the insistent [SOUND] rhythmic
motor and also because of compression.
This is actually,
although it's very intense,
this is actually a very short
movement by Beethoven's standards.
This combination of compression,
intensity, and
insistence of the rhythmic motive
that makes this movement exceptional.
The second movement begins in
a diametrically opposed way,
with a long, lyrical,
lovely theme in the strings.
But soon the brasses enter with
a contrasting heroic theme.
And again, we hear here that short,
short, short, long idea.
[MUSIC]
Short, short, short long.
All played by the brasses which once
more makes it sound very heroic.
Now, Beethoven does something use,
unusual here with regard to the third and
fourth movements.
He links the third movement to
the fourth movement by means of I,
a gigantic crescendo.
A Beethovenian swell as it's called,
though maybe we should call
it a Beethovenian tsunami.
It's entirely made up of the same pitches,
and
these pitches continue to turn,
or continue to twist.
They circle around.
[MUSIC]
And then gradually the pitches raise
a little bit as the volume raises until
we have this gigantic swell, this great
wave of sound come over top of us.
[MUSIC]
Brasses are in at the top of the line.
With the triadic theme.
[MUSIC]
And on it goes.
Eventually, because this movement,
indeed this symphony,
has taken several surprising turns,
at the end Beethoven must prove that
he's not surprising us once again.
Not deviating off course.
Not crying musical wolf.
So he reassures us with,
with what is arguably most over the top
final cadence ever written
in the history of music.
[MUSIC]
[APPLAUSE] Well, again,
Beethoven the Great Communicator.
We always know where we stand with
Beethoven, what his message is.
And here the message is simple, the end,
the end, the end, the end, the end.
Let's review what's special now about
Beethoven's Symphony Number Five.
First of all,
it doesn't have a nickname oddly enough.
We've got the Eroica as number three,
we've got the Pastoral as number six.
We have this strange beginning [SOUND] as,
as I say here,
something of a sucker punch, a surprise
punch in the nose at the beginning.
There's the emphasis a constant
emphasis on the short,
short, short long rhythmic motive, and
almost all the material is derived from
that single motive or single musical cell.
There's the importance
of the diminished chord,
that tension filled diminished chord,
particularly in the first movement.
And there's the linking of the third and
fourth movements by means
of a Beethovenian swell.
That's the first time that had ever.
Never been done in music.
There is the bulking up of the orchestra
for the finale of this symphony and
the emphasizing of sound for the sake
of sound, sound for the sake of sound.
As we'll see here in our next session.