[MUSIC]
Sorry to leave you hanging there.
Did that intentionally.
The title of this segment is
Beethoven's Gift To Music: Sound.
That seems like a silly thing to say.
That Beethoven's gift to music was sound,
but in a sense it was.
He was the first composer to
create a sound that was so big,
and so gorgeous that we, the listener,
well we just wanna wallow in it.
By comparison, here's the sound of
a typical big symphony, by Haydn, and for
Mozart too, for that matter.
But here's one by Haydn.
[MUSIC]
End of Haydn's 94th Symphony.
Now that's a big sound for Haydn.
That's as big as it gets.
Now here's a moment in
a symphony by Beethoven.
[MUSIC]
Well obviously,
that's a huge buildup of volume.
There's really only one musical
idea there that gets repeated over,
and over, and over, and over again.
Iteration, as more and
more instruments are added to play it and
the volume of sound builds.
And almost inevitably with Beethoven,
as the volume sound builds to a climax,
the brasses enter with
an heroic sounding theme.
Here's another example of Beethoven
using the same sort of musical gambit
creating a grand gesture.
As I like to call it.
This one is from the overture
to Leonore Number Three.
And for this, we'll show an image drawn
from YouTube that's really a promo for
the London Philharmonic and
50 great classical hits.
But it's kind of fun to watch.
[MUSIC]
And Beethoven not only wallowed in sound,
per se,
just by itself,
merely to build a crescendo.
Often, he seemed to do so, just because
he liked that particular sound.
He was prepared to sit there for
a long time, because he liked the sound.
This tended to make, of course,
his pieces much longer, and
here's a particularly lovely example
of that from his sixth symphony,
the Pastoral Symphony, Symphony of 1808.
And before we begin,
here's what he's doing, he's essentially.
[MUSIC]
It's really just coming down a triad
there, so let's give a listen.
It's the autograph on the screen.
[MUSIC]
Om, there's the bottom note,
your sitting on that note, om, om.
[MUSIC]
Finally is moving.
Bass is playing,
more and more volume.
That was lovely.
I really enjoyed that.
By the way on the screen you can see the
autograph of this Pastoral symphony here.
But he's not finished.
[MUSIC]
As a matter of fact, he's back,
he's starting again in another pitch.
[MUSIC]
All the way down there.
It just sits on that, om.
[MUSIC]
Finally he moves, finally he moves
A long, long passage.
Just one sound, but
the sound is luxurious, it's gorgeous.
Well how did he create this luxurious or
gorgeous sound?
Well he did it in part by
adding new instruments.
Let's go back to his 5th Symphony.
As you can see here In the 5th Symphony,
Beethoven adds for the first time,
the contrabassoon.
Now the contrabassoon actually
plays the lowest pitches of any
instrument in a symphony orchestra.
The lowest note.
Lower than the double bass.
So Beethoven is bulking up
the lower sounds of the orchestra.
And in addition, he added trombones to
the symphony for this Symphony Number 5.
Now that seems a strange thing to say,
because trombones have really been
around since the 14th century.
But they'd been used exclusively
in religious music and
in operas,
especially to signify the sounds of hell.
But here Beethoven uses the trombone
in a symphony to enrich the sounds of
the brasses, creating this big
robust brass, in the vernacular,
ballsy sound, that became part and
partial of romantic music.
Let's listen to a bit of the sound
of the trombone as heard here for
the first time in a symphony here in
the final movement of the finale of
Beethoven's Symphony Number five.
We heard this before but let's focus
particularly on the brasses now.
[MUSIC]
The trombones are playing underneath.
And then they'll be foregrounded in just
a second with part two of this first.
[MUSIC]
And here we go.
Oops we're not gonna go,
but I'll play it for you.
[MUSIC]
Trombone solo.
And on it goes.
But the addition of the contrabassoon and
trombone weren't all,
Beethoven also here in the fifth
symphony adds a piccolo thereby
expanding the top range of the orchestra.
Now Beethoven most
effectively used the piccolo,
a smaller high flute of course, in
the storm scene of his pastoral symphony.
Here provides a sort of
sonic special effect
of the wind whistling at the top of
the sonic spectrum during the storm.
This high piccolo can cut cleanly
through even the densest
sort of orchestral texture.
Let's give a listen.
[MUSIC]
Hear it up on top?
So Beethoven adds new instruments
to the orchestra, top and bottom.
And accordingly he creates
a larger orchestra, new woodwinds,
new brasses were added.
and to balance him, well, he needed more
strings, if Mozart had thirty, thirty five
in his orchestra, Beethoven usually around
sixty players in his, twice the number.
And similarly, here we see Mozart's piano
on the left, and Beethoven's on the right.
Mozart's piano weighed exactly,
still weighs that,
because it still exists,
weights 187 pounds.
Beethoven's Broadwood piano,
which also still exist,
weighs about 400 pounds, more than twice
as much weight, twice as much volume.
So technology, in some ways, has allowed
Beethoven to create this bigger sound,
and to delight in it, to stop the music.
I don't need more motifs,
don't need more themes, more melodies.
I just wanna hear that sound.
I wanna hear that sound.
Do you hear that, do you hear that,
do you hear that?
That's what he seems to be saying in so
much of his music.
Beethoven could make the sound bigger,
hit the ball farther,
because he had new and better equipment.
A silly comparison I know,
but it makes a point.
Well, let's see what we've
learned in this segment.
Let's review, by means of a quiz.
I'll let you study for a few moments.
And then we'll talk about the answer.
Okay, let's see how you did, now.
Let's check out the incorrect answer.
Okay, good for you.
C is correct.
Beethoven actually slows down
the rate at which musical ideas,
new motives, melodies,
harmonies, etcetera,
slows down the rate at which
musical ideas come to us.
Because he wanted to take more time to
stop and enjoy the sound of the moment.
For him more than any previous composer,
the sound was the theme.