[MUSIC]
Remember this image?
It was created by
an artist in 1938 to give
a sense of what Beethoven's life was like
as he reached middle age and beyond.
Although fictitious,
it does contain many elements of truth.
The mess all around,
the broken piano strings,
the bowl of porridge on the keyboard.
And especially the ear trumpet,
lower left, that helped Beethoven hear.
Let's visit the bear in his lair.
Here's a 19th century map of Vienna.
We've actually seen it before.
Although Beethoven moved a lot,
and sometimes had two or
three abodes simultaneously,
in his late middle age, his most used
apartment was on the ramparts of Vienna,
on the walls protecting the old city.
Remember Napoleon's bombing there in 1809.
And here's how the same building looks
today, still up on the ramparts.
Called the Pasqualati House.
Let's go inside.
Here we see a piano from Beethoven's day,
though not one that
Beethoven himself played.
We'll see one of these later.
What was life like here
in Beethoven's apartment?
Well, a contemporary observer visiting
from Paris about 1809 tells us
what he saw.
Quote, imagine all that is most filthy and
untidy, puddles on the floor,
a rather old grand piano covered in
dust and laden with piles of music.
Beneath it, I do not exaggerate,
an unemptied chamberpot.
The little walnut desk
next to the piano was
evidently accustomed to having the
contents of the inkwell spilled over it.
The chairs were covered with plates full
of the remains of the previous evening's
meal and with clothes.
Now, the person who saw Beethoven the most
in his last years was a lad of 12.
The son of an old family friend of
Beethoven, one Gerhard von Breuning,
who tagged along after the aging composer,
and later wrote down what he saw.
Here's one story the young Breuning tells
about Beethoven, now completely deaf,
as the composer enters a cafe.
Here's a cafe like the Frauenhuber Cafe
that we saw earlier.
So, Beethoven comes in and he sits down.
And this is where his music was performed,
this is where he often had dinner.
He comes in, and he sits down.
Let me read you a quote
here from Von Bruening.
He knocked for the waiter.
[SOUND] Who did not come at once.
Then he knocked again.
[SOUND] And while waiting, he took out his
music notebook and started to compose.
Finally the waiter appeared but the deaf
master was no longer aware of him.
Since Beethoven was a steady customer, the
waiter went away, and Beethoven wrote for
a long time, deep in thought.
Finally, he closed his book and
asked for the bill to pay for his meal,
but he had neither received nor
eaten anything.
This is what Von Breuning had to
say regarding Beethoven's demeanor.
He was neither handsome nor elegant,
in fact, he was unkempt and
even wild in his appearance as you
can see from this direct quote.
And his behavior was sometimes,
well, downright bizarre,
as we can see from this next
quote that I'll read here.
"He always had the habit, when he had been
at his desk for a long time composing,
then he felt that his head was overheated,
of rushing over to the washstand and
pouring jugs of water over his
head." All of this was done in
the greatest haste in order not
to lose the flow of his ideas.
That's interesting.
Without his noticing it the water he
poured over his head would sometimes go
all over the floor and even through
the ceiling to the floor below and
this occasionally led to disagreeable
situations with the people downstairs.
[LAUGH] I bet they did.
Another quote,
another characteristic of his
was the vehemence with which he would
discuss subjects that interested him.
And sometimes, as he walked up and
down the room during such discussions,
he would spit on the mirror,
instead of out the window,
without noticing the difference.
Well, by the 1820s,
Beethoven had changed apartments yet
again, now to the house
of the Black Spaniards.
And you can see that here on
the map with the blue star.
The building once existed, but
was torn down around 1900.
But there's an early photograph of it,
with my arrow pointing to the windows
that were Beethoven's windows.
Young Von Bruening's detailed
description of this apartment
allows us to reconstruct it.
And as you can see,
I'll use a little pointer here.
So, we come into, up the stairs.
He always lived in these
top floor apartments.
Comes into an ante-chamber,
took off his coat.
Come into this entrance hall here
that was filled with portraits
of some relatives and
other people of interest to him.
This was his music room over here where
he kept essentially the scores of music,
existing scores of music.
But his principal music
room was over here.
Here he had two pianos, and
we're going to take a look at
one of those two pianos now.
Here's an engraving made only
a few days after his death.
Through the window we you
can see the moonlight and
the spire, the Saint Steven's Cathedral
in the background.
And now look.
This is very interesting.
Look how somebody has tidied up the floor.
Beethoven's music is all now
neatly stacked down below.
Actually, there were two
grand pianos in this room.
A Graft that we don't see here on the
right, and an English Broadwood given to
him in 1817 on the left, that we do see.
Okay, so this was the essential music
room and it had the pianos in it.
Let's go back to our floor plan now.
Now, remember that Bruening said that
Beethoven didn't actually write music
at the piano.
Why would he want to?
He was deaf anyway.
He couldn't hear.
But he composed instead
at a small walnut desk,
which by this time he kept in
a separate room over here.
And that desk also survives today.
It's in the Beethoven House in Bonn.
Isn't that interesting?
But let's go back to our floor plan.
And here we see not only the pianos and
these two windows, but
Beethoven had his bed in
this essential music room.
And it was here that he died in 1827.
Now here's and engraving of the death
mask of Beethoven by a well-respected
Viennese artist, Josef Dannhauser, done
only a day or two after Beethoven's death.
And now another contemporary
engraving showing
Beethoven's body being carried out of his
apartment that's the arrow on the right,
with his corpse and
the pallbearers the arrows on the left.
It was taken to a local church that church
still exists, here we see it on the left,
for the funeral and then sometimes later
it was carried and ultimately interred
in the Zentralfriedhof outside
of Vienna where it rests today.
Nearby are Schubert and Brahms by the way.
But let's look again at this
image of Beethoven's funeral.
Look at the crowd.
More than 20,000 people,
one in every ten citizens in Vienna
turned out for this funeral.
That's far more per capita than turned
out for the funeral of Michael Jackson.
Schools were closed and
the army was called out to maintain order.
Beethoven had become a rock star.