[MUSIC]
Romance, romantic.
What does that term, romance mean?
Well we have romance languages,
meaning those that derive from Latin,
French, and Italian.
We have romance, meaning love and
love relationships.
A romantic, well,
someone who is eternally idealistic.
Now, these last two senses,
Love and Idealism,
are associated with sentiments important
in the west during the 19th century.
So we call this the Romantic Era.
Here we see the dates of
the Romantic Period, roughly 1820 to 1900.
But all of this is very fluid and these
periods overlap, as we've said before.
But why look at this dreary slide when
we have images like this to look at.
Here is Eugen Delacroix's Romeo and
Juliet.
This was the century in which their
romance and those of others, Paolo and
Francesca de Rimini and Tristan and
Isolde, for example, were revivified.
So, idealistic love.
Romance and Romantic Narratives are at
the center of the Romantic Sensibility.
Another almost obsession
with romantics was Nature.
Here we see a slide of John Martin's
MacBeth on the Heaths, a vast landscape.
Nature too worked her magic on
the minds of the romantics.
Wild, untamed, all powerful nature.
We see this in the art and
we hear it in the music.
Beirden's Pastoral Symphony,
Schubert's The Trout Quintet,
Strauss's Alpine Symphony, are typical.
Here's an example by Johannes Brahms
written at the end of the 19th century.
It's a song with German lyrics, and
as you'll see from the English translation
it's full of references to nature.
Dark night, mild wind, flowers the moon,
the stars the birdsong and so on.
[MUSIC]
Sometimes,
as in
the
song,
human's
and
nature
are in
harmony.
Often a human soul contemplates
the wonders of nature.
As in this image, by one of my favorite
painter's of the romantic era.
The German, Caspar David Friedrich.
This painting is called,
appropriately enough, The Dreamer.
But here notice the church,
a man made construction,
how it bonds as one with
the trees in the background.
There's no barrier between the human and
the natural world here in
the imagination of The Dreamer.
Dreaming too was part of the aesthetic or
Romantic music.
With this image of The Dreamer on the
screen, let me play as a bit of background
music a portion of Robert Schumann's
piano piece, Traumerei Dreaming.
Composed as you see in 1838.
[MUSIC]
But the Romantic period was also an age
in which dreams could go tragically array
with depictions of nightmares of
the fantastic and the phantasmagorical.
Victor Hugo's The Hunchback of Notre Dame
and Mary Shelly's Frankenstein and
Francisco Goya's Saturn eating his young,
from the Prado in Madrid, as shown here.
In music the horrific is audible in pieces
such as Mendelssohn's Varporgisnaught and
Musorgsky's Night on Bald Mountain.
[MUSIC]
Well, that's enough of that for
the moment, let's fade that out.
The 19th century is also the age
of poetry and the romantic poets.
Victor Hugo and friends, Goethe, Heine,
Eichendorff in Germany and of course,
the English Romantics of Wordsworth,
Keats, Shelley, and Lord George Byron.
Here's a slide of Byron.
He traveled over the Alps,
swam the Hellespont, fought and died for
Greek independence, and seems to have
had an affair with his half-sister.
That bad, and dangerous to know,
was the saying of the day, about Byron.
Mad, bad, and dangerous to know.
Well, many romantic artists seemed
to have been such, as well.
But Byron was also a gifted poet,
who inspired many musicians.
Here's a 19th century printed
volume of Byron's poetry.
Who bought these books?
This flood of romantic poetry that
appeared on the scene in the early 1800s.
Well, buyers from the increasingly
large middle class.