[MUSIC]
When I was a student taking
history courses, I was puzzled.
Almost every period that I studied
discussed the rise of the middle class.
And I suppose that's true,
in every age, after the middle ages.
In the middle ages there
was only one class.
High clergy on one side and
the aristocracy.
Well, they were the 1% and everybody else,
well, they were on the on side.
The peasants were on the other side.
There after Little by little the middle
class seems to have been on a constant
rise down to the present day.
And this was particularly
true in the 19th century.
In the United States, the number of
people in the urban middle class
went from roughly 5 to 35% of
the population during the 19th century.
In Britain,
incomes doubled between 1850 and 1906.
So too, a similar growth in
the numbers of homes that had
pianos at the center of what we, in the
United States, would call a living room.
But they, in those days, called a talking
room or parlor, really a gathering center.
And at the epicenter of the parlor was
the piano, around which the family
gathered before the days of TV and
computers, for fun and for relaxation.
This was the center of a new and
important kind of music making.
Private, domestic music making, but still
music making with aspirations to high art.
Here again, is the entertainment
center in Beethoven's day,
The Public Theater Opera House,
where Beethoven's Symphony No.
5 has premiered in 1808.
But now,
here's another kind of music center.
One that developed 15 or 20 years later.
We're now in the home of Middle class or
Upper middle class family.
This in fact, is the home of
one Joseph von Spaum in Vienna.
He was a friend and
patron of the composer Franz Schubert.
Senior Michael Vogl is at the center,
there at the left arrow,
and composer Franz Schubert
accompanies him, seated at the piano.
In early 19th century Vienna,
they called such gatherings Schubertiades,
because only the music of
Schubert was performed.
A Schubertiade then,
was a domestic gathering, a party,
that featured the songs and
dances of Franz Schubert.
And look closely,
the ladies still look splendid,
the gentleman are still wearing neck ties,
but everyone is now looking inward.
This is not art for external large
scale public consumption, but private,
domestic music making in an upper middle
class home, as the furnishing suggests.
Now, here's that same scene,
I emphasize again,
the same scene reillustrated
some 30 years later.
Art, as is true with history,
can be manipulated to tell more or
less any story the creator or
the historian wants.
Schubert's reputation has grown greatly
since his death [LAUGH] in 1828.
And so has Schubert.
He's now much larger in this painting.
And where's the singer Michael Vogel?
Well, he was originally there, but
now he's disappeared entirely.
Leaving Schubert the center of attention.
Revisionist history, so
let's focus on Franz Schubert, and
find out more about him.