[MUSIC]
Franz Schubert was born in Vienna in 1797.
He was the son of a school
principal who encouraged
the boy's obvious musical talent.
When he was 11,
young Schubert competed for, and
won, a place as a boy soprano in
the famous Imperial Court Chapel.
The boys of which,
their descendants at least,
are still known today as
the Vienna Boys Choir.
At the age of 15, Schubert's voice broke,
as he said, he croaked his last.
And so he was gradually eased out of
the choir, and out of the choir school,
and when on to earn an effective
teaching certificate at a local college.
So he tried his hand at grade school
teaching in his father's school,
but with no particular success.
So Schubert quit his day job, and although
he gave music lessons from time to time,
and had some small income from
publishing his songs, for the most part,
Schubert live a Bohemian existence,
no steady income.
Roaming with friends and
mentors in downtown Vienna as
the situation required, and
spending much of his evening pub crawling,
as he called it, with his friends.
But composer Schubert was
remarkably productive,
producing nearly a thousand
compositions and
more than 600 songs in his short life
of just 31 years, yes, 31 years.
Here's Schubert in his youth,
wearing his iconic glasses.
And here's Schubert in his late 20s,
one of the last portraits of him.
Mozart, Hayden, Beethoven and Schubert,
well they were all 5 feet 5 inches tall or
less, and
Schubert was the shortest of them all.
His diminutive size and glasses
exempted him from military services,
a boon to music history.
Anyway, although Schubert wrote in all
genres of music, operas, religious music,
chamber music, piano sonatas, and
symphonies, he's known today firstly,
as a composer of art songs,
as we said, more than 600 of them.
Indeed, Schubert created the art
song of classical music,
the art song as we know it
in classical music today.
The Germans call the 19th century
art song, and we often do as well,
we English speakers do as well, they
called it a Lied, Lieder in the plural.
The high art song with piano
accompaniment of the 19th century.
To the extent that Schubert was known at
all in Vienna, and he didn't really become
famous until after his death,
he was known as the composer of Lieder.
But let's back up to
Schubert's early years.
Indeed, he was a prodigy as a composer,
like Mozart before him.
Here's a song Schubert wrote in 1816,
when he was 19.
It's about a fish, a trout, again,
more nature in the romantic era.
The visuals of this video
are a little bit silly, but
we get a good English
translation of the German and
the singer here is the incomparable Leider
specialist Dietrich Fischer-Dieskau
[MUSIC]
Phrase one, part one.
Part two.
[MUSIC]
Phrase two, part one.
Phrase two, part two.
[MUSIC]
Phrase two, part two repeated.
Now because this is a strophic song,
the music is gonna start all
over again with a new text.
Phrase one, part one
[MUSIC]
Phrase one, part two.
Phrase two, part one.
[MUSIC]
Phrase two, part two.
And phrase two part two, repeated.
And that's probably enough of that,
he faded out right about here, lovely.
What we're paying attention
to in particular here,
is the ingratiating melody, and
the bubbling accompaniment.
It's typical of the freshness and
sweetness of the Schubert sound.
Now Schubert knew a good thing when he
heard it, or at least when he created it.
And as it heightened before him,
Schubert took an excellent song tune and
made it even greater,
made even more out of it.
He used it again as
a piece of chamber music,
specifically here in a quintet for
piano and strings a few year later.
So again,
he's taking this preexisting song, and
he's gonna use it as a movement in
a quintet for a piano and strings.
As you watch this video from
a group of Korea, first a question,
which instrument is
playing Schubert's song?
[MUSIC]
Tempo's a little bit slower.
And notice now in the chamber version,
Schubert repeats
the phrases of the melody,
this is phrase one repeated.
[MUSIC]
And of course the question was,
who's playing the melody?
Well the first violinist
is playing the melody.
Now we're going on to phrase two.
[MUSIC]
That's the viola.
And back to the first violin,
this is the end of our second phrase.
[MUSIC]
Now the piano will jump in,
with the melody ornamented.
[MUSIC]
Repeat, the other strings
are just adding counterpoint,
fast counterpoint against the piano.
[MUSIC]
The second phrase.
There's our violist
providing counterpoint.
Here's the unusual distribution.
We don't really have
a string quartet here, but
a quartet first violin, viola,
cello, and double bass.
There's no second violin, the double
bass replaces the second violin here.
Who's got the melody now?
[MUSIC]
Well not the first violin, he's playing
counterpoint, mostly scalar fashion.
[MUSIC]
There it is to the right,
the viola has the melody.
[MUSIC]
Here's our second phrase, viola.
The piano is just answering,
responding to the cello.
[MUSIC]
Next, a variation.
Double bass now has the melody,
as you can see.
[MUSIC]
Okay, let's phase it out here,
with a sense of the wonderful quality of
what is arguably one of the funniest,
and most ingratiating pieces in
the entire repertoire of chamber music.
This music built on
a song by Franz Schubert.
And this gives you a sense of
the seemingly effortless ease,
with which Schubert could
write this sort of melody.
Shubert's like Mozart in this regard,
seemingly effortless lyricism,
as we heard here, in the case of our scaly
friends Trout, in the Trout quintet.
But let's back up further to a Lied that
Schubert wrote a year earlier, in 1815,
Erlkonig, or Erlking, then as now,
Schubert's best known work.