[MUSIC]
Here we see Schubert's first
published work, the Art Song or
Lied Erlkonig, Elf King in english.
This wasn't Schubert's
earliest composition.
But it was the first one he
was able to get published,
as it says here on the title page,
1st Werk.
And it became a smash hit.
In the course of the 19th century,
nearly 100 composers did arrangements or
covers of it.
Indeed this one song alone made Schubert's
reputation in the 19th century.
How old was he when he wrote this
masterpiece, this song for eternity?
The ripe old age of 18,
which causes me to ask,
who wrote the greatest piece,
a masterpiece, at the earliest age?
Mendelson, with his octet,
Mozart, Schubert?
Paul McCartney,
with Love Love Love Me Do, he was 15.
Well it's difficult to say, but
one could make a strong case for
Schubert and his Lied Erlkonig.
What's this song about?
Well to know what any song's about,
you just have to look at the lyrics.
Unlike purely instrumental music, in
which the music itself does the talking,
here with a song
the lyrics tell the story.
What's interesting is that,
unlike the Beatles say,
who generally wrote their own music and
the lyrics, in the Romantic era,
none of the great composers was
a great poet of song lyrics.
Each went to a work of a poet,
opened up this book of poetry, and
found a suitable poem and set it to music.
So let's look at the poem Erlkonig.
Schubert found the poem in
the works of the famous poet
Johann Wolfgang von Goethe.
Here we see the 18 year old Schubert's
original score set in Goethe's poetry.
And we can follow,
let's see if my cursor is working here.
There we go.
And here is the beginning of the text.
[FOREIGN]
And
so on it goes.
Now there were two kinds of poetry, or
two principal kinds of poetry in
the 19th century, lyric and narrative.
Lyric poetry was usually about love or
nature, and
was usually set in strophic form.
Narrative poetry, on the other hand, tells
a story, usually a well-known story, or
a legend in the form of
what is called a ballad.
A ballad is a long, sad story or
legend set as poetry.
Now, the Erlkonig is an old
Nordic folk story or legend
about the king of elves who, if he laid
on his hands on the child brought evil,
indeed, killed the child
simply by his touch.
So don't expect a happy ending
here from the Erlkonig in
our poetic ballad by Goethe, no sir.
Here's the text.
Let me try reading it to you in my not so
good German, and
you try following along, the English.
It's important, very important here,
that we understand the text
of this particular Lied.
[FOREIGN]
And as
you will
hear,
Schubert
treats
Goethe's
ballad
Erlkonig
as
a through
composed
Lied, no
repetition
in the
music.
Again, it unfolds continuously
from beginning to end.
Okay, the Schubert Erlkonig challenge,
how does Schubert
use a host of musical gestures, musical
symbols, to paint this frightful scene?
And indeed many artists did paint and
continue to paint
right down to the present day
the frightful scene of the Erlkonig.
Here you see that of Moritz Schwind
a good friend of Schubert who knew
what Schubert had in mind.
So back to our challenge,
your task is to identify at least
five musical gestures used to characterize
the actors and the events in this drama.
How does he depict, for example,
the galloping horse, the steady father,
the excitable son, and
his growing anxiety?
The Erlkonig in his charming ways and the
Erlkonig with his deadly trick, the horse,
slowing down, and the tragic end,
how did Schubert depict all this in music?
Well, we're going to follow along with
a score that integrates a recording and
some other information about the structure
of Schubert's harmonic language,
a score, a video here,
prepared by my colleague, David Thomas.
As we go along, I'll identify for
your who is speaking.
And you think about what the musical
gesture is that Schubert employs
to underscore, to heighten though music
the dramatic story that's about to unfold.
[MUSIC]
Okay, narrator begins.
Who rides so
late through night and the wind?
[MUSIC]
Father is about to enter.
Whoops, that's the father's song.
Here's the song
[MUSIC]
Now the father replies.
Now first appearance of the friendly,
trustworthy, Elkonig.
[MUSIC]
And the accompaniment changes.
The boy.
[MUSIC]
What's happening to his pitch level?
And now where do we go for the father?
[MUSIC]
[INAUDIBLE] of rain.
Back to the Erlking, again.
How does the music change here?
[MUSIC]
The boy, has his music changed yet again?
Back to the father.
[MUSIC]
How has the music not changed here?
And watch out, it will take you by force.
The boy is terrified.
[MUSIC]
Vocal range.
Back to the narrator.
[MUSIC]
It arrives at the end with
the doctor awaiting him.
[MUSIC]
The horse stops.
Not bad for an 18 year old.
Well, how did you do?
Let me give you a chance
to think about it.
Think about it for a moment.
Well rather than just have me give
you the answers, why not submit yours
in the form of a quiz, a reinforcement
quiz at the end of this segment.
Well, as mentioned Schubert's Erlkonig,
because of the extraordinary
drama of this song, became the best
known art song of the 19th century.
Painted and repainted and rearranged by
almost anyone who had access to a piano.
What had started out as
private domestic music
in the midst of a middle
class Schubertiad became so
popular that it couldn't be
contained within a living room.
It had to be moved outside and
onto the large concert stage.
Here on the screen you see the musical
contents of a program that
concert pianist Clara Schumann played
in 1862 in the Erard concert hall,
a large public hall in Paris.
We needn't go through
all the program here,
in which Clara was featured
as a soloist and accompanist.
But you see that Schubert's
show-stopping Erlkoenig was saved for
a rousing conclusion at
the end of the first half and
Robert Schumann's piano collection
Carnaval at the very end.
So let's move on in our discussion of the
art song now to Robert and Clara Schumann.