[MUSIC]
Here we see an early photograph.
A daguerreotype of the 1840s
showing Clara and Robert Schumann.
They're music history's only power couple,
each a powerful creator in his or
her own right.
Robert Schumann went to university
the prestigious University
of Heidelberg in western
Germany to study law.
Then, as now parents thought
law was a safe profession.
And Schumann did come away
with one unique distinction.
He lived in Heidelberg as
a law student for a year, but
failed to attend a single class.
He just played around with music.
So music was indeed his true calling.
And off he went to Leipzig, Germany.
And he went there to study piano with
the eminent piano teacher Frederique Vica
who just happened to have
a beautiful daughter named Clara
who just happened to be
a child protege as a pianist.
Clara, by the age of eleven,
had already performed in public in Paris.
Robert well he was a nobody.
Young Clara she was
an international sensation.
You may know the story
despite the strenuous and
legal objects that father
Frederick put in their way.
Robert and Clara were married.
In 1840, he was 30, she was about 20.
Soon Clara bore Robert eight children.
Here they are,
all gathered together in a Google Doodle.
But look, look at the toll that it took,
Clara now 15 years later.
Here they are side by side.
1838 and 1853.
As to Robert here he is at comparable
ages to the earlier slides with Clara.
As you may know he suffered
from bipolar disorder and
gradually disintegrated mentally.
The climax of which was, pursued by
what he thought were demonic voices,
he jumped into the Rhine River
near Dusseldorf.
Well, he was pulled to
safety by fishermen but
he spent the next three years in a mental
institution at his own volition,
where he died in 1856 at the age of 46.
Perhaps as a result of his
sometimes unstable mind,
Robert was something of a streak composer.
Maybe it's all too easy to say that well,
when he was in his manic phase,
he would only write one kind of music.
Only write keyboard music, or only write
chamber music, or only write songs.
But it does seem that way.
It does appear at least that almost all
of the songs cluster around 1838-1840.
And we'll investigate
one in just a minute.
During this period the 1820s and 1830s,
composers would sometimes take
a group of poems on a single topic and
set them all together as a unified group.
We call this a song cycle.
A song cycle is similar in concept in,
in pop music to a concept album,
say by the Beatles as with
the Sgt Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band.
Concept album.
A group of songs that tell a story or
tie together in some way or another.
One such song cycle is entitled
Frau in Lieben und -Leben,
A Woman's Love and Life.
Here the poet, Adelbert von Chamisso,
depicts the emotions of a young
woman as she falls in love.
Becomes engaged and is married.
Our composer has taken eight poems and
set them as a group.
Perhaps cuz the text here mirror events
in the true life romance of Robert and
Clara Schumann.
The cycle dates from 1840 and
the two were finally married in 1840.
Both Robert and Clara Schumann
wrote things other than liegers.
She wrote chamber music and songs.
He wrote chamber music,
symphonies and even operas.
So Clara too was a composer,
at least before she met Robert.
But marriage seems to have
brought her career as a composer.
To an end.
Here's what Clara wrote in
her diary at that time.
Quote, I once believed that I
possessed creative talent, but
I have given up this idea.
A woman must not dare to compose.
There has never been a woman able to
do so, should I expect to be that one?
End quote.
Was Clara selling herself short here?
Did she not have the capacity
to compose as well as Robert,
to compose as well as her
best male contemporaries?
Was it the lack of opportunity and
encouragement and
ultimately eight children
that held her back?
Well you be the judge.
Let's go do something of a back-to-back
comparison of a song by Clara and
one by Robert.
But for this to be a real test you
shouldn't know who composed which.
So I've chosen two songs, each set
to a lyric poem and each about love.
Again, I'm not gonna
tell you who wrote which.
Is the composer Robert,
or is the composer Clara?
You identify the composer.
And can you,
in fact identify a female composer?
Does music have a female or
feminine quality to it?
Might it be less good, or
might it be more good in quality?
Okay, let's look at our text again.
Anyway, we're gonna concentrate here on
song number four of this cycle Du Ring
an meinem Finger, Oh,
You Ring on My Finger.
The woman has just been married and she
stares down rapturously at her new ring.
As you can see,
there are five strophes to this lead, and
we would expect the composer to set it
in strophic form, changing the text.
But continually repeating the music for
each new strophe.
But as you can see,
our mystery composer here doesn't do that.
He or she repeats the music in a way that
creates another well known musical form,
and that is,
just looking at the letters there,
that is, well, A B A C A,
Rondo form of course.
Rondo form, with a piano coda.
And that's a bit of a surprise.
That's a bit of a surprise.
And what do you think of this text?
Let's focus now on our text and
in red you see strophe four
clearly it was written in
the days before sexual equality.
Quote, I will serve him,
I will live for him,
I will belong to him entirely, and so on.
Wow, I'd never get away
with that in my house.
And notice that this strophe four in red
really is the musical
high point of the song.
So let me play a little
bit at the keyboard here.
Play a little bit of the A material.
And then the B and so on.
Here's the A section.
[MUSIC]
Okay here comes b.
And then eventually go back to a.
[MUSIC]
And that brings us to
the contrasting c section,
the most dramatic in terms of range,
has the highest range, the loudest volume.
It's the most dissonant,
this is the climax of the song.
[MUSIC]
And coming off of the climax,
with the retard.
And then back to [INAUDIBLE].
And so on.
So again the climax
there is the c section,
where listeners learn that
this singer is just absolutely
thrilled to be delighted by
her subservient position.
So that's a bit of
the background in this art song.
Let's hear song a, from beginning to end.
And for this and our second mystery piece,
we're going to move from a concert hall
and we'll have better acoustics and
we'll meet our guest.
So here we are, in Yale's Sudner Hall,
little bit better acoustics than
what we usually have in the studio,
and we have a guest with us today,
it is our own Sylvia Leath.
So Sylvia, tell us please,
where do you come from?
>> I'm from Bethesda, Maryland.
>> Bethesda, Maryland, and
obviously, you're a singer, so
when did you first start
taking singing lessons?
>> I started taking lessons probably
when I was in middle school,
I did a lot of musical theater, and
then when I was in high school I started
studying with a teacher who
taught classical technique.
And I started doing classical
repertoire and that was when I was 14.
Most teachers won't take on
students who are younger than 16,
15, 14, because before that the body and
the voice is not really mature
enough to work with, I guess.
And I think 14 is supposed to be
considered a little bit young for
starting, a lot of my friends at Yale who
do opera started when they were 16 or 17.
>> Uh-huh, really?
That's very interesting.
So singers really don't start
studying classical music
seriously until really their
advanced teenage years.
And it probably, as Sylvia was saying, has
to do with the length of the vocal cord
and the development of the vocal cord and
that sort of thing.
So here you are now at Yale University and
what year are you?
>> I'm junior.
>> You're a junior.
Your third year here.
And what's your major?
>> I'm a German major.
>> German major.
Well that's good for us because we've
obviously got some German lieder to deal
with today, and you'll be able to execute
that diction just perfectly, I'm sure.
>> I hope so.
>> So we're going to start now,
I think we're going to go ahead and
visit our friends Robert and
Clara Schumann, and
we're going to have first song a,
and then song b.
[MUSIC]
Now song b, with lyrics by
Friedrich Ruckert in four strophes.
As you can see here I've
heightened the word nichts 0.
In the first three strophes of this poem,
the lady tells us what she
doesn't want to be loved for.
Oh don't love me for my beauty, and
no don't love me for my youth, and
no don't love me for my money.
And finally in the fourth stanza,
don't love me for any of these, but
yes just love me for love,
just for love alone.
So nicht and ja are the keywords here.
And each time they appear, they do so
in the context of a shocking
minor chord insertion.
I'll play it at the piano.
[MUSIC]
So again.
So listeners will wanna be
on the look out for that.
Also notice in the song that although
it's strophic, the music for
each strophic is slightly modified.
And so we have here what's called
obviously modified strophic form.
So I think we can see on the screen here,
by the s's I mean strophe one and
strophe two, slightly modified strophe
three, slightly modified and so on,
there are four strophes.
And a piano coda at the end,
and how does this operate?
Well you can see by the musical
examples there Let's go on to
the last four measures of each and
I'll play them here.
It's really a question of changing
the rhythm towards the end and
changing the course of
the melody towards the end.
I think you'll be able
to hear the difference.
Here's the last four
measures of the top example
[MUSIC]
And then, the last four
measures of the bottom example.
[MUSIC]
Slightly different, slight variation
there, modified the musical line.
And two other points here.
Notice by this slide that the
accompaniment here is rather complicated,
rather dense by the standards of the lied.
It's good counterpoint,
remember both Robert and
Clara Schumann had spent a great
deal of time in the city of Leipzig.
She grew up there and
the two were married there.
And what composer spent the bulk
of his career in Leipzig?
Well yes, J S Bach.
So indeed, the music and the spirit
of Bach with its counterpoint and
chromaticism in the inner lines hovers
over the music of the Schumann.
Here's the Bach-like chromaticism.
[MUSIC]
You can see that on the screen with
the rising blue lines, now once again.
[MUSIC]
And then down a little bit lower.
And then finally this idea of consonance
to dissonance that occurs in the coda.
We have music moving from a dissonance to
a consonance all by chromatic half-steps.
The bass holds the note down here, [SOUND]
and the upper parts which are here.
[MUSIC]
Slide in this fashion.
Dissonance to consonant here.
An intensity and
then ultimately a very pleasing ending.
All right, that's a bit of song b.
Let's go back now and hear our guest,
Sylvia Leith,
as she performs for us, song b.
[MUSIC]
>> [FOREIGN]
[FOREIGN]
[MUSIC]
>> So which song was by Robert Schumann
and which was by Clara Schumann?
Could you tell the difference?
Was one better than the other?
Was there a feminine touch
in the music in any way?
Aside from that,
which did you like better and why?
Well, there are two quizzes here
at the end of this segment.
One asking you to tell us which composer
wrote which song and
which song you preferred.
And the other quiz asks you to review
in effect the following important
ten terms from this session.
And to tell us where we
are in this session,
let me play this, a final cadence.
[MUSIC]