[MUSIC]
How do we communicate one
human being to another?
Sometimes we do it through spoken words.
Sometimes through signs or symbols,
algebraic letters and numbers,
for example.
Or sometimes just through
gestures without words,
as is true of the communication or
messages sent to us by a mime.
Here we see the famous Marcel Marceau,
silently communicating two
very different emotions.
Sometimes gestures are accompanied
by music and dance, as we see here.
Gestures and dance are at the heart of
a communicative art we call ballet.
The ballerina acts out the meaning
of the ballet through gestures and
dance, the meaning of the story.
Animals in the animal kingdom,
dolphins, whales, birds and
others well, they communicate by sounds.
Sounds that sometimes seem very similar
to what we humans call music, but
humans usually communicate
through spoken language
as I'm communicating with you now.
And here is how it works.
Over time, a group of people,
let's say all the people living on
the island of Japan or in France,
they will agree upon the meaning of
a set of phonemes, a set of sounds.
And they place these phonemes in an order,
in a sequence that forms a sentence,
a unit of sense that makes sense to
those who understand this language.
These organized phonemes
communicate meaning and
feelings, anxiety, fear,
joy, sadness, whatever.
The sounds of classical music,
well they also communicate, of course.
They too communicate anxiety,
fear, joy, sadness.
And when these sounds, the meaning of
which we've all come to agree upon
commonly are strung together,
this music too communicates to us.
When meaning filled sounds
come in a purposeful order,
such music can narrate a story,
tell a tale.
A story about an event in the life
of a hero, or of a people, or
maybe of a sequence of events,
human or, as experienced in nature.
When such a story is told exclusively
through instrumental music,
what we've created is
called program music.
Now, the art song or Lied that we
just studied in an earlier session,
well, that's not program music
because there are lyrics there.
There's a text that tell us a story.
Ballet is not program music
because the acting and
the pantomiming of the dancers suggest
the meaning of the story as well.
So program music is purely
instrumental music, thus,
a definition of program music.
Program music is instrumental music,
usually written for
a symphony orchestra,
that seeks to re-create in sound
the events portrayed in some extra-musical
source, a story, a legend a play,
a novel or even an historical
event such as a military battle.
Well how about some examples Greg?
Okay, likely you've heard for
example of Tchaikovsky's 1812 Overture
in which Tchaikovsky tries to
recreate events in music of
the Battle of Borodino between Napoleon's
troops and the Russians in 1812 or
the story of Romeo and Juliet as retold
through music, again, by Tchaikovsky.
Or Mendelssohn's overture
to Shakespeare's play,
A Midsummer Night's Dream in which
the composer attempts to capture,
in sound,
the events that unfold in that play.
The 19th century was a high
watermark of program music, and
many composers used it as
a better form of communication,
a way to communicate better with
the listener, music as narrative.
As composer Franz Liszt
said about program music,
and let me grab my note card here.
This is what he said,
Program music protects the listener from
a wrong interpretation of the music and
directs his attention to the poetic
idea of the whole end quote.
But not every composer was taken
with the notion of program music.
Johannes Brahms wrote no program music.
He didn't want his music to tell a story.
Maybe he thought program
music was too simple,
or naive, or too restrictive of
the imagination of the listener.
Brahms wanted only to communicate
feelings and sensations.
This sort of music,
as opposed to program music,
came to be called Absolute music,
Pure music, if you will.
You can see here a definition of it.
But let's stick with program music and
find out how it came to be and
how it works.