[MUSIC]
Let me play something for
you and see what you think.
Let me create a short story and
put a little bit of music to it.
So let's say one day, there was a boy.
Skipping through a forest,
bright sunny summer day.
[MUSIC]
Then, cloud came over and
wind came up, starting to rain.
[MUSIC]
A burst of lightning and thunder.
And there, in the dark rainy forest.
[MUSIC]
A bear appears.
A bear started to chase the boy.
[MUSIC]
And caught him and killed him.
Always friends, they came together and
carried his body to a chapel.
When they were in the chapel,
all of the friends
[MUSIC]
We gotta sing a hymn to the boy.
While they're in the chapel,
the sun came out.
[MUSIC]
And the spirit of the boy descended and
then rose to the sky.
Silly, I know, but
that's the essence of program music.
Over time,
composers developed sonic signifiers.
Triple it, major key for happy, maybe some
crashing chords and dissonant chords for
disruption, rising chromaticism,
minor, that sort of thing.
Steady minor tempo for a funeral march.
These signifiers we have come to
understand as conveying meaning in music.
Done tastefully, stringing these together,
we can make a story.
If you do it tastefully, as I suggest,
well then it can be effective.
Done to excess, I suppose it can
degenerate into cartoon music or
video music.
Utilitarian music rather than
the supposed high art music.
When did we get this language of music?
When did we all start to speak or
least understand this language of music?
Well, it goes back to the renaissance and
the madrigal.
Remember how the composers of
the madrigal focused on particular
words of the text and
tried to create in music?
Onomatopoeic sounds that would match it.
A sound that would sound out the meaning
of the word, words like buzz or smooth.
In the 17th century, the baroque era, this
language of music became so well known.
That the text could be stripped away and
the listener would still understand the
meaning of the various musical gestures.
Now the go-to piece here, of course,
is Vivaldi's The Seasons and
the Spring Concerto.
Let's review this piece and
do so in the form of a quiz.
You'll remember Vivaldi created
a series of events in nature and
placed them in a particular order to
tell a simple story about a spring day.
So, I've extracted the important
musical signifiers and scrambled them.
Let me play them for you,
and you unscramble them.
You place the musical excerpts
in the correct order.
But how do we know what
the correct order is?
Because that's the order In
which Vivaldi presented them.
Okay, so you can see here on the screen,
we have four event.
A storm, a river, a clearing, and
that clearing of the atmosphere could
come before or after a storm, and birds.
So I'm just gonna start
up at the top here, and
I'm going to play the first audio clip,
and we will see what you think.
[MUSIC]
Okay, what's the next event?
You identify the next event.
[MUSIC]
Okay.
Next event or entity or
item moving down to this one.
[MUSIC]
And now the last one.
Well, how did you do?
Did you get them all right?
Did you get them in the right order?
Well to find out,
we'll have to take the next recap quiz.