[MUSIC]
Now we come to the iconic
piece of program music,
something of a thunderbolt of program
music, Berlioz's Symphonie fantastique.
Before we look at this work by Berlioz,
let's discuss the various types, or
genres, of program music that we
might experience in a concert hall.
We've listed them here on a slide.
As you can see, we have a tone poem,
sometimes called symphonic poem,
a one movement piece for orchestra.
Actually, we've already experienced
this beginning of our course,
Richard Strauss' Also sprach Zarathustra.
We could mention Romeo and
Juliet by Tchaikovsky,
Night on Bald Mountain by Mussorgsky.
Then there is the genre
of the program symphony,
a multi-movement composition for
orchestra.
Symphonie fantastique, Berlioz, the Faust
Symphony of Liszt, Sheherazade even,
perhaps, of Rimsky-Korsakov.
They would be all examples
of the program symphony.
And finally the dramatic overture that
could open an opera, or open a play,
or even open a festival.
They are, again,
as with the tone poem, one movement.
The William Tell overture, for example,
opens the opera of that name by Rossini.
The 1812 Overture of Tchaikovsky
commemorated the opening
of a convocation in honor of that
event in Russia in the 1860s.
And finally, of course, Midsummer Night's
Dream, well, that's an overture by
Mendelssohn that opened a Shakespearean
play of that same name.
Well, let's start with what's arguably
the strangest and most bizarre example of
program music, again,
Hector Berlioz's Symphonie Fantastique.
Obviously, it's an example
of a program symphony.
Let's start with an excerpt
from this symphony.
As you listen, think about what you feel.
What Berlioz is trying to
depict here is a scene,
a scene that is part of
the program of this symphony.
What is he trying to communicate here?
Where are we?
[MUSIC]
Okay, well let's, let's fade
that out here just for a moment.
And let me give you a hint.
Where does Berlioz take us musically?
To the scene on the left, or
to the scene on the right?
You choose.
[MUSIC]
So here we have two paintings
from the same period,
one by Constable, the other by Goya.
Which sort of atmosphere was Berlioz
trying to conjure up through music,
left or right?
[MUSIC]
Well, the atmosphere on the right.
The music that you just heard is
his vision of a descent into hell.
And I think you'd agree that we heard
descending music with strange sounds,
the cacophony of hell.
But before we proceed,
a quick word about Hector Berlioz.
Berlioz was born in
the south of France and
was trained in classical literature and
basic science, but not in music.
Of all the great composers, he was
the only one who could not play the piano.
He could only strum out
a few chords on the guitar.
His father, well, he was a village doctor.
He sent the young Berlioz up to Paris
to the prestigious Ecole de medecine,
Medical School on the Left Bank.
And it's still here today,
near the Sorbonne.
And here's how it looked
in the 19th century.
But Berlioz was no fan of the horrific
dissections that he had to witness as
a medical school student.
And even in his memoirs, he talks about
jumping out a window during one of them.
So after a year, he dropped out of
med school to give himself over to
the study of music at the Conservatory and
the Opera House, both across the river
there, on the Right Bank of Paris.
Here's a view of a concert in
progress at the Conservatory.
Although always the rebel and contrarian,
Berlioz did manage to win a Prix de Rome,
a composition prize.
But he really preferred Paris to Rome,
mostly for the music and the theater.
Indeed, in the second and
third decades of the 19th century,
Shakespeare was taking
the stage of Europe by storm.
And in 1827, a group of Shakespearean
actors came to Paris to play both
Hamlet and Romeo and Juliet.
Berlioz went, and he was smitten.
Here's where he went,
to the Theater Odeon.
That's the outside of it as it
existed in the 19th century.
Now let's go inside, as it looks today.
I can personally attest, there's
very little leg room in those seats.
Anyway, Berli goes, Berlioz goes into
this theater, sees the Shakespeare and
falls in love with Shakespeare and
with the leading lady, who was playing
Ophelia to Hamlet, and Juliet to Romeo,
the young Irish actress Harriet Smithson.
Here she is in a portrait of that time.
Berlioz, well, he tried to meet Harriet.
He went to her dressing room.
He followed after her.
In modern parlance, he stalked her,
almost like a crazed fan would
stalk a Hollywood starlet today.
And Harriet, well, she was a star, but
she was terrified and rejected Berlioz.
Rejected, Berlioz began to contemplate and
execute an artistic response,
a multi-movement symphony that told
the tale of an imaginary, dreamlike,
ill-fated love in which the stalker
ends up killing the young woman.
If nothing else,
you can see that Berlioz is building here,
at first,
on the true story of his love for
Harriet, and then his imagination
takes over, a vivid ima,
imagination that leads to a fantastic or,
in this case, fantastical story.
So fantastic, or fantastique,
here, doesn't mean so
much that it's great, though it is great.
It's fantastic in that sense.
But it's also a fantasy.
Well, how did it play out,
this story in a symphony?
Well, eventually,
Berlioz's fantastic symphony was
premiered at the Paris Conservatory.
And Harriet Smithson, who up to that time
had no idea that she was the center of
the symphony,
with Harriet Smithson in attendance and
listening, eventually during the
performance, the premiere, she caught on.
As to the symphony itself, well,
it's constructed not in four, but
in five movements,
like a five-act play of Shakespeare.
Like his Hamlet or his Romeo and Juliet.
And here's something else that's new.
Berlioz wrote out this program and
had it printed and
handed to everyone in the audience at the
first performance of the finished work,
the first example in the history
of music of concert program notes.
Program music, program notes.
Let's start with the first movement, and
remember, these are Berlioz's words,
not mine.
A young musician sees for the first time
a woman who embodies all the charms of the
ideal being he has imagined in his dreams.
The subject of the first movement
is the passage from this state of
melancholy reverie to that
of delirious passion.
What was Berlioz's vision of the beloved?
Well, here is the musical incarnation
of her, Harriet Smithson.
She becomes an obsession,
a musical obsession or fixation.
An Idee fixe.
So let me try to play this for you.
I may need my glasses to see it,
maybe not, we'll see.
Play the Idee fixe for
you here at the keyboard.
[MUSIC]
Now rising sequences,
maybe a little bit faster.
[MUSIC]
Now up to the top,
he begins to come off it.
[MUSIC]
A typical romantic theme.
It's long, it's not balanced,
no two plus two phrases here,
as you can see by all of
the ties up there in the melody.
It's rhythmically amorphous,
and it's pushed upward.
It's climax-oriented,
pushed on passionately by the ever-rising
melodic sequence, as you heard.
Okay, now a bit of the second movement.
Let's see where Berlioz has taken
us next in his imagination.
We'll hear the same melody, but
now it's altered to fit
the next scene of the story.
But where are we?
Again, where does Berlioz
take us in this scene?
[MUSIC]
Yes, we're at a dance.
Our hero is now at a party, and
he sees the beloved across the room.
Our beloved, the Idee fixe,
is transformed, of course.
The melody is now changed into a more
symmetrical waltz in a clear triple meter.
Now let's take a look
at the third movement.
Now we're in the country.
The artist, our musician, hears in
the distance two shepherds piping.
He hopes that soon he
will no longer be alone.
So the way Berlioz has set
this up is as follows.
Onstage he has an English horn,
that's presumably Berlioz himself.
Offstage there is an oboe.
And they engage in a dialogue.
She loves me.
She loves me not.
Eventually, the oboe ceases to respond,
ceases to answer.
This leaves the musician alone and
despondent, with dire
consequences to come.