[MUSIC]
As you can see by Berlioz's
description of movement four,
things now take a turn
toward the dark side.
Berlioz imagines the story thusly.
Quote, having realized that
his love goes unrecognized,
the artist poisons himself with opium.
The dose of the narcotic,
too weak to kill him, plunges him into
a sleep with the most horrible visions.
He dreams that he has killed his beloved,
is condemned to death,
led to the scaffold, and
now witnesses his own execution.
So this is s march,
a march to the scaffold for a beheading.
As a boy growing up during
the period of the Napoleonic wars,
Berlioz heard many military bands and
military instruments.
In addition to bringing the harp and
the English horn, a low oboe,
into the orchestra, Bers,
Berlioz also incorporated the coronet,
a short mellow trumpet, and
an ophicleide, an early form of the tuba.
Of these, the ophicleide,
the tuba was the most important,
because it opened the door to more low
brasses within the orchestra which Berlioz
uses in this march to the scaffold.
As we listen here focus
on the low brass sound.
[MUSIC]
There it is again.
Well the march of the condemned prisoner,
our musician, reaches the scaffold with
growing excitement on the part
of the gathering crowd.
Remember, beheadings in this period
during the French revolution and
there after,
beheadings was a spectator sport.
So the musician arrives,
his head is set on the guillotine, and
then one last thought of his beloved.
We know that because we hear the,
the sound quietly in the clarinet.
Then the guillotine falls.
Kaboom.
Off comes the head and the crowd cheers
as signaled by triumphant brass chords.
[MUSIC]
There's a gathering crowd.
Rushing to the scaffold.
[MUSIC]
And the crowd cheers.
Well let's hear this again.
This is program music at its best or
most extreme.
First a reminiscence of the beloved,
again, in the clarinet.
Then the fall,
sharp fall of the guillotine, and if you
listen very carefully, you'll hear that
Berlioz even depicts the fall of the head
into the basket, thump, thump, thump,
thump, at the distance of an octave.
A first, and last,
in the history of music.
[MUSIC]
The reminiscence of the beloved.
Guillotine.
Thump, thump.
End of our musician, end of
movement.