[MUSIC]
With our protagonist musician now dead,
we would assume that that
would be the end of the story.
But not so.
He and we now descend into hell
as our fantastic dream continues.
What does a descent into Hell sound like?
Well we've already heard this music at the
beginning of our session on program music
and our twisting image of Francesca Goya.
Let's continue down and
we'll see who we meet along the way.
Well lo and behold there she is,
our beloved, and now look at her.
She's been turned into an old hag,
a crone.
A grotesque version of former loveliness.
How do we know that this is our beloved?
Because Berlioz's program
is very explicit,
very descriptive here in this fifth and
final movement.
Here's the program.
He sees himself at the witches'
sabbath surrounded by
a troop of frightful monsters of
all sorts gathered for his funeral.
The beloved melody returns but
it has lost its noble,
modest character and is now only base,
trivial and grotesque.
[MUSIC]
Down further we go in our descent
until we reach the bottom of Hell.
And we'll know we've arrived at
the bottom when Berlioz sounds his new
low brass instrument, the ophicleide or
tuba, on a long held pitch.
A stable pitch, which tells us that at
this point, we've reached rock bottom.
[MUSIC]
There's the note, the bottom.
And then suddenly.
[SOUND] The strangest sound.
[MUSIC]
Well, church bells give an odd
religious tone to the proceedings.
And the sacrilege continues in
the music when the low brasses,
led by the new tubas, play in
unison the melody of the Dies irae.
The signature chant of the Roman Requiem
mass, the burial mass,
again of the Roman Catholic church.
A melody that belonged to the church for
at least 700 years by this time.
And notice that at the repeat
of the opening phrase,
the rhythmic durations
are shortened by half.
The rhythmic durations are shortened by
half which is called rhythmic diminution.
[MUSIC]
Diminution.
Yeah, now the weirdness continues.
Here, Berlioz shares with
us his vision of a black or
blasphemous mass, a parody of
the traditional Christian mass.
Your babies serve as communion
wafers in this hellish scene.
And Berlioz has his witches
join a bizarre dance that
unfolds in the form of all things,
a fugue.
Having parodied the Roman Catholic
church with an old chant,
why not parody the Paris Conservatory,
the home of the old academic fugue?
Now a fugue that unfolds in the middle of
another composition is called a fugato,
fugato, a short fugue.
Let's listen as this fugato
unfolds in the middle of Hell.
And I'll indicate the entries of
the subjects as marked here with an S.
[MUSIC]
And pretty soon our fugato fades out.
But Berlioz wasn't finished with
learned counterpoint here in Hell.
What would it sound like if
Berlioz had combined his fugue
subject with the Dies irae in
a moment of double counterpoint?
[MUSIC]
Fugue subject up above,
Dies irae underneath.
[MUSIC]
Okay, double counterpoint.
Now it's time for
our protagonist musician to burn in Hell.
For this,
Berlioz would need another musical first.
What musical sound, what sound, could
produce something akin to burning wood?
How can we have a musical
gesture like that?
Well, maybe the wood of the back
of the violin bow would suffice.
So for this special effect,
Berlioz requires the player to flip
the bow over and play as you see here.
Not with the usual horsehairs,
but with the wood on the back,
scraping it on the strings.
The direction in the score says col legno,
col legno, with the wood.
So let's listen to the end of Symphonie
fantastique as it races towards
an exciting conclusion beginning
with col legno technique and
I'll point out the secants of
musical events as we proceed.
[MUSIC]
Well that was quite a story,
quite a program, but
how does the story really end?
Well, it turns out that
Berlioz did meet Harriett.
And that the two did marry and
then they were miserable ever after.
Sometimes life just doesn't imitate art.
Hector complained of Harriet's
increasing weight, and
Harriet complained of Hector's
increasingly frequent infidelities.
She died in 1853, and was buried, and
then reburied, or re-interred, elsewhere.
He died in 1869, and
was buried in a small cemetery.
To the north of the river
there in Montmartre in Paris.
Then, for the 100th anniversary of his
death, poor Harriet was moved yet again.
This time up to that cemetery, in the same
cemetery in Monmartre next to Hector.
And there the two lie side by side today,
probably still squabbling.
[LAUGH] As they say, it's quite a story.