[MUSIC]
Well, there's much more we
could do with program music.
I'd love to introduce you to the music
of Tchaikovsky's dramatic overture,
Romeo and Juliet.
See how that sounds,
just a clip from that.
[MUSIC]
And, perhaps also,
music from Tchaikovsky's, 1812 Overture.
Just a sampler of that.
[MUSIC]
Or music from Mussorgsky's,
Pictures at an Exhibition, or
Rimsky-Korsakov Scheherazade,
and so many others.
But I can't because these are long pieces,
and they take a long time to play out and
a long time to discuss.
And we're out of time.
So let's end with one last
interactive engagement to see if
you speak fluent program music.
What I mean by that, of course,
is to see if you can engage
in a musical conversation from
the listener's point of view.
Can you recognize what's being said?
Can you recognize what
the composer wants to say to you,
wants to communicate to you?
Let's see.
All right, so here's our quiz.
We have six events or
scenes, if you will, and
six audio clips down below, audio clips
by Beethoven, audio clip B by Grieg,
C Suppe, D Beethoven,
E Brahms, and F Wagner.
And up above,
we have six scenes or events.
As you can see here, we have a storm
scene, a funeral march, a calvary, or
horse march, at a fast tempo,
a Sunrise in the midst of nature, Spacious
alpine meadow and mountains, and finally,
Triumphant pilgrims marching along a road.
So, let's begin.
I'm gonna play audio clip A, and
you match it with the scene.
[MUSIC]
All right, that's enough of that.
Let's go onto audio clip B.
[MUSIC]
That's probably enough of that.
Now audio clip C, by Suppe.
[MUSIC]
Enough, that's probably enough of that.
Let's hear some more Beethoven.
[MUSIC]
All right, we'll stop it there.
Next is music by Brahms.
[MUSIC]
Okay, and then finally, music by Wagner.
All right.
Well, how'd you do?
Here are the answers.
Storm scene, well,
that was music of Beethoven.
Funeral march, well, more Beethoven.
Calvary march, music by Suppe.
Sunrise, music by Grieg.
Alpine mountains, music by Brahms,
featuring the French horn.
And the Triumphant pilgrims march,
featuring the trombones
there with Richard Wagner.
If you did get them correct,
congratulations.
You obviously understand program music.
You got the message.
You got the composer's message.