[MUSIC]
Western musical culture,
is the only musical culture that
has keyed fix pitched instruments.
Let me say that again,
keyed fix pitch instruments.
What's a fixed pitch instrument?
Well, it's one that doesn't allow for
a change of pitch, doesn't allow for
a tuning, during a performance.
So, here's an opening quiz.
In the list that you
see which of the three
instruments are fixed pitch instruments?
You don't have to adjust them,
while you're playing a concert.
Good.
Harp, Organ, and Piano.
With the oboe, you can blow harder or
less hard and the pitch will rise or
fall, same thing with the trumpet or
the trombone.
With both string instruments,
you can slightly extend or
shorten the length of string and
the sound, will get lower or higher.
The voice does the same thing,
with the vocal chords, lengthening or
shortening them.
The harp, of course,
doesn't use keys, so the organ and
piano are really the only fixed
pitch instruments with keyboards.
Now, other cultures have
fixed pitch instruments.
The Chinese, for example, have the Pipa
and the Indonesians, well, they
have the Indonesian Gamelan, but neither
if these, obviously, has a keyboard.
Only, Western music has
keyboard instruments.
And, Western music, has relied heavily
on keyboard instruments, indeed for
more than a thousand years.
First with the organ, and later with
the harpsichord and then with the piano.
The result of this heavy reliance
on fixed pitch keyboard instruments
to accompany voices and
other instruments, was that fixed pitch,
very precise pitch, came to be
privileged in Western musical culture.
Western music doesn't slide.
Between pitches but
goes immediately and directly bum, bum.
From one exact pitch, to the next.
And these pitches, have been set
out on a grid at fixed spots.
Western music, with its grid is more
precise in terms of melody and harmony,
but lets much less nuance
than non-western music.
Again, in Western music we have bars for
rhythm and a grid for pitch.
If nothing else, Western music is
comparatively rigid and fixed.
As we saw in our earlier session
in medieval and renaissance music.
The organ has been around in the West,
with keys, for more than a thousand years
and, the harpsichord for more than 600,
and the piano, for more than 300.
Let's take a minute to review,
how the harpsichord and piano make sound.
You can see that, this harpsichord, from
around 1600, has only three and a half
octaves to it, it's very small, very small
keyboard, very few keys, very few pitches.
Now here's a, layer,
somewhat bigger harpsichord,
that allows us to see where the jacks
are located at the blue arrow.
Now remember,
that the harpsichord had a jack mechanism
in which small bits of plastic, well,
of course, back in the day those small
bits of plastic were bits of crow quill.
Small, hard bits that could be pushed up,
by a key and
strike a string and then slide back down.
You'll see, where the plectrum,
or the striker of the string,
is located within the jack,
as we watch a quick video.
[MUSIC]
Pretty nifty,
[LAUGH] virtuoso performance, but
the harpsichord did have limitations.
Well, what, what were they?
Think about it, for a moment.
What couldn't the harpsichord do?
Well, here are some of the disadvantages.
It had only one dynamic range at a time.
And it couldn't shape a phrase.
That's particularly important,
couldn't shape a phrase.
It couldn't play, loud or
soft one note to the next.
And it couldn't play loud enough
to compete with an orchestra,
at least with the late classical and
early romantic orchestra,
because it didn't have the volume.
So to solve this problem of limited
volume an Italian inventor in
Florence created a new kind of
instrument called the pianoforte,
the soft loud, because it could play
both soft and loud, and instantly.
Here the strings were not plucked,
but struck by hammers from below.
And they could fall back or
escape back down after being struck.
Without this escapement mechanism,
the hammer would still be
controlled by the key.
You push the key down and as long as you
were pressing the key the hammer would
stay stuck up against the string and
mute the sound of the string.
So that was no good.
The complicated escapement
mechanism that you see
here allowed the string to sound and
a hammer to fall back, so
that it was immediately ready to strike
again when the key was pressed down again.
Of course, this instrument came
to be called just the piano.
And here's how the inside
of it looks today.
But let's go back to
Mozart's piano of the 1780s.
And as you can see it too is short.
It has only, you know, 5 octaves.
And as mentioned before, it's light.
It weighs only exactly 187 pounds,
because it lacked,
among other things, a metal frame.
The strings are thin, so
they tend to break rather easily.
Now, here you see, Joseph Haydn,
seated at a keyboard and composing.
Haydn's favorite piano,
is made by Johann Kurnica in Vienna.
Kurnica's store,
was in the center of Vienna.
You can see it here at the red arrow.
Just down the street from where Mozart
premiered many of his piano concertos.
You can see that at the blue arrow.
So Mozart, Heiden, and
Beethoven, would have all played
the kind of piano you see here.
Notice that on these late 18th Century
pianos, that there were no pedals.
Now, today, pedals are used to raise or
lower the felt dampers.
Raising the dampers, of course,
allows the sound to continue to sound.
Lowering the dampers,
extinguishes the sound.
On these late 18th century pianos,
a knee lever mechanism does the job.
And you can see it here,
at the blue arrow.
Eventually, in the 19th century as we'll
see, pedals were put on or near the floor.
All right, that's our quick review
of the piano up to early Beethoven.
Beethoven arrived in Vienna in 1792, and
the piano that you see here
was made in Vienna in 1795.
So let's see,
this very piano in the extraordinary
Yale Collection of Musical Instruments and
let's meet our guest.
The distinguished pianist, Robert Blocker.