[MUSIC]
So let me say a word about Robert Blocker,
if I may.
Robert Blocker is
a distinguished music educator.
More than any Dean of the School of
Music that I have experienced in
my long time here at Yale, he has been,
by far and away, the most distinguished
in the sense of artistic accomplishment,
and particularly financial accomplishment.
It is now possible,
owing in large measure to his good labors,
that any student admitted to
the Yale School of Music can come here and
get a free education in music.
Great for Yale, great for
young people, great for music.
But really impresses me about
Robert Block is the following.
In addition to being a distinguished music
educator he also a world renown concert
pianist, and that's really difficult
to do, to have two careers like this.
So I'd like to ask Robert, and
I don't know the answer to this, Robert
what time did you get up this morning?
>> [LAUGH] Very early, but
I normally get up very early.
Well, I know that from the time
I got emails from you.
I get them at, say, 5:10 in the morning.
>> That's about right.
>> He is already up and rolling, and
Robert how are you feeling today,
you feeling tired?
Have you been anywhere interest of late?
>> Well, as you know I'm just
getting back from China.
So, well, I'm acclimating rather well.
>> You were performing in China.
>> I was.
>> Where in China?
>> I was in Shenzhen.
>> I think what we'd like to do now is see
if Robert would like to comment on
the difficulty of playing this.
It might sound easy, oh gee, just go
play a Mozart on this little piano.
How hard can that be?
Oddly, this morning this may be
Robert's most difficult challenge.
So we're starting off
with a tough one here.
And what do you feel when
you go to this piano?
>> It is the most difficult transition for
me.
And I think this piano and
the others that we'll talk about in here,
hold special gifts for
us, gifts of knowledge and
wisdom about the music itself.
About the times that
the music was composed.
And certainly about how
we think about sound,
in terms of the historical nature
of the piece we are playing, and
I'm thinking particularly
now of Beethoven.
>> Hm.
>> Because normally when we attend or
listen to a Beethoven concerto we're in a
large hall with a concert grand Steinway,
a big piano,
an orchestra of 40 to 60 people.
And to think that this
was the instrument for
these concerti at that time is
a remarkable kind of beginning point.
And then the evolution.
So these pianos are instructive for us.
They hold special gifts.
It's remarkable, for me at least,
when I sit down and touch the keys.
And I just stop for a moment and
think, who has heard music
come from this instrument?
Where did this instrument reside?
What kind of life has it had?
And each instrument really
takes on its own life.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And
I think that's a kind of remarkable,
emotional piece to put
with the music itself.
But maybe we should hear a few notes.
And I wanted to mention also
about the pedaling on this piano.
>> Yes.
>> The pedals are our levers
underneath the keyboard, and
that's one of the biggest adjustments.
And, depending on the physical
frame of the pianist,
that can cause different
kinds of problems.
I mean, I found myself yesterday lifting
the piano a little bit off the floor.
And the other thing that
the piano does is it allows for
a lot of sensitivity and finger weight.
So those are transitional
issues that any pianist has.
I think it is precisely why
in recent years so many
artists really devote themselves to the
playing of these historical instruments.
So this is my disclaimer,
I am not one of these
historical artists who would have
far more familiarity with it.
On the other hand though,
I think that for the modern pianist
not to have this instructive wisdom
when it's right here as a resource,
would be a huge lapse of judgment
on my part, for me personally.
So, let's hear just a few notes.
I'm going to play, first of all,
the second movement of a Mozart sonata,
K332, and
it will give you an idea of
the intimate quality of this piano.
[MUSIC]
>> Now Dean Blocker turns
from Mozart to Beethoven,
to compare the sound of the opening
of two concertos by Beethoven.
The first concerto, Opus 15,
1797, and the third,
six years later, of 1803.
The point being, how much more
dramatic the latter concerto sounds.
>> So beginning, of course,
with piano solo in C major would be this.
[MUSIC]
So there you have one idea about how this
would open up in this earlier concerto.
The third, is more expansive,
and a bigger piece.
[MUSIC]
So there you see quite a difference in
the way this piano is going to be used.
>> You almost hear Beethoven crying out,
give me a bigger instrument, please!
It is so dramatic, and so intense.
>> And, he's saying, Robert,
please get the right notes.
[LAUGH]
>> Before we leave the early Beethoven
type piano,
let's take a close look at that
knee lever mechanism that Robert Walker
was using to lift the dampers and
allow the strings to continue to sound and
the piano to sing more.
And notice that on this keyboard
you'll see the typical black on white
scheme of today reversed.
In this period, you were just as likely
to see white on black as black on white.
But within a decade, black keys
above white keys became the norm.
All right, now Dean Blocker will play with
the dampers up and then with them down.
>> Possibly the camera can see,
it's a very slight lift here.
And this is the difference
in sound though,
first without it you would hear this.
[MUSIC]
And that's just with finger legato,
but with this you have.
[MUSIC]
It's a way of sustaining the sound
just a little bit longer.
>> Okay, let's slide around the room,
to a larger piano of Beethoven's day.
While not owned by Beethoven, but
a make that he would have played.
It was made by the Bösendorfer
company in Vienna,
a company which very much
still exists today in Vienna.
This Bösendorfer was fabricated in 1830 so
it's an historically correct instrument
for playing late Beethoven and Schubert.
You'll see the greater mass here,
it weighs almost three times as
much as our earlier Könige piano of 1795.
It has a few more keys and as you'll
hear it has a much bigger sound as
Robert Blocker explains, as he introduces
us to this Bösendorfer instrument.
>> It's bigger in mass and
the keyboard is longer.
There's more pitch range there,
and also the key structure is longer.
Depending on the shape of your hands,
very difficult to play
an instrument like this, I think.
Here it gets a little bit easier, with
keys, you can move around a little bit.
This was an instrument that
is particularly conducive
of the music of Schubert.
And I'm gonna play a little bit of that.
But before I do,
if you could travel back a few minutes ago
to these Beethoven concerti
where I just played the opening.
Hear the difference in this piano, which
is designed for what was happening then.
More public concerts in larger spaces.
[MUSIC]
And then the third.
So you have a much larger dynamic
range in this instrument.
The music of Schubert is running
alongside the music of Beethoven here,
and this sonata was written very early
in his sonata works, but
not published until after his death.
And again here you'll hear the range of
dynamics on this particular instrument.
[MUSIC]
Unfortunately, we have to fade
it out here for reasons of time.
But the obvious point here is that
although the pianoforte was invented in
the 1700's, it's not until 1830,
130 years later,
that the piano begins to sound something
like the grand piano that we know today.
But now,
progress really accelerates rapidly.