[MUSIC]
As we continue to move around the room of
the Yale Collection of Musical Instruments
we come to a piano made in Chopin's day,
in Paris in 1842 when the composer,
was at the height of his power.
As you can see by that blue arrow,
it's a kind of piano preferred by Chopin,
a Pleyel piano, but, let's look inside.
Let's look inside at the case here.
And what do we see?
Well, let me see if I can
get my pointer working here.
We see the first signs of
cast iron reinforcement.
See that bar there,
running up in this direction?
Here's another one here.
And you can see faintly this strip
outside around the sounding board,
comes all the way down here.
Down here, across here and
these are anchored.
These are anchored.
These are tied across in this fashion.
Well, cast iron reinforcing for
a piano was invented in America.
In the city of Boston,
in the late 1830s and
the idea was quickly
carried back to Europe.
The point of this was the following,
the strings of the grand piano
are anchored at the far
end in the sounding board.
If you put too much tension on
the sounding board, it can implode.
With metal reinforcement you can put
more strings on the instrument and
really tighten them and
the sound board won't collapse.
Thicker, tighter strings produced
a bigger sound as Robert Blocker
demonstrates with a prelude, a short
freestanding composition by Chopin.
>> I'm going to use two very
different Chopin preludes.
The first in C minor,
which is fortissimo, a huge sound, and
you'll see how this
piano supports that and
then a more intimate
sound in the latter one.
[MUSIC]
And even though there
are pianissimo sounds in there,
there's a different
tamber in the A major and
just maybe the opening phrase of
this prelude will demonstrate that.
[MUSIC]
Its harder to negotiate in some
ways with a very, very light sound.
>> Moving again, we leave the favored
piano of Chopin, the Pleyel and go over to
that of Franz Liszt, an Erard piano,
manufactured again in Paris in 1881.
A couple points to notice here, first, the
Koennicke piano on the left has no pedals,
as we saw before but
rather these knee levers.
This early piano, and this is the second
point, this early piano could make
a very soft sound by bringing strips
of felt up against the strings.
You can see the bright white strips
underneath at the blue arrow there.
They can be pushed up to quiet the sound.
Up above, at the red arrow, are the
dampers that stop the sound completely.
Now, with a piano from the 1820s onward,
the device for lifting these dampers
off the strings was a pedal,
now placed just above the floor.
The same was true for the soft pedal.
Well, how did the soft pedal work?
Well, by the time of this Pleyel and
the Erard, there were at least two and
sometimes three strings for
each key on the keyboard.
And the pedal on the left would slide the
hammers, all the hammers to the right so
that only one string would sound at
a time producing a softer quieter sound.
So, the right pedal lifts the dampers and
allows the sound to carry.
The left piano creates a softer sound.
Damper pedal on the right
at the red arrow.
Soft pedal on the left, at the blue arrow.
Second point,
this Erard piano is a late instrument and
you can clearly see the cast
iron reinforcing bars.
The sound is big, pretty much that
of the concert grand of today,
which will be obvious as
Robert Blocker plays, again,
the same Chopin Prelude in C minor but
now on this larger Erard.
As he plays,
watch his right foot as it clearly
moves the damper pedal up and down.
And notice that just
before the second phrase,
he'll bring in his left foot, bring
it forward, to engage the soft pedal.
Thereby, helping the composer make
his music, what he wanted it to be.
He wanted this phrase to be a soft phase.
So, he's now going to, literally,
soft pedal this last musical idea.
[MUSIC]
>> The Erard is a slightly
larger piano than the Pleyel.
It's a little bit longer,
it has more wood.
But I think, another intangible in
any historical instrument or for
that matter, new instruments,
is how they're cared for.
This piano has had wonderful care.
And one can tell that when you hear it,
as well as when you play it.
The Pleyel has had a more
difficult existence and
in an instrument like that
it's harder to restore.
I think this is an extraordinarily
beautiful instrument, and
just to demonstrate slightly
one other thing for you,
I want to play the opening
of a Schubert impromptu.
And you can literally hear the top
voice just sing on this instrument.
[MUSIC]
So, it has this beautiful
singing quality to it and
hopefully you could hear that earlier
even in the fortissimo sections.
It's truly a remarkable piano.