[MUSIC]
Well, as we follow Robert Blocker
from piano to piano,
I think you're coming to have an
appreciation of why this Yale collection
is arguably the finest collection of
keyboard instruments in the world.
In the far corner you see
another remarkable piano,
one owned by Richard Wagner at his
home in Tribschen, Switzerland.
And it was on this instrument that
Wagner composed parts of the music
of the Ring Cycle,
parts of Siegfried and Gotterdamerung.
And of course, Wagner's father in law,
Franz Liszt played on this piano
as well when he visited Wagner.
Yet as rich as this instrument is,
when Robert Blocker plays it,
you'll be struck by its clarity.
>> And now here today at Yale we
have not only the opportunity for
our students to play and
to learn from this instrument, but
with yet a new technology to
share this with a wider world.
As Craig pointed out earlier,
this piano has a lot of clarity.
And I wanted to use a couple of examples
from the Brahms Intermezzo, Opus 118.
Late pieces in Brahms'
life where he's refined
this orchestra style in
an economy of resources,
and you can hear some of
the contrapuntal things that
I'm going to point out and
what clarity is.
First of all,
an excerpt from Opus 118 Number 2.
[MUSIC]
So you can hear the voices very
clearly interacting with each other.
The piano has a lot of
strength from Opus 116.
Again, the B section of the capriccio.
[MUSIC]
So in this piano we better
understand certainly
the dramatic contrasts that
we hear in Wagner's writing.
Because the piano gives him that basis for
thinking about this in
his own imagination.
>> Now we move to an instrument that
is less clear but much richer in sound,
the massive Steinway of
just three years later,
1867, only three years after
the end of the American Civil War.
The Steinway in the Yale Collection is so
big that it requires a special
corner all to itself.
Notice that it's far bigger
than any instrument we've seen,
the biggest in the collection.
We've arrived at the nine foot
long concert grand of today.
But the year is only 1867.
It was built, not in Vienna or
in Berlin by Germans, but
by German immigrants coming to America,
in this case one Henrick Steinweg.
Now, Herr Steinweg soon became Mr.
Steinway, who setup a piano manufacturing
company in New York in the 1850s.
And we'll be joined by Nicholas Renouf,
senior curator of the collection
to introduce us to this
massive new instrument.
So welcome to America,
that burgeoning dynamic new country in
which technology was changing everything.
We're going to take a look now and
a listen to beautiful large Steinway
piano that has a signficantly different
sound to it than the one we just heard
with the earlier Wagnerian Bechstein.
So we've left Germany, Switzerland,
and now we are only three years later
in the United States with
this new Steinway piano.
>> This instrument, dating from 1867,
was made at a time when our
country was coming of age, not only
industrially, but culturally as well.
Examples such as this, and
instruments by Steinway's rival,
Chickering, set the European
industry on its ears.
They were appalled that we
had done something that so
impressed the public and
musicians as well.
What we see here is
a complete unitary cast iron
frame that's absolutely rigid in its
resistance of the string tension.
So even greater sonority is
possible with this instrument.
It has the overstrung bass that made
history as well as the cast iron frame.
And it gives us really the modern piano.
>> It also, I should add,
has a very different action.
And when we speak of the piano action,
it's the way the keys react
when they're depressed.
And this is a very,
very sensitive action but
certainly not as sensitive as
some of the earlier pianos.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Nothing is as sensitive as that first
Beethoven piano.
But just to give us a good comparison,
I want to use the same Brahms examples
that we did on the Bechstein.
And you can see, even in this wonderful,
large Steinway piano,
you have a clarity of sound and
even more expansive range, and
especially color because
of the cross-stringing.
[MUSIC]
>> To amplify two points
made by Nicholas and Robert,
the massive size of the Steinway is
made possible owing to an innovation
of an American company in Boston,
the Chickering Piano Company.
Now Chickering introduced the uniform or
single piece cast iron frame.
Now you can see on the left here,
the German Bechstein of 1864 with
the pieces of iron that are attached
to other pieces of iron.
With the Steinway, there is much more
iron surrounding the entire sound board.
it's all one piece, single cast.
And a second point, Robert mentioned
the over stringing of the Steinway.
You can see with the Bechstein on
the left that the bass strings
run out in a straight line
with the other strings.
To the right you see that
the Steinway company decided to
take those bass strings and
run them up and over the middle strings.
The earlier Bechstein
did have an advantage.
Parallel stringing did
produce a very clear sound.
The Steinway, with its overstringing,
creates a richer, more homogenous sound.
And after Steinway really all
grand pianos were made with this
overstringing technique.
But as we can see,
the overstringing is more readily apparent
here on this overhead photo
of a modern Steinway.
The middle strings run straight out.
Follow the red arrow there straight out.
While the low bass strings ride up and
over, as indicated by the blue arrow.
Let's go back to the collection now for
a final thanks to our two guests.
So that concludes our brief
tour of this extraordinary
collection of keyboard instruments.
Again, arguably the finest collection
of keyboard instruments in the world.
My thanks to Robert Blocker,
Dean of the Yale School of Music,
Senior Curator Nicholas Renouf of
the collection of musical instruments.
This collection, this splendid
collection is open to the public.
So if you're ever in New Haven
please come join me and
join our colleagues at
the collection here at Yale.
Thanks very much.
And the final takeaway from our visit
to the Yale collection of musical
instruments, in the first 100 years
of the existence of the piano,
from its invention in 1700 to the piano of
around 1800, not all that much changed.
But during the next 60 years or so,
up to the Steinway of 1867 that we saw,
the piano changed enormously,
going from an almost tiny toy with limited
sound to a monster of various colors and
huge sound.
Notice of course that all this happened
during what period in Western history?
Well, the Industrial Revolution
in Europe and America.
For the piano, the great age of change
was the 60 years between 1800 and 1860.
And not much has changed on
the concert grand since then.
The Industrial Revolution
with the piano and
with other musical instruments,
as we'll see, was the first great era
of technological change in
Western musical history.
The second great change of
technological advance came
during the 20th century with
the popularization of recorded music.
And then especially with a capacity to
digitalize recorded sound to the point
that the entire world of music can
now be contained in a phone and
held in your hand.
Now that's real change.