[MUSIC]
Here we see on the screen
a portrait of Frederic Chopin,
as painted by his very good
friend Eugène Delacroix.
In his day, Chopin was called the poet of
the piano, and he wrote exclusively for
the piano.
No purely instrumental works,
other than those for the piano, or
that involve the piano one way or
another as a accompanied instrument.
Chopin was Polish by birth, but
his father was french, a french citizen.
And Chopin himself spent almost
all of his adult life in Paris.
In the end living comfortably
in an apartment on the trendy
Place Vendôme across from where
the Ritz Hotel stands today.
And in this apartment,
Chopin died in 1849 at the age of just 39.
Chopin was slight of frame and
weak of constitution.
He actually died of tuberculosis.
And unlike his friend Franz Liszt,
Chopin much preferred
the quiet calm of the exclusive
salon of the well to do,
to the, Rather large public concert hall.
Chopin's favored instrument was
a Pleyel piano, as we've seen.
Made by the firm of Camille Pleyel.
This one constructed in 1842.
To the right, you see an actual photograph
of Chopin, taken in his last year, 1849.
A sickly figure.
As to what Chopin wrote for,
and played on the piano,
well, Nocturnes, Etudes, Preludes.
We heard Robert Blocker play,
Chopin's Prelude in C minor.
Music with a Polish national or
nationalistic flavor, Mazurkas and
Polonaises, and
two lovely piano concertos.
Our aim with Chopin, will be to focus on
the Nocturne genre that he made famous.
What's a Nocturne?
Well as the name suggests it's a night
piece, but a dreamy night piece.
No nightmares here, only blissful,
perhaps romantic sleeps.
Invariably we hear a gentle
rocking accompaniment in the bass,
that's often spun out as an arpeggio.
And a beautiful melody comes in above.
As we listen to the lovely Nocturne in
Db Major, notice that this style of music
is almost identical to that which we
will hear later with Bel canto opera.
Indeed the arpeggios below simply recreate
the big guitar effect, as we'll call it.
The big guitar effect,
as we will hear in our next session.
When he arrived in Paris in 1830, Chopin
heard much Bel canto opera by Bellini and
Donizetti, and that idiom obviously
seeped deep into his musical psyche,
into his musical consciousness.
[MUSIC]
Lovely.
Let's move on to hear parts
of a more famous Nocturne.
One in E Flat Major.
You've likely heard it before.
It was dedicated to,
as you can see here, to Camille Pleyel,
the piano maker, piano manufacturer.
Here we have melody and
chordal accompanied now,
moving with the accompanied here,
moving constantly in a low,
let me see if I can get my cursor
working here, low, middle,
high, low, middle, high,
low, middle, high fashion.
And then up above, of course,
here is the melody.
Let's listen to it.
[MUSIC]
Now in his Nocturne,
we hear this songful melody four times,
each subsequent time in
a more elaborate form.
Chopin is obviously working through
here theme and variation form.
Let's hear one of these
ornamented variations,
as indicated within the blue braces.
[MUSIC]
Finally the end.
And again, the sound of Bel canto singing
comes to mind as we listen to the soprano
line work up to a peak, and then hold
as the music stops on a half cadence,
or a pause cadence,
a pause chord on the dominant.
And then we enjoy a solo
vocal like cadenza,
before a final simple iteration
of the tonic major triad.
[MUSIC]