[MUSIC]
Here's an interesting image.
It's a painting done in 1840,
by Josef Danhauser.
In it we see all the artistic
luminaries of the 19th century.
A portrait of Lord George Byron
was on the wall.
Well, he was dead by 1840.
That's why you have a painting of Byron.
Here he is, up here.
And then, arm in arm,
the composer, Rossini, next to
the violin virtuoso, Niccolo Pioneer.
Standing over here the great French
poet of the 19th Century, Victor Hugo.
Seated here,
we have Alexander Du Mot Pair,
author of the novel The Count of
Monte Cristo and The Three Musketeers.
Over to his left is Chopin's paramour,
Aurore Dudevant.
Who worked under the name of George Sand,
George Sand, the author of numerous,
highly successful, popular novels.
She, of course, had to take a nom de
plume because it was difficult for
any woman to get any attention as
an artist in the 19th century.
Always smoking cigars, as was her want.
Down here in supine position,
we have Marie Dagul, author of seven
important books on French history.
She, too, had to write under a nom de
plume, Daniel Stern, in that case.
Up here, on top of the piano,
an overly large bust of
Beethoven who looks down on
the assembly from Olympian heights.
Beethoven was the artistic figure
who dominated in the 19th century.
All of these great artists look
reverentially, in silence, upon Beethoven,
and none less so than Franz Liszt,
seated at the piano, the greatest pianist,
pianist, of the day, and look at
the enormous size of his hands here.
So there they all were.
Well, actually they all weren't.
These individuals never came together for
this portrait.
They were just painted
in from other images.
In modern parlance,
this whole things was Photoshopped.
What was it, then?
Well, it was a marketing ploy,
effected by a piano manufacturer,
one of the many then working in Vienna,
one Conrad Graf.
The painting, as we said, was a marketing
tool of the sort that we have today.
If Derek Jeter or Roger Federer wear
a Movado watch, you should, too.
If Franz Liszt plays a Graf piano,
you should, too.
So, go out and buy one.
Enjoy it.
Choosing Liszt as the poster boy for
the piano was clever salesmanship, for no
one was better known as a virtuoso pianist
in the 19th century than Franz Liszt.
He was a towering figure.
He had movie star good looks, and
he always liked to be painted showing
the right side of his face because he
had a large mole on the left side.
And he was the rock star
of the nineteenth century.
Three thousand, mostly women,
would crowd into the newly enlarged
concert hall to hear him
play all across Europe.
We once had Beatlemania in the 1960s, but
the use of the term artist's name plus
mania was first coined back
in the 1840s by the German
poet and reclaimed it for Liszt.
Lisztomania it was called.
Women fought for a lock of his hair.
For a torn away part of his velvet gloves.
They threw flowers at him on the stage.
Through his public performances,
Liszt established the piano
recital as we know it today.
Liszt was the person who actually
coined the term, recital.
It was a poetic recitation in music and
by Liszt alone.
Up to that time a solo artist would have
to share a program with other performers.
You'd think you got cheated if
more than one, only one showed up.
Liszt was also the first
to turn the piano.
At right angles to the stage,
again possible because he
favored his right side.
Anyway, it was quite a show,
and Liszt lived life large.
I could go on and on.
It's really a fascinating life of
a flamboyant figure and a great artist.
And oh, did I mention that later in life,
after many mistresses on many continents.
Bougival Lizst took holy orders and
lived in the Vatican for a while.
I'm not making this up.
And styled himself as Abby Liszt.
And here we see Abby Lizst later in
life in saucerdoodle dress playing for
a large well-to-do group.
Maybe with an emperor and
his son in the front row, I can't be sure.
But what I can be sure of is
that the piano he was playing is
a Viennese Bösendorfer because the name
is right there above the keyboard.
We saw a Bösendorfer in the Yale
collection earlier on in this session.
And again, the adoring crowr,
crowd here has thrown flowers at his feet.
But if Liszt had a choice, especially
when he was in France or England,
he preferred and Erard piano of
the sort that we have seen before.
And here's an instrument with a history.
Remember, we said that,
earlier on in our session,
we said that the two most
innovative companies or
piano manufacturing at this time
were not in Europe but in America.
One was Steinway in New York.
The other is Chickering in Boston.
And just as manufacturer
Conrad Graf did a bit
of celebrity marketing with Liszt, so
too did the American firm Chickering.
Chickering shipped this
gigantic grand piano,
concert grand nine feet long as
you can see there, all the way
to the Vatican where Liszt was living for
a while in the 1860s.
And then over the Alps to Hungary,
to Liszt's home in Budapest.
And here's where it rests today, in Pest.
A massive state of the art.
And grand piano in every way.
Well, what did Liszt write for the piano.
Well, he wrote Hungarian Rhapsodies and
transcriptions for
the piano, such as we saw with
regard to Schubert's Erlking,
Liszt transcribed this into
a piano-only arrangement.
And we have the studies,
the transcendatal transcendental etudes,
and the concert etudes.
So, what's an etude?
That's a study.
Etude is a piece with the aim to
improve someone's technique through
practice the particular aspect
of performance to teach, well,
maybe how to play a chromatic scale very,
very rapidly.
Or to keep your hands
together while leaping up and
down in octaves and not miss any notes.
Or play an arpeggio with just
the left hand alone whatever.
Maybe your mother made you practice
etudes or studies of Clementi or
perhaps Cramer when you were
a fledgeling young pianist.
As a youngster.
Well, there's an irony
here with Lizst etudes.
They're so difficult that you
have to already be a virtuoso to
play the etudes that would
allow you to become a virtuoso.
Lizst etudes are really no help
at all to those wishing to
learn how to play the piano.
Only a dozen or so
people on the planet Earth,
as Robert Schumann famously commented,
could actually play these etudes by Liszt.
They were of transcendent,
transcendental difficulty.
Let's give a listen to just one of
the transcendental etudes by Liszt.
One entitled Wild Hunt.
Don't try this at home kids.
[MUSIC]
Now, of course, almost every
successful public figure is likely
to be the object of cartoons and
caricature at one time or another.
And Liszt was no exception.
Piano player, as we see here,
or was he piano slayer?
But one thing that such images
seem to have in common is this,
that Liszt appeared to have
more than just two hands.
And critics referred to
his three-hand trick.
He could keep a bass and soprano going,
but somehow fill the melody in in
the middle with another, third, hand.
Now, while all this might seem like just
pure showmanship, technical razzle dazzle
of the most superficial sort,
don't sell Liszt short here.
Sometimes, there is
extraordinary artistry,
far-seeing artistry, in his music.
I want to end this session with a bit of
Liszt's etude, called Un Sospiro, a sigh.
And it does have, in the midst
of all the technical virtuosity,
the loveliest, sort of sigh-like melody.
But it's the end that
impresses me the most.
There are some bizarre chordal
shifts involving a tritone.
Let me see if I can
play just one of these.
[MUSIC]
That's a strange relationship.
And this Etude concludes with a core
progression of the sort that no
one else was writing it this time.
The kind of rich harmonic sound that will
only become commonplace 50 years later.
Liszt was not only a showman,
he was a visionary.
[MUSIC]
Harmonic shift.