[MUSIC]
That was music from George Gershwin's
1930 musical Crazy Girl and
the song I've Got Rhythm.
Well we've all got rhythm.
Rhythm, along with melody,
harmony, tone, color, texture and
form, are the essential elements of music.
We'll be exploring these elements
in our next several sessions.
We'll start with rhythm,
because rhythm provides a framework,
a framework in time in which sounds,
pitches, can rest.
We all have rhythm, of our lives,
and a beat, a heart beat.
And, of course,
there's a beat in music too.
Most music has a regular pulse to it.
Some music, Gregorian chant, for
example, doesn't have a beat.
Here's a group of singers I organized some
years ago singing a Gregorian chant at
Yale University,
along with an image of a chant manuscript
from the Yale rare book library.
In this music there really is no beat.
[MUSIC]
Very beautiful, but no beat.
Pop music usually has a very strong beat.
That's one of the things
that makes it popular.
We respond,
almost primordially, to a beat.
Here's an example of a pop
piece with a strong beat, and
also a strong backbeat that
helps us emphasize the beat.
It's a video created as a somewhat
organized, or maybe disorganized,
flash mob, or flash dance, recently in
the main library of Yale University.
[INAUDIBLE]
[MUSIC]
Pretty good.
It's almost impossible not
to tap your foot to that.
In classical music, there is a beat,
but it's often suppressed.
It's more subdued.
The rock musician, Brian Eno,
who worked with the Beatles,
once said classical music
is music without Africa.
Meaning that music without
a strong rhythmic profile.
And for the most part, he was right.
But here's an example of classical music
in which there is a pretty clear beat,
Pomp and Circumstance March by
the classical composer Edward Elgar.
You've probably heard it at a graduation.
[MUSIC]
Not surprising that in this classical
movement, the beat is pronounced because
we're supposed to march to it
during a graduation ceremony.
I'd say in Pomp and Circumstance,
we have a medium strong beat.
But here's a much better example of what
I mean when I say the classical music
often has a suppressed beat.
Or the sound of the beat is weak.
Indeed, where is the beat here?
Can you tap your foot to it like
you could with the Macklemore?
Here's Debussy's Claire de lune.
[MUSIC]
So, we have heard strong beat,
medium beat,
and very weak beat or suppressed beat.
Beats come along in regular intervals and
are of the same duration, regular beat.
However, the western psyche doesn't like
streams of undifferentiated anything.
We group time into units of seconds,
minutes, and hours to make sense of it.
We group decades and centuries into
periods and call them the Renaissance and
the Enlightenment, to help us make
sense of what would otherwise be
a seemingly endless flow of time.
I'm convinced that in
my Toyota automobile,
the safety belt alarm goes ding-ding-ding,
ding-ding-ding, ding-ding-ding if I
don't have my seat belt fastened.
So too in music, we group the endless
flow of beats to make sense of them.
Here's an undifferentiated flow of beats.
We can sound them with this gadget.
And we've been doing that
since the time of Beethoven.
[SOUND]
Called of
course a metronome.
And here's what we instinctively do.
We take these beats and
group them into units of two.
So here are the beats.
Now group into units of two, or
we can group them into units of three.
And of four.
But in fact, in most, but not always,
music written in four beats is just
a multiple of music in two beats.
So really, for our course, we are going
to have just two beat music and
three beat music.
Music in duple or music in triple meter.
Now, I just used the word meter there.
When we group beats into regularly
recurring units, we create meter in music.
Meter is simply a pattern of
regularly recurring beats.
The lines that separate the groups
are called bar lines or measure lines.
Each unit constitutes a bar or a measure.
Bar lines tend to make
western music on a grid.
Other cultures don't have
this kind of grid, and
as a result their music is
a good deal more flexible.
But we in the west, we have these
measure lines, or these bar lines, and
it's almost as if you can't
break out from behind the bars.
That you're kept inside of the measure.
Okay, so we've talked about beats,
and meters, and measures, or
bars and bar lines.
Now, let's take a look at this same
material in a slightly different way,
but before that,
I've got a question for you.
What are the two axes, or
coordinates, of music?
Again, what are the two axes,
or coordinates of music?
Right.
Pitch and duration.
Otherwise said, sound and time.
Pitch is represented on a vertical
axis in written form, and
time on a horizontal one.
Here's a graph to demonstrate this.
Now, here's a score of
a piano piece by Beethoven.
This musical score is
just a complex version
of this previous slide's simple idea.
Pitch is indicated vertically,
time horizontally.
How do we get from this simple
idea of a two axes graph
to this complex version of musical
notation that you see on the screen?
Well, we'll look at that
in our next segment.