[MUSIC]
Let's look at some images
of musical notation.
But we should say at the outset that
Western music is the only musical culture
that uses musical notation
in a controlling way.
Yes, there is Chinese musical notation,
and there is Indian musical notation.
But neither controls the creation and
performance of music
to the extent that notation does in
the Western classical tradition.
So how did Western musical notation begin?
How did we get from this
complex score here?
How did we get to it?
Well, let's look at some slides,
and see how this unfolded.
Western musical notation began when
musicians in monasteries, around the year
900, common era, began to create
a graphic image of their music.
They tried to capture and
freeze sound onto paper,
or in this case onto parchment.
And they did so in this fashion.
Notice all the undulations here.
The musical scribes are trying
to represent the high and
low flow of the music by graphic symbols.
They look like worms, squiggling across
the page, but they're called, these little
aggregates are called neumes, neumes that
represented a collection of pitches.
If the voice produced a high pitch,
they wrote a visually higher symbol.
Eventually, these neumes were separated
into individual discrete pitches
called notae, hence our word note,
a symbol for a pitch.
But these notes, originally, were only
indicators of pitch, not duration.
Eventually, as you can see by both
the left and right hand image here,
eventually musicians introduced
the practice of assigning
each note a particular note
shape to indicate its duration.
The note could have tail on it or a flag,
or could be filled in or it could be open.
It could have a dot after it and so on.
It took several hundred years
from roughly 1200 to 1600 for
this system of symbols representing
duration to quite literally take shape.
So now we understand something of
the origins of these notational symbols
in the West.
And they are just symbols of something.
They represent something,
pitch and duration.
Let's look at how we use them today.
Originally the beat in music was
carried by this thing, the open circle,
the whole note,
as you see on the left of the screen.
Then as more and more texts was added
to the music over the centuries
the beat fell down to the half
note as the beat carrier.
And today, most music is represented by
the symbol in the middle of the page,
the quarter note as carrying the beat.
The quarter note as beat carrying unit.
Notice here that we have
a duple division in the music.
Whole note is divided into two halves,
half note into two quarters,
quarter note into two eighths, and so on.
There's also a triple division,
which is affected by means of a dot
that adds 50% of the value to the note.
This makes a half note equal to two,
not three quarter notes.
The dotted quarter equal to three
eighth notes, not just two, and so on.
And this is how we get
triple meter in music.
We can see how this works in a patriotic
song, known in the US as My Country
'Tis of Thee, elsewhere as God Save
the King or God Save the Queen.
On the top, you see the text.
Beneath it,
horizontal dashes to show duration.
Then duration appears in a different way.
In musical symbols.
Then the beat is shown by
quarter notes below it.
Again, the quarter notes
represent the beat in most music.
Finally, we see the position of
the quarter note within each measure.
But we don't want to make
things too complex here.
This should be a course about emotions and
feelings.
You don't have to read musical
notation to feel and to have emotions.
You don't have to read musical notation
to get a great deal out of music,
to get a great deal out of this course.
Generally speaking,
here's all you have to know.
Whenever you see a musical example,
musical notation signs
placed higher vertically
represent high sounding pitches.
Lower signs mean lower sounding pitches.
Notation that gets increasingly darker
with more flags on it represents
that that music is moving faster up and
down, left to right.
Darker means faster.
I'll play it for you.
[MUSIC]
You can imagine how the reverse of
that operates coming back down.
Voila, that's all you need to
know about musical notation.
[MUSIC]