[MUSIC]
Beat and
meter are rather easy to understand.
Oddly rhythm is a bit more complicated.
Rhythm is the organization of time
into compelling patterns of long and
short sounds.
Here's a famous melody, one created
by the French composer, Maurice Ravel
from his ballet, Bolero of 1928.
There's a tune, a succession of higher and
lower pitches shown vertically.
And there's a rhythm moving left to right.
Now let's strip away pitch and
leave the rhythm alone.
And it will look like this
as we see on our next slide.
But what we hear first at the beginning
of Bolero is not the melody but
another rhythm.
This one.
And it's played by a snare drum.
Now a snare drum, as you may know,
has no particular pitch.
It just plays a rhythm, pure rhythm.
I'll tap it.
[MUSIC]
And that's all the snare drum player does.
So he better like that pattern,
he's gonna be doing it for the next 14 and
a half minutes.
Now beneath the snare drum pattern,
low strings play another rhythm that
provides something of a harmony.
Let's take a look at that now.
Bum.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
Eventually, the flute enters,
adding the enchanting melody.
So now we have three
rhythms operating here.
One in the flute,
which also carries the melody.
One in the snare drum,
which is a simple, or pure rhythm.
And a third in the bass,
which is providing something of
a harmony below the melody up above.
So, we have three rhythms
that are staying within and
emphasizing the structure of the measure.
Three different rhythms
sounding simultaneously,
three different patterns of longs and
shorts.
Let's give a listen to
the South Korean Phil Harmonic Orchestra
as it performs this work.
I like the recording engineering here,
it's very easy to hear
the three musical parts.
[MUSIC]
So who's playing the beat here?
Well, no one is actually playing the beat.
About the only time an instrument
plays the beat in the music is when
the bass drum in a marching
band plays the beat.
Or maybe a drummer in a rock band
playing the bass drum by means
of left foot on a pedal.
So how is it then that we hear the beat?
Well, we hear.
[MUSIC]
Well, our ear, actually our brain,
digest this complex of information and
extrapolates it from it a basic structural
framework underlying the music.
So kinda platonic mental reality
over arching structure that
no one actually hears.
No one actually sees but it's there.
But we do hear the beat.
And we hear the beats organized
into groups of three.
One two three, one two three, and so on.
Bollero is written in triple meter.
We feel the triple meter, and
that's all that really counts.
But if we want confirmation of this,
we can look at the musical notation,
particularly the base, where we
see clearly three quarter notes or
the equivalent of three
quarter notes in each measure.
Why do we hear?
It is triple meter.
To see how that works,
let's turn to a class video demonstration.
[MUSIC]
What's the key here?
What do you listen to?
How many think it's in duple meter?
Raise your hand.
How many think it's in triple meter?
Okay, almost everybody thinks it's
a duple meter, and that's correct.
Now, we worked through this
just a little bit once before,
what is it that tells us
that it's in duple meter?
It's the?
>> Bass.
[MUSIC]
Because it's organizing itself
very strongly in duple patterns.
There's one other
interesting thing in here.
This would be, well, let's think
through that in one additional way.
And that is, notice that in duple
meter we have a strong beat.
Right?
Strong, weak, strong, weak, strong,
weak, strong, weak, in that sense.
Or if we have triple, it would be
strong weak, weak, strong, weak, weak.
There would be two weak beats, or two
unstressed beats between each strong beat.
We could do this.
[MUSIC]
And we'd have the waltz of the bulldog.
It'd be pretty cool to see actually.
>> [LAUGH]
>> So there,
I'm simply taking the Cole Porter piece
and throwing in an extra beat in each
measure, an unstressed beat in each
measure, and it works out pretty well.
Notice, this would be, Harvard would've
had a field day with this melody if
Cole Porter had not done one thing.
He makes this really rather snappy
by the use of this kind of stuff.
[MUSIC]
We're coming in on bum, bum, bum,
bum, and it's dun, dun, dun, dun,
da-dun, dun, dun, da-dun.
What's that a good example of?
Syncopation.
Yeah, terms on the board up there.
But it's a good example of syncopation.
Sort of jumping in ahead of time, cutting
off the beginning in there ahead of time.
And throwing off the metrical balance for
a very short period of time.
Okay, let's see now if you can hear the
difference between duple and triple meter.
I'll play two examples.
[MUSIC]
That's number one, here's another one.
Which is duple, which is triple?
[MUSIC]
Right.
The first one was triple,
second one was duple.
How'd you do?
Well here's one more.
Let's try another, one last one of these.
You'll like it.
First there was music by Hendel.
That was this piece.
[MUSIC]
That's our triple meter piece and
we had music by Schubert.
This is our duple meter piece.
[MUSIC]
Let's try one other one.
What about this one?
[MUSIC]
And so on.
Right again.
Triple meter.