[MUSIC]
At the end of the class video I
was talking about syncopation.
What's syncopation?
Well actually the term comes from
a Greek word, syncope, to cut off,
or to to compress.
In music, syncopation works this way.
A composer sets up a beat and
an expectation of a beat.
But then,
throws in a strong pulse off that beat.
Something off the beat.
Here are two examples.
[MUSIC]
Here's our beat.
So there is a simple instance of
syncopation, where you see the arrows.
Let's take a look at another example here.
This time from the well know theme song to
the TV or the cartoon show, The Simpsons.
So we could start a beat.
[MUSIC]
Pretty catchy,
maybe that's why that show is so popular.
To drive home the point of
syncopation one more time,
let's watch another class video.
So let's play just a little bit
of The Entertainer very slowly.
My question to you is
where is the syncopation?
Is it in the left hand of the piano or
in the right hand of the piano.
Is it in the bass or the melody?
[MUSIC]
Where's the syncopation, left hand?
Right hand?
Right hand.
Bass is just going.
Well, what is the bass going?
[MUSIC]
In that fashion.
One, it's playing eighth notes.
One and two and, sub divided into beat.
Where as the syncopation.
[MUSIC]
It's there.
Ya di, di, di, di, di and so on.
So you're tapping your foot,
you're tapping the beat.
And a lot of the music
is coming off the beat.
Let's see if we can do that.
Let's see if we can create our
own syncopated orchestra in here.
We've got an example up here,
this is the conception of it.
Let's see if we can actually execute it.
What I'd like you to do,
everybody tap your foot,
we're gonna do this in fours just for
because I think it works out better.
So everybody tap your
foot with a four beat.
Here we go one, two, three, four,
one, two, three, four nice and loud.
Come on.
I wanna hear it.
[SOUND] Okay, now take your
hand on a chair, your notebook,
your computer, whatever and
do syncopation off of that.
According to this pattern.
One, two, ready go.
Da da da da da da da da da
da da da da da da da da
da da da da da da da da da da da
da da da da da da, da, da, dum.
Okay, good,
I see Daniel down here's got this nailed.
Okay.
So that's what syncopation is and
it isn't much more difficult than that.
But if syncopation is hearing
an accent off the beat,
how is it that composers tell
us initially where the beat is?
And what the meter is?
Crucial here is the phenomenon
of the downbeat.
The most stressed and
always the first sound of every measure.
It's called the downbeat
among other reasons,
because the conductor's hand always goes
down with the first beat in every measure.
One, two, one, two, or one,
two, three, one, two, three.
Composers are always sending us messages.
Messages in musical sound,
not spoken words.
There are four ways that composers signal
to us where the downbeat is in music.
Four ways they tell us where to stomp our
foot most loudly to get things organized.
In fact, when you dance,
you've gotta get the composer's message.
You've gotta get a sense of where
the downbeat is or you can't proceed.
So here's how composers tell
us where the downbeat is.
Through duration, through accent, through
range, and through change of harmony.
Exactly how this works is
shown in the next class video.
Okay, way number one.
Way number one.
That has to do with duration, duration.
Notes are simply longer.
Held longer.
That's how we have a sense
of where the downbeat is.
[MUSIC]
Beautiful.
I guess it's a spiritual.
Beautiful music.
But think about that.
[MUSIC]
Short long, short long,
short long, short long,
short long, short long, short long.
And all of those long notes
are coming on the downbeat.
So that's how we start to
hear that as a downbeat.
And that's how we know to make
our hand go down at that point.
So that's one way.
Now another way is through accent.
And to exemplify this let's turn to some
classical music, the music of Mozart.
So here we have Mozart's 40th Symphony.
His famous G minor symphony, and
Linda, go ahead and start to play it.
Just go ahead.
Maybe a second or two before it pops up,
but it's gonna come up.
[MUSIC]
Several of you were
actually conducting this.
That's great.
Okay this happens to be in duple meter and
that's fine.
That wasn't the question here but great.
You're hearing that and I'm delighted.
What Mozart has done here, if we could
get the score up here of Mozart's music,
we would see that he has put
a little sort of arrow, over top of,
a wedge over top of each of the downbeats.
[MUSIC]
So that the string player
will really accent those.
But the string player would
be accenting them anyway.
Why?
Any violinists in here, or
anybody ever played a stringed instrument?
What are you always told to do?
If you are playing a downbeat with
an up bow, are you in good shape?
No, no, no, no, no.
Your teacher would not be happy with that,
your bowing pattern is probably
backward at that point.
String players are taught, whether it's
cellists going this way, downbeat, or
violas and violinists coming down this way
that the downward motion of the hand or
the strong pull across should
come with the downbeat.
That emphasizes the downbeat.
That's how we know the downbeat.
So, so far we've had duration and accent.
Mozart is actually
writing accent into this.
The third way that composers signal to us,
that we pick up almost intuitively,
the whereabouts of downbeats is
through patterns of accompaniment.
We'll call it range.
Here's a waltz by Ricard Strauss, not to
be confused excuse me, by Johann Strauss,
not to be confused with Ricard Strauss,
that we heard last time.
[MUSIC]
>> And so on.
What is important here is the left hand.
>> [MUSIC]
>> That's why we hear
a triple pattern here.
We're hearing two weak beats and
the strong beat is always
in the lower position here.
So we're getting low, middle,
middle, low, middle, middle.
Or it could be something as we had
the other day in the Tchaikovsky
piano concerto.
Low, middle, high, low, middle,high.
But each time the downbeat
seems to be coming
in association with that lowest note.
So, range or
position here in the accompaniment can
often times signal this information to us.
And finally, and
most important, these others I think
have been pretty straight forward.
These others have been
pretty straight forward.
But, what has not been straight
forward is something that you might
listen to many, many times, and not be
aware of, and that is chord changes.
If you know that we have chords in music.
[MUSIC]
Sort of these building blocks
that support a melody.
And they have to change for
that melody to be consonant all the time.
But where they change,
often times, is on the downbeat.
Most frequently,
chord changes come on the downbeat.
So, composers signal to us in
a fourth way, the downbeat,
by means of chord change.
Now, we're gonna play you just
a little bit of pop music.
Not too loud, Linda,
'cuz this thing is really hyped up.
But let's listen to a little of this.
It's in a straight forward four.
Rock really comes forth not so
much in twos but in fours, so
we'll call this a four four and you can
kind of beat a four pattern to it, or
you can beat a two pattern,
it doesn't really matter.
But notice that whenever the chords are
changing, they're changing on downbeats.
So let's hear a little bit of this and
then we'll stop so they don't sue us for
copyright infringement, when we go
somewhere else and take another chunk.
[MUSIC]
Okay, listen.
Change.
[MUSIC]
Okay, so that's all they're doing there.
They're just taking every
time their changing, and
also every time I say change, and
eventually you'd be saying change too.
Every time they're changing,
your hand is going down.
Your hand is going down.
So chord changes may be
the most powerful of all
of these aspects of where the downbeat is.