[MUSIC]
Finally, one last thing that has
to do with duration in music.
And that is tempo.
That's a very simple idea.
Life has a tempo, and so does music.
Tempo in music is simply
the speed of the beat.
We have a moderate tempo,
which is actually called moderato.
And we have faster tempos
that are called allegro.
And very fast there are vivace and
prestissimo, and you get the idea.
And we have slower ones called adagio and
lento, that sort of thing.
We can represent this on a slide
that shows us the different
tempos and
the number of beats per minute here.
Let's try this one.
We're gonna start all the way at the top
here with lento, very slow tempo.
Gonna move this up in the middle
now at about moderato,
then up to allegro, vivace,
presto and ultimately prestissimo.
And just a final word about tempo.
We can speed it up or slow it down.
If I speed it up, I create an accelerando,
just the Italian word for acceleration.
Similarly, if I slow it down,
I create a ritardando, a retard.
Now normally in music, we like to
have a steady beat, steady tempo.
And that usually happens in pop music
where there is a steady beat, and
especially in rock where there's
a hard-driving steady beat
to which you can dance.
We dance to a steady tempo.
But in classical music,
which is rarely dance music,
musicians like to play with the notion
of tempo just a little bit.
Nuance the beat ever so
slightly at moments that are important to
the articulation of
the structure of the piece.
They delay the beat just a little,
maybe push ahead here, pull back there.
I could play the following passage by
Robert Schumann very regularly, and
it would sound one way, or
with slight variation in tempo and
it would sound another.
Let's patch in a bit of video played
from a good Steinway playing the beat
at first in a steady fashion,
and then nuancing it slightly.
Okay, so
now we're gonna do a little experiment.
We're gonna differentiate what happens
when you play exactly on the beat,
exactly on tempo.
As opposed to what happens when you
loosen things up a little bit and
allow the beat to be nuanced ever so
slightly.
To make sure that we're really are staying
on the beat, let's turn on this gadget.
Once again, this is our metronome, and
this will give us a beat here, three,
four, one, two, three, four.
[MUSIC]
[NOISE] Get out of my face,
get out of here.
[LAUGH] So,
let's try it now a different sort of way.
Let me play with the beat and
the tempo ever so slightly.
Pushing it ahead here when
I feel that that's what
the rhetoric of the music demands,
pulling back here when we're coming
up to a major point of articulation.
Same music, but without the metronome.
[MUSIC]
Cognitive psychologists have done
studies that show that we respond
emotionally much more favorably
to music that is every so
slightly off the beat, ever so
slightly off pitch now and then.
Next time you listen to your favorite
pop singer, just listen to how he or
she can be slightly off pitch at
one moment or slightly off tempo
at one moment, and then pull it back on.
That moment of intentional
imperfection of the beat or the pitch,
that adds emotional intensity
to our musical experience.
Predictably, reality is on the beat.
Art is slightly off the beat,
slightly off beat.
Art makes reality a lot more exciting.