[MUSIC]
>> Have you ever been to an opera?
You ever seen an opera live on per son or
broadcast on television or
in high definition HD at a movie theater?
If you like opera, many people do,
many people don't.
Why not?
Who do some people not like Opera?
But many people do love opera.
Students, retirees, everyday folk,
and I happen to be one of them.
And you don't need a lot
of money to see opera live.
You can do so now via HD broadcast and
movie theaters around the world.
It'll cost a movie ticket and
the quality is very, very good.
Online brings opera to everyone,
just like digital education brings
education to everyone in our digital age.
So I'm a big proponent of the art
form of opera, and it's my job here
to convince you of the power, the beauty,
and yes, even the glamour of opera.
Let's start with a quick review of
what we've learned up to this point
in our course about opera.
Which composers have we studied?
And by way of a,
are you paying attention quiz,
which one person have we not studied?
Well, you see the names here.
And, of course, we have not studied
an opera by the magician Harry Houdini.
He didn't write any.
But we had looked at parts
of operas by Monteverdi and
Purcell and Handel and Mozart.
And now, as we come into the Romantic era,
to simplify it greatly,
we see two strong operatic traditions.
The first, of course,
is the Italian tradition.
The Italians started opera.
Wait a minute, you'll say,
Handel was German and Mozart,
well he came from Austria.
They weren't Italian.
Yes, that's true, but both made a living
as opera composers writing Italian opera.
The other tradition that develops,
somewhat later,
is the German operatic tradition.
We'll omit the French and
the English here for the moment.
The German tradition.
Well Mozart, Weber, Wagner, Strauss, and
carrying us into the 20th Century
Schoenberg and his pupil Alban Berg.
But how do we know that these
are the dominant traditions?
Who says that they are?
Who says what matters?
Well the people do.
The people who go to opera houses.
Let's look at the operas offered by
the metropolitan opera of New York City.
New York is very much an international
city, so it's representative.
When adding up the numbers for
one recent season
I came to see that the operas of
Giuseppe Verdi and Mozart dominate.
But the absence of German
opera surprised me.
So I went back one year and
looked at the repertoire for that season.
And it seemed to be more typical.
Richard Wagner was more prominent.
Again, the Italian
tradition with Verde and
now the German tradition
with Wagner dominate.
And that's what we'll be talking
about briefly in this session.
The important thing to note is this,
in both Metropolitan Opera seasons,
opera is written during the 19th century,
the romantic era, dominate the stage.
About three-quarters of
the opera that we hear today,
they were composed in the Romantic period,
the 19th century.
Romantic escapism and
opera seem to go hand in hand.
And just to make sure that we're all
back up to speed before proceeding,
here's a quick quiz for you to engage.
We have six blanks and four terms,
so two of the terms get used twice.
Have a go at it.