[MUSIC]
Bel canto is a term that was frequently
heard in connection with opera,
most especially with Italian opera.
And it applies to type of singing,
a type of music and a type of opera
that arose in Italy during the 1820s with
Rossini and then Bellini and Donizetti.
And continued with the operas of Giuseppe
Verdi and into those of Giacomo Puccini.
Literally, bel canto,
means beautiful singing, singing with
an especially rich, luxurious tone.
Although that sound can sometimes
be intense and dramatic as well.
As a type of music, bel canto means that
the music of the opera is focused almost
entirely on the aria.
And that the music of the aria has
focused entirely on the voice,
the beautiful lyrical tones of the voice.
To be blunt, in bel canto opera,
the accompanying orchestra
has little to do except
plunk out supporting chords.
It's in a way, under employed.
Let's look for
example at an aria here, Casta diva.
You can see the very simple accompaniment.
Only tonic and dominant chords
strung out as an arpeggio here.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
Sounds like a guitar
strumming in the background,
hence the expression big guitar effect.
Because of the simple nature
of the accompaniment,
all of the attention is
focused on the soprano voice.
In this case, we had the auria Casta diva,
Chase goddess from Bellini's opera Norma.
Here Norma sings about the Chase goddess,
the moon.
Although the chase women of
the opera is Norma herself.
By coincidence this notion of the Diva,
the goddess, becomes a word to denote
the female goddess of the opera,
the perhaps temperamental soprano.
It's a term we begin to hear in the 19th
century associated with a female singer
in a similar way as we associate
the term prima donna, or first lady.
Maybe first temperamental lady.
Anyway, let's get to the signing.
Again, here the orchestra just
plays a few chords as arpeggios and
then gets out of the way.
In this classic example
of bel canto signing,
you'll hear the late Australian
soprano Joan Sutherland.
She's the diva here.
[MUSIC]
>> So
that was the soprano singing bel canto.
But there are various kinds of
sopranos as this next slide suggests.
There is the coloratura,
a high, light, agile voice.
There are also three other
types of sopranos, first lyric.
We usually associate that
with bel conto singing.
Perhaps the best known of these
lyric sopranos is Renee Fleming,
with her incomparable vocal control.
Then there's a type of voice that
pushes itself just a bit toward
the dramatic side,
called spina vocce, lyrica spinta.
And then the dramatic soprano,
that's called for
most obviously when
a huge sound is needed.
For example, to sail above the large
orchestra in the operas of Wagner.
Then of course, there's the slightly
lower soprano called the mezzo.
Mezzo, halfway.
Halfway between soprano and alto.
And then the low alto,
which in opera is called the contralto.
As to the men, well of course,
we have the tenor.
In the 19th century, around 1830 or
so, the tenor voice finally and
definitively replaced
the castrato as the male lead.
So the hero, henceforth in opera is the
tenor, with there being lyrical tenors and
the more dramatic ones,
again for Wagnerian operas.
Between tenor and bass,
we have the baritone or varitones,
variable voice because it could swing
between low tenor and high bass.
And, finally, bass itself.
What makes a great singer?
Well, natural gift, good training,
and of course hard work.
As to natural gift, we might take a look
at this image of Joan Sutherland who for
my money was the greatest
soprano that I ever heard.
She can do it all, from contralto to
coloratura and with a huge volume.
But she did have perhaps
a somewhat unusual physiogonmy.
An elongated head in a body
standing 6'3 tall was her stature,
in some way a reflection of
her exceptional vocal chords.
By way of comparison,
the body of seven time gold medal winning
swimmer Michael Phelps, who's said to
have the body of a shark, small waist,
huge shoulders,
a perfect swimming machine.
But maybe I'm getting in over
my head here so let's move on.