[MUSIC]
Well as we saw in an earlier segment,
judging from the number of operas
performed at a typical, large opera house,
the reigning king of opera Giuseppe Verdi.
He gets more performances
than anyone else.
More than Mozart.
More than Wagner.
Why are Verdi's operas so popular?
In a word, they're never bored.
That's the key to a success
as a dramaturgist,
as someone crafting great theater,
making drama work in a theater.
As Verdi, himself, said,
quote, there's only
one thing that the public won't tolerate
in the theater, and that's boredom.
End quote.
Verdi avoids boredom by means of action
filled librettos, lots of romance,
lots of intrigue, and murders galore.
And as you can see by the slide here,
three of his librettos are based on
action packed plays of Shakespeare,
two involving murders.
Macbeth and Othello.
And Verdi's music too, is action packed,
but what does that mean?
Action packed music.
In what way can music be action packed?
Well, with Verdi it's condensed.
A lot happens in Verdi's music
in a brief amount of time.
And as in Beethoven's music,
there's never any ambiguity as to how
we're supposed to feel about the music.
Now Verdi wants us to feel this sensation.
Now that sensation.
Now this emotion.
Now that emotion.
Emotions are obvious and
they come quickly one after another.
So, Verdi's operas rarely
are enormously subtle.
You want really subtle things
in opera go listen to Mozart.
Go listen to the Marriage of Figaro,
for example.
But if you want banner
headlines of emotion, well.
Verdi is your go to person.
To see how this works, let's listen,
not to an aria as you might expect, but
to an overture by Verdi that's just
purely instrumental, instrumental music.
The overture is short,
it lasts only two minutes.
Which tells us a lot about various
capacity for dramatic compression.
How he can pack in many
contrasting emotions within just
a short period of time.
The piece in question is
the overture to his opera, MacBeth.
Let's give a listen as Ricardo Muti
conducts, and I'll comment as we go.
[MUSIC]
Here begin with music that
sounds somewhat non-committal.
Maybe a lot of movement onstage.
But then, oh.
You know this is not going to end well.
Notice those low brass.
Trombones to the right, tuba.
[MUSIC]
Ooh.
A little suspense building up.
[MUSIC]
Aha, low trombones again,
probably coming up here in seventh
cord falling melodic sequence.
[MUSIC]
But that idea doesn't last for long.
Dominant chord and tonic resolve.
The lovely lyrical flowing.
[MUSIC]
It could well be sung,
it's about conto aria.
[MUSIC]
And that too, doesn't last too long,
as we slide away to more diminished and
minor chords.
[MUSIC]
Tension builds, rising melodic sequence.
Whoops, no this is falling.
[MUSIC]
Another hold cadence.
There's that lovely melody, back.
[MUSIC]
A very simple accompaniment
underneath that melody.
Again, typical of bel canto.
And you can begin to hear a fade out.
[MUSIC]
Rising, minor trial, withholds and
then intensity grows.
Compression, intensity,
maximum drama in minimum time.
Sometimes maybe even
really obvious emotions.
And it's never dull, and it's often very
beautiful, and surely this in many ways
accounts for various great popularity
with opera goers around the world.
Tip five.
By his, perhaps,
most popular opera, La Traveata.