[MUSIC]
Well, if you have to choose just one
among Verdi's many successful operas,
which do you choose?
Which will most quickly give you
a sense of what Verdi's all about?
Well I'd recommend La Traviata.
It's about love.
It's about disappointment in love.
And it's about death.
So there are plenty of
emotions to go around here.
And there is also a lot of very exciting
and a lot of very beautiful music.
Now of course in five minutes we
can't go through an entire two and
a half hour opera.
So here's what I suggest.
Here you might take advantage
of the recommended textbook,
The Essential Listening to Music,
where I lead you through the entire opera.
But you could also watch
the opera on YouTube.
But let's push on.
The title, La traviata, in Italian
means the woman who has gone astray.
La, the feminine article
on the other side of
tra via, the road,
the wrong side of the tracks if you will.
And here, to the left, we see that woman.
Verdi's libretto is based on a true
life story of the relationship between
Marie Duplessis and the raider, Alexandra
Dumas, the younger, on the right.
His father wrote The Three Musketeers, and
the Count of Monte Christo, among others.
Dumas the younger turned this
true life story into a play, and
Verdi based his opera on the play.
The play was also turned into a ballet,
with music by Chopin.
And into a film in the 1930s
with the glamorous Greta Garbo.
Marie Duplessis was a social phenomenon.
She was a courtesan, in a word, a high
class prostitute, a high class hooker.
She had many lovers including pianist
Franz Liszt, but she died young
at the age of 23 of tuberculosis, the same
disease that claimed the life of Chopin.
Marie's short, scandalous, sensational
life was well known in the day,
as you can see by the comment upon her
death by none other than Charles Dickens,
who compared her notoriety to
that of the famous Joan of Arc.
Okay, let's meet
the characters in our opera.
Here we have the representation
on stage of Marie Duplessis,
Violetta, she's the heroine, the soprano.
Her lover of course,
the hero is Alfredo, a tenor.
Alfredo's father well that's Germont,
an authority figure who
attempts to place discord between the two.
And here, finally, the villain of the
opera who is sometimes Alfredo's lover and
protector Baron Douphol,
bass baritone voice.
In terms of action, well in the first
act they meet, they fall in love, but
she vows at the end of it to remain free.
In the second act they live
together happily for a while,
but his father drives them apart.
Third act, she returns to Baron Douphol.
Alfredo fights a duel with him and
is banished to Italy.
Violetta is dying of
tuberculosis back in Paris,
Alfredo races back to rejoin her,
but it's too late.
Once again,
we have this convention of the heroine
dying at the end of a romantic opera.
She sings her last and then dies.
Violetta, Tosca, Mimi, Isolde, Carmen,
as we'll see later in our session today,
even Brunhilde.
The romantic convention of long
love gone tragically awry.
All right,
well let's listen to some of the music.
We'll start with the first
act here where the hero,
Alfredo, first professes his love for
Violetta.
He does so in an aria.
Well, actually it's a duet,
which Violetta joins in on.
Alfredo's aria begins low and slow,
sometimes with a minor twinge to it.
Love is serious.
And notice the simple oom
pah pah accompaniment.
The orchestra again provides only
the simplest sort of accompaniment
to the tenor, in this case,
tenor bel canto voice.
Let me play just a bit for you,
of the accompaniment on the piano.
It is indeed very simple.
It starts here.
[MUSIC]
Couldn't be simpler.
>> Okay, we'll just pause it here.
Notice in this opening passage that we're
coming along in a slow triple, one, two,
three, one, two, three, and how the singer
and conductor slowed way, way down there.
Well this is called tempo rubato.
Slow way down so that the singer here,
Luciano Pavarotti,
could luxuriate in that
slide from the leading
tone up into the tonic
[SOUND] in that fashion.
Let's listen to this one more time, and
we'll focus on the rise of the leading
tone into the tonic and the tempo rubato.
[MUSIC]
>> A great example of the flexibility
of tempo in the romantic period and
a leading tone pulling into the tonic,
and a great sound, of course,
Pavarotti has the voice to
make this all his work.
When Violetta entered,
she brightens things up.
She sings higher,
lighter, always in major.
Soon the voices join rapturously,
the musical intervals embracing
sweet sounds, the thirds and sixths.
And as you listen, notice the role of
the orchestra, as the duet proceeds.
Here's a question for you.
What does the orchestra
do here at the climax?
[MUSIC]
>> Okay, now we're coming to
the top of the page here.
[MUSIC]
>> Now they're about to go off, jump off.
Well, what did the orchestra
do at the climax?
Absolutely nothing.
It stopped playing entirely.
Only at the end, the second blue arrow,
does the orchestra return
with a few tonic chords.
And again, note that Alfredo and
Violetta have the same rhythms here.
They're very much in sync.
They're very much together,
sweetly in love.
They are sweet on one another,
in sweet sounding thirds and sixths.
So here we are.
Let me see if I can dig this out.
[MUSIC]
Thirds and sixths.
There is six two third.
And then the orchestra
comes back in simply.
[MUSIC]
Well as we proceed to the end of this
first act we see that Violetta is
ambivalent about love.
Maybe she'd rather be by herself, be
better off without any serious commitment,
be better off just enjoying life and
all it's earthly pleasures.
Violetta tells us all this in a package
of musical items called a scena.
Now a scena, of course, is simply
the Italian for the idea of a scene,
a coherent sequence of
aria recitative aria.
We'll start with the recitative.
And note that now,
unlike the unaccompanied recitative
just harpsichord or early piano,
only as we had with Mozart.
Now, recitative is accompanied by
a large portion of the orchestra.
Now we have [FOREIGN] accompanied
recitative, of course.
The recitative is followed
by what we call a cabaletta.
A fast, concluding aria that allows the
signer to declaim something emphatically,
in this case I will always remain free,
and then
dramatically exit the stage as the curtain
falls to end the scene and the act.
Here's Violetta's Recitative.
We will follow along
with the English text.
[MUSIC]
>> We are at the top of the page.
>> And now the orchestra starts
out with the aria, the cabaletta.
And it suddenly will break off and
then recommence.
[MUSIC]
>> Watch how sensual,
the dive way down in this difficult aria.
[MUSIC]
>> Low point.
And immediately soar up high.
High up into the sky with happy.
[MUSIC]
>> And she just repeats these words here.
Soaring spirits.
Soon Alfredo could be heard from outside
the window outside reminding her.
>> [FOREIGN]
>> Now his music.
And seriously minor,
when the mystery of love.
[MUSIC]
A little dissonance here, hm,
pain yet delight to the heart.
[MUSIC]
But, Violetta brushes off
the thought of true love, and
after another vocal flourish, she begins.
[MUSIC]
Repeat the cabaletta.
Okay let's pause it there.
So here we begin to hear a scena,
repeat of the cabaletta
with the vocal part growing
ever more dramatic and
ever more virtuosic,
especially at the end.
Let's take a look at the end,
and we'll see what goes on.
Okay, let's look at this slide here.
I'll put on my glasses, and
we'll see if we can't find this page.
Aha, I know we've got it here somewhere.
So this is the very last page
of the first act of La Traviata.
The soprano,
well it's actually interesting to look at,
Verdi has written this two ways.
As you can see the cursor up on top here,
one option is for just to have the singer,
maybe a non-adventurous singer,
to come down and just rest here.
A very high range singer,
one with a high vocal capacity,
could go all the way up and execute
the syncopations on that super high C
up there, and
then gradually make her way down, and
then back up through a melodic sequence,
or repetition through here.
Until we come to this spot.
So let me play just a little bit for you.
And I think I'll be starting about here,
focusing just on the melody.
[MUSIC]
Okay, that's what Verdi wrote.
Now oftentimes in modern performances,
the soprano will be a bit more aggressive.
So the soprano will be
coming up to this high note.
[MUSIC]
Go up there, to the A up above.
But in this recording,
watch what Joan Sutherland does.
It's really extraordinary.
She's coming along in this fashion.
[MUSIC]
And then does this.
Jumps all the way up to that
super high E-flat and nobody did,
Verdi didn't write at all.
[MUSIC]
And then brings it back to the tonic,
in that fashion, high down there.
So listen to this performance
by Joan Sutherland.
[MUSIC]
>> Wow, that's really sort of
virtuosic fireworks there.
Notice that it required her really to
add four or five additional bars, so
that you get up there and sit and
really exploit that super high note.
Well, that's the end of just
the first act of Verdi's La Traviata.
I hope you'll go on to explore
the remainder of the opera on your own.
But, a final thought.
We've talked a lot about
the female soprano voice here.
And what about the tenor voice?
Almost every great operatic tenor
has had a go at singing this role.
This role of Alfredo,
ever since Verdi created it.
Here's another cabaletta,
this one from act two of La Traviata,
in which Alfredo vows to avenge
the dishonor that's been heaped upon him.
He will wash it away, the disgrace.
And, for fun, let's hear three
performances of just a snippet of
this aria, this cabaletta,
and you compare them.
You get to be the judge,
you get to be critic.
So, what are we gonna listen for here?
Well, as you can see, we wanna listen for,
among other things but
not necessarily all in each recording.
Quality of richness,
quality of the variation of the tone,
the comfort level,
does the voice sound strained?
Capacity to control the tone,
capacity to hold pitches.
Especially the climactic and very high
final pitch, it's actually a high C.
And the end, it's very important here,
as we'll see, and finally, the overall
tempo of the performance, often
the greater the vocal control, and vocal
control is a virtue here, the greater
the vocal control, the slower the tempo.
So a slow tempo will suggest that this
singer has greater vocal command.
So we're going to begin here
with a comparison of our tenors.
First we'll hear the great
Spanish Mexican tenor Placido Domingo,
a skilled singer and
highly intelligent musician conductor.
Both of these recordings,
by the way were studio recordings.
The first Domingo 1977,
the second of Pavarotti in 1979.
Let's begin with Placido Domingo
singing Dei miei bollenti spiriti.
[MUSIC]
>> Okay, so that's one presentation of it.
Now a second, again, Luciano Pavarotti,
1979, same material.
[MUSIC]
>> And finally now
the Hungarian Tenor Peter Kevol.
Notice what he does in particular,
notice what he does with the final pitch,
that difficult to get high C
that's been a challenge to every
tenor who has attempted this role.
[MUSIC]
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Well what did you think?
Take a quick quiz on the performance of
these three singers and then if you wish,
a second quiz that reinforces some of the
vocabulary that we have been employing.