[MUSIC]
So here we are.
We've got about 20 minutes to
talk about Richard Wagner.
This is a travesty.
Wagner is a huge subject.
Which composer has more books written
about him, Bach, Mozart, Verdi, or Wagner?
Well, Wagner.
Which composer changed the face
of 19th century music the most?
Well, a toss up here.
Certainly Beethoven, or perhaps Wagner.
Which composer it was.
The most original thinker and
creator in the entire history
of western musical theater.
Well arguably again Richard Wagner, but
although our time is short, let's get
going and lets make the most of it.
Wagner was born here Leipzig Germany in
1813 the same years as Giuseppe Verdi.
And Wagner received a bit of musical
training here at this church.
In this church music school on right,
at the St.
Thomas Church & church music school.
Who else worked here in this church?
And who lived in this house?
Well, J.S. Bach of course, for 27 years.
But Wagner got only the smallest
sort of musical education here.
So in many ways, Wagner was an outlier.
Wagner exposure to music
was very different.
Unlike that of Bach,
Mozart, and Beethoven,
who you see on the left, think about
the upbringing of Wagner compared to them.
Bach, Mozart, Beethoven, well they
all came from a family of musicians.
They all had a father in the business.
Wagner was never sure who his father was,
and
he was essentially self-taught in music.
He was both pupil and teacher to himself.
To earn his daily bread,
young Wagner worked in theatres,
as a conductor, composing on the side.
For awhile, he nearly starved to death,
and in fact,
was thrown in debtor's prison in Paris.
But then his big break came.
It happened back here in Dresden,
as you can see by the red arrow.
When he was offered, and accepted,
the prestigious post of composer and
conductor here,
at the Semper Opera House in Dresden,
Germany, here, as we see it restored
after the second World War.
But with the Revolution of 1848,
Wagner became
a persona non grata in Germany and
fled to independent Switzerland.
And for the rest of his life he seems to
have lived off of other people's money.
Off of the largess of one patron or
another.
Here's the living room of his
house in Tribschen that he enjoyed
rent free, and
here's Wagner's living room.
Not so bad for a man with little or
no income, artist or con artist?
Well a little of both,
maybe a lot of both.
And here's the grand piano
that was provided for him.
Provided by his most generous patron,
King Ludwig of Bavaria.
Mad King Ludwig as he was known.
He was the builder of the fantasy
castle Neuschwanstein.
Eventually King Ludwig
also supplied Wagner with
the money to build his own
theater in Bavaria in Bayreuth.
The Bayreuth Festival Hall,
where Wagner could produce his operas and
only his operas.
Or what Wagner came to
call his music dramas.
So here's an image, a slide,
a photograph actually
of what Bayreuth looked like as
the theater was being built.
And here's what it looked like
when it was finished in 1876.
Now, this is a fascinating image.
It's a bit of mythmaking and
a bit of marketing, a promotion for
a meat extract, a vitamin.
And with this product,
each buyer received the free card.
It was much like American baseball cards
today or prizes in boxes of cereal.
On this card, we see an important moment.
Not only the dedication
of the new theater, but
the presence of the new ruler,
Kaiser Wilhelm I.
Well, he's ruling
the newly unified Germany.
Wagner is on the ascent, and, the German
nation is on the ascent as well.
Look at how much bigger Wagner has
gotten on the left of our picture,
to the right there of Wagner is the,
let me see if I can identify it here.
Here's Franz Liszt.
Short, white haired Franz Liszt.
Here's Richard Wagner, and point of fact,
Wagner is only three years younger than
Liszt and actually [LAUGH] much
shorter than Liszt, almost as a joke.
Let's take a look at this next
image where we see the two of them
standing next to a set
chair in similar positions.
But in this image,
we see see the young looking Wagner, well,
he's almost the equal in stature and
he's certainly taller than Liszt.
Equal to stature to the Kaiser.
So, history here is being re-written.
Art in the service of politics.
The image is making a cultural
statement about what
Germany thought it was at this time.
Germany loomed large and
Wagner loomed large.
And here's the way Bayreuth looks today,
very much a center of German culture.
Let's go inside.
Inside we see an exceedingly
plain auditorium.
Why so?
Well, Wagner was something
of an egomaniac and
he didn't want the audience to focus on
anything other than the music and drama.
His music and drama.
But Wagner was an innovator.
His theater was the first not to admit
late comers once the act had begun.
His theater was the first to use
gas lighting instead of candles and
this allowed for the dimming of
the lights during the performance.
And Wagner was also the first to put
the orchestra completely under the stage,
in what's called the orchestral pit.
So let's slide here left to right,
down into the pit over here.
The audience would hear the music,
but not see the players.
Hear Wagner's music, but
not see who was producing it.
Well, what music did Wagner introduce to
the listening public at the inauguration
of his impressive new theater?
Well, he introduced his Ring Cycle,
which we'll now explore.