[MUSIC]
As we have seen,
the era in which Richard Wagner grew up,
in the 19th century,
was a profoundly literary period.
But while Berlioz and
Beethoven was reading Shakespeare,
Wagner was reading Nordic mythology.
Specifically he began to
read Das Niebelungenlied,
the Song of the Nibelungs.
A medieval legend that had been edited and
published in Modern German in the 1820's.
Here is one of the original manuscripts.
One from the early 13th century surviving
in a monastic library in Saint Gallen,
Switzerland.
And at that very moment that Wagner
was carried away with this fantasy,
this fantasy Nordic literature,
other Nordic literature was being
rediscovered and published.
The Anglo Saxton Beowulf in
the Finnish Kalevala, for example.
Wagner took the story of this legend,
the story of the Nibelungs and
began to craft a libretto for an opera.
Wagner's the only major composer
to have written his own librettos.
So he wrote a libretto, but
then he found he needed to say more.
He needed more explanation, so
he wrote another libretto, a prequel.
And then a prequel to that prequel, and
then another until he had four librettos,
a tetralogy which came to
be called The Ring Cycle.
Here are the four operas
of the Ring Cycle.
Why is it called the Ring Cycle?
Because the story of the Nibelung
turns on the creation, the magic ring,
the possession of which gives
its owner power over the world.
If this all sounds familiar, it is.
What we've got here is the beginning
of popular, Nordic fantasy literature.
First in English translations
of the Song of the Nidelungs,
and then in fantasy, elaborations,
as created by J.R.R.
Tolkien, The Lord of the Ring,
CL Lewis, Chronicle of Narnia and
more distantly, George Lucas's Star Wars,
George Martin's Game of Thrones.
Wagner started it all.
What's the plot of Wagner's Ring cycle?
Well, it's complicated.
With Wagner, every thing is
kind of long and complicated.
But to pare this down to 25 words or
less if you will,
there's a chief god, Wotan,
who sees the power-laden ring, and
for a moment he controls the world.
He's fathered many children
with many different wives,
including his favorite his daughter,
the rebellious Brunhilde.
Events require Wotan to punish Brunhilde.
Her punishment is to be
quarantined in a ring of fire.
A ring of fire that only a super hero,
named Siegfried,
only a super hero can penetrate.
Siegfried does this and then he and
Brunhilde go on to further adventures and
conflicts.
In the end, he's killed by treachery,
and she rides into emulate
herself in a ring of fire,
a final configuration.
Another instance of a heroine
dying at the end of an opera.
And in this fiery conclusion
the entire world of Wotan and
the gods goes up and down in flames.
To make sense of,
to pull of this together,
nearly 17 hours of Opera,
Wagner employed a new technique.
One using what contemporaries call
light motifs, signature motifs.
Musical tags or musical identifiers.
Light motifs are leading motives that
lead the listener through the opera.
Let's listen to a couple of
the many dozens of light motifs
Wagner employs in the ring cycle.
Here are just four,
starting at the beginning,
with the motive representing
the ever flowing Rhine River.
[MUSIC]
Now the motive for the Rhine maidens,
those sub fluvial women who swim beneath
the river Rhine and sing of gold.
[MUSIC]
And now the motive with a curse
associated with the ring.
[MUSIC]
And finally,
the motive signaling Valhalla,
that magnificent fortress
home of the gods,
that Wotan has built for
his extended family, and other gods.
[MUSIC]
That's the most sonorous
of the motives and
it's always the job of
the brasses to play it.
Okay, a couple further points, usually
Wagner's light motives are assigned not
to the singers, but to the orchestra.
Wotan or
Sigfried mentions a sword on stage,
the sword motive will
mention in the orchestra.
Even if the character says nothing,
the orchestra can still tell us what he or
she is thinking by playing
a light motif in the background.
So Wagner's music can even
penetrate to the subconscious
by means of the unseen
orchestra beneath the stage.
Even before the character is aware of it,
we know what he or she is thinking.
Finally, Wagner's notion
of what we call an opera,
well it's not what we usually
think of opera as being.
And he didn't like the term, Opera, so
he called his creations Music Dramas.
And the structure of the melody of his
music dramas is very different from that
of Italian opera in which is
entirely separately from aria and
that gives us this format
that's called a numbers opera.
Well, Wagner wasn't in
favor of the numbers opera.
He, on the other hand,
wanted Melody that unfolds continually.
He called this Endless Melody.
But in truth, it's as much song
declamation as it is melody.
Most of the melody and
the dramatic high points of the music
drama, are presented by the orchestra.
The orchestra is hugely important
in Wagner's music dramas,
much more so than in various operas.
But none of this will make much sense
until we've actually heard much more of
the music.