[MUSIC]
We're here today by way of Wagner's music,
is indeed only a teaser.
Only the smallest sample
of his great music.
But I would like to share
with you a bit of video
that my colleague Steve Malinowski and
I, mostly Steve if truth be told,
have created for
Wagner's famous Ride of the Valkyrie.
This is an overture to
the final act of the second
music drama of the Ring Cycle,
Die Walkure.
Here the women warriors,
the Valkyries, ride up from
a battlefield toward Valhalla carrying
the bodies of fallen heroes in battle.
This is the music, in instrumental form,
that precedes the next
scene that we'll see.
This is the music that opens the third and
final act of Die Walkure.
You'll recognize this music and
I'll comment as we go.
We start out here in trills,
[MUSIC]
You see woodwinds
And each time a new one enters,
it's up or down an up or down an octave.
A rhythmic mobic is now started out.
[MUSIC]
Now, of course, the theme
Minor
[MUSIC]
Transition to major.
More low brass enters.
More trombone and
tuba as the texture builds.
[MUSIC]
Now this part, Wagner's original,
he wrote this as
an instrumental [INAUDIBLE].
[INAUDIBLE] been some,
Valkyries with their cries up above.
Here they are, swinging through
the air on Wagner's stage and
singing cries to one another.
[MUSIC]
Once again the theme comes back,
a light motif.
[MUSIC]
With the brass reappearing in there.
He'd hold the tubas there,
we worked to that climax and
we're going to fade it out here.
We're actually half way through
this exciting, driving overture.
But let's move on.
Eventually Valkyrie Brunhilde
meets up with her father, Wotan.
He must punish her for suborning incest.
We needn't go in to the specifics of that.
To inflict the punishment as said,
Wotan will surround Brunhilde
with a ring of fire.
Wotan knows that he is sacrificing.
We'll never see again his beloved child,
his most favored of all children.
But the social order of the world,
Wotan's world, requires that this be so.
As we've seen, everything with Wagner is
complicated, so I've tried to simplify and
explain this climactic scene as we
view it in a production from
the Metropolitan Opera performance.
I tried to provide a guide here
with a synopsis of the drama.
And I'm shortening the text admittedly.
And I tried to provide
an identification of the light motifs
as we proceed through this.
Here as we see Wotan say
goodbye to Brunhilde,
here in Wotan's farewell.
[MUSIC]
[FOREIGN]
Then gradually diminishes,
rises by a pitch, and continues.
Well, that's extraordinary,
that's extraordinary.
What Wagner had really foreseen here,
I believe, is what we would call today,
an IMAX theater.
Sitting in a darkness
with an unseen orchestra,
completely surrounded by sound and
completely enveloped in the drama
that's unfolding before us.
As I say, as the most original,
most transformative force in the history
of Western theatre,
it's difficult to deny Richard Wagner.