[MUSIC]
Let's begin our session on the romantic
orchestra with a quick review quiz.
I'd like to play two pieces for you,
have you listen and tell me which is from
the 18th century, the classical period,
and which from the 19th, the romantic era.
Most important,
let's think about what it is that you
hear that leads you to this conclusion.
Let's hear the first clip.
[MUSIC]
Okay, and now the second clip.
All right, I hope you agree that the first
is from the classical period, and
the second from the romantic period.
A symphony of Mozart,
the Linz Symphony, and
an overture by Richard Wagner,
Overture to the Flying Dutchman.
Let's dig down a little bit deeper
here and pursue the classical model.
You can just read my evaluation
of the music as it plays.
[MUSIC]
All right, and now the romantic
paradigm with a famous passage from
Tchaikovsky's Romeo and Juliet.
And again, you'll see my synopsis.
[MUSIC]
Let's compare now the size of
the orchestras that created this music.
In the Mozart classical orchestra,
there were roughly 30 to 35 players,
as you can see here.
To the left, we have first violin,
second violins on the right,
some violas here, three cellos,
two double basses and pairs of woodwinds.
No trombones, for example.
Slight on the brasses, and
this was a rather large
orchestra by Mozart's standards.
Okay, here's the seating chart that
might typify the orchestra for
the Tchaikovsky that we just heard.
Many more brasses and woodwinds, and
to balance them, more strings are needed.
And down at the bottom, of course,
you can see this person, the conductor.
When did we get a conductor for
the western symphony orchestra?
Was it with Mozart?
So here we have Mozart, or
the actor playing Mozart,
conducting in the remarkable film Amadeus.
But the scene, while dramatic,
is not historically correct.
Mozart conducted seated at a keyboard
instrument, usually the early piano forte.
So when did conductors start to
stand up and wave their arms around?
Well, oddly enough in the mid-19th
century, the same time that urban centers,
especially London, got crowded
with vehicles on the street and
a traffic cop appeared,
waving a stick or a lantern at night.
Here are silhouettes of one of
the first standing conductors,
the composer conductor Carl Maria von
Weber, a distant relative of Mozart.
Here's Liszt conducting a large orchestra
in Budapest late in his career.
Liszt directs all, a God-like figure.
And here are two silhouettes of
Wagner conducting in his late career.
Maybe the most remarkable
image of this sort however,
is a concert in Covent Garden.
In the center of London,
1846, published that year,
this engraving, published that
year in the London Daily Mail.
You see the conductor.
See if I can point to the conductor.
There he is standing in the middle
of a massive orchestra.
The strings are to the front of him.
The woodwinds are in risers
up to the back here.
And then further back,
we have the percussion tympani, and
then even more tympani and brasses, and
that gigantic bass drum all the way at the
back, as you can see up here at the top.
So the 19th century orchestra was getting
larger and larger, and louder and louder.
Think about it for a moment.
What was the largest man-made
sound that a citizen of the 19th
century would've experienced before
the electronic amplification of sound?
Only two things were louder than
the full symphony orchestra,
the steam engine and the cannon.
The symphony orchestra was next in line,
however, in volume.
The notion of the fire power
of the 19th century orchestra was not
lost on the listeners of the day.
As we see in this 19th
century satirical drawing,
this cartoon of Hector Berlioz
conducting the firing of the brasses.
[MUSIC]
Pretty impressive.
Within a mere 40 years,
from Mozart to Berlioz,
the sound of the orchestra
had increased enormously.
What was driving this change?
What has driven every important change
in the west in the last 300 years?
Technology.