[MUSIC]
When we enjoyed the music of Beethoven,
specifically his Symphony No 5,
and the music of Berlioz, specially,
his Symphonie fantastique,
we saw how these innovative
creators increased the size and
the color of the symphony orchestra.
Here's a review question.
What three new instruments did Beethoven
bring into the symphony orchestra?
Put your thinking caps on now.
Good.
Contrabassoon, trombone, and piccolo.
And what about Berlioz?
What instruments did he introduce?
Good again.
Tuba, harp and cornet.
And the English horn, well,
we'll get to that in just a moment.
As you can see by this
comparison of instruments,
from the 18th century on the left, and
those of the 19th century on the right,
we see how technology
improved the flexibility.
Well, they could play
more pitches in tune.
And their facility,
they could play the pitches a lot faster
because of the introduction of valves and
new keypad extenders, here for the flute,
the french horn, and the trumpet.
Indeed, up to this time,
the horn was just called corno, horn.
Now it's called the french horn
because it has these fancy new valves.
Now here's a fascinating image: a factory
with assembly line production
during the Industrial Revolution.
And it's huge.
It was the factory of
Adolphe Sax in Paris.
He, of course,
was the inventor of the saxophone.
Notice [LAUGH] first the production
assembly line with the smallest parts
being assembled on the left and gradually
the instruments would be assembled and
grow in size as we move
around to the right.
Notice in his shop,
these manufacturing saxophones of course.
We see a giant one
hanging from the ceiling,
the roof there, at the arrow on the top.
But also,
he was manufacturing trumpets and tubas.
Notice the tubas are visible
at two lower arrows there.
They really do look like, if you look
closely, they really do look like cannons.
And here we see these low brasses as they
look today in a recording studio session.
Note especially the trombones and
the tubas.
[MUSIC]
And Hector Berlioz added one other
instrument to the orchestra, and
that was the English horn.
Ironically, of course,
the English horn is neither a horn, it's
not a brass instrument, nor is it English.
It's a woodwind instrument,
a low oboe of French origin.
But it does have a particular
sound that we think of as being,
well maybe perhaps mournful, or
melancholy, or even nostalgic.
Let's listen to what might seem to
be the melancholy, or nostalgic
quality of the English horn with an image
of the American Midwest in the background.
The composer, Dvorak,
wrote some of this symphony while residing
in the Midwestern state of Iowa,
in Spillville, Iowa to be precise.
[MUSIC]
And while all of these woodwinds and
brasses were being added to the orchestra,
to balance them more strings were needed,
and a bigger string sound.
The string instruments themselves,
they didn't get bigger, but
how they were constructed did change.
Let's look at the slide of a violin here.
First of all, notice with the Baroque
violin that the finger board on the left
is on the same plane, same flat plane,
as the body of the instrument.
But on the top, with the modern violin,
the fingerboard is at an angle.
And that requires a higher bridge
which lifts the strings away from
the instrument, allowing the player
to dig in more with the bow.
And then, there's the bow itself,
it's gotten larger in the 19th century.
And the horse hair would make up
the sounding part of the bow, well,
that has gotten wider and
the steel rod is placed inside,
that makes it possible to tighten the bow
and increase pressure on the strings.
And the strings of the instrument
were now uniformly made of wire,
no longer animal gut, gut of sheep,
or animal gut of cat, cat gut.
That's why kitty is smiling
here at these new, or
newly reconstructed instruments that
allow for more power and color.
All right, with the newly enlarged
orchestra in place let's see how,
as the orchestra got bigger,
musical time slowed down.