[MUSIC]
As you might suspect,
with the orchestra growing ever larger,
producing an ever larger sound,
concert halls got larger as well.
And they changed in function,
or in purpose too.
Here again we go back to Vienna and
Beethoven's day.
The Theater an der Wien,
where Beethoven premiered his famous
Symphony Number Five in 1808.
This image dates from only
about two years later.
Here we can see draped
in red bunting here,
the imperial box with
a double headed eagle.
Down here to the left, up next to the
stage is the orchestra with the musicians
and on the stage here to the bottom
lower left what do we see?
Horses!
This was a civic auditorium,
an entertainment center,
almost as in a Las Vegas auditorium or
Radio City Music Hall in New York.
But after Beethoven's death,
two things happened.
First, some of Beethoven's admirers in
Vienna built a music only concert hall,
the beautiful Music Society Hall,
the Musikverein, as it's called in Vienna.
Here, just music.
No circus acts.
On this stage, Johannes Brahms conducted.
So too, did Gustav Mahler,
whose music we'll hear shortly.
And 2, and this is the second point,
sudden hush came over the concert hall and
it's listeners.
The idea of a quiet,
quiet only concert hall enters now.
Music was no longer thought
of to be entertainment, but
it had become in the romantic era,
high art.
Art that was to be heard
in reverential silence.
And this new temple to the God of
Music came to be replicated elsewhere.
First in Liepzig, Germany and
then in the United States.
Now admittedly Carnegie Hall in New York,
that's the first great
American concert hall.
And it was a little bit different.
It does have a circular model.
But, the symphony hall in Boston is almost
an exact reproduction of the Musikverein.
As you see here in this sort of
shoebox effect is drawn again
from the Musikverein.
And here let's go to Woolsey Hall,
At Yale University in New Haven,
again, this sort of shoe box design.
It has many similarities with
the Musikverein in Vienna.
And even in modern times the Vienna
prototype has been adopted,
Avery Fisher Hall in New York and
most recently at the Schermerhorn
Symphony Hall in Nashville.
So, this is the Schermerhorn Symphony Hall
in Nashville.
But it all started in Vienna,
with the Musikverein.
With sounds, such as those produced by,
as you will hear here,
symphonic composer Jean Sibelius.
Great music and great acoustics for music.
[MUSIC]
So these ever larger concert halls for
music only, of the late 19th and early
20th centuries, well they were not only
visually stunning, but acoustical marvels.
And in many ways, they were the finest
concert halls for music ever created,
home to the largest symphony
orchestras ever created.