[MUSIC]
The music we just heard
on the opening slide
is a little more music
than we usually hear.
It's some of the beautiful adagietto
of Gustav Mahler's Symphony Number 5.
And Mahler conducted, as we mentioned, on
the stage of the Music Variety in Vienna.
He conducted the Vienna Philharmonic
from 1898 until 1907 and
then he came to New York.
So although Mahler,
like his contemporary, Sigmund Freud,
was born in the Czech Republic,
he made the core of his career in Vienna.
Mahler was both a conductor and
a composer.
He conducted during the winter months and
he composed during the summers.
Most of what he composed
falls into two categories.
First, songs accompanied by an orchestra,
a genre that we call the orchestral lead.
And then, symphonies,
nine complete symphonies in all.
But unique to Mahler was his
urge to incorporate songs or
music from songs into his symphonic works.
As you can see, in all but
two of his symphonies,
previously composed vocal
music played a role.
Let's see what some of these
symphonies sound like, let's take for
example the end of
Mahler's first symphony.
Which shows us again the extent of
the power of the late romantic symphony
orchestra.
The conductor here is the young
Venezuelan Gustavo Dudamel leading
the Los Angeles Philharmonic.
What do you think of his
style of conducting here?
Do you like it or not?
I'll comment about the performance as
we go though the music pretty much says
it all.
[MUSIC]
Rising motif, then the trumpets.
Mostly by step.
[MUSIC]
Standing motif, mostly by step.
Tremolo, you saw there in the screen.
[MUSIC]
Descending motif using
interval of a fourth.
[MUSIC]
A little bit of literally grand standing
on the part of the French hornsmen.
The accompaniment,
looks like at least six people.
[MUSIC]
The tempo rubato as it flows down.
Drums going down,
[INAUDIBLE] motifs going up.
[MUSIC]
Notice he's conducting without a score.
Notice also we have two tympany here.
Horn, the semi-motif, now the ascending
motif will come in with it, counterpoint.
Double counterpoint.
[MUSIC]
This is the half step slide.
And this is all, [INAUDIBLE].
[MUSIC]
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Okay, well obviously,
we've come a long way
since the sound of Mozart.
In less than a century and
it's the orchestra that's carrying
the day here in Mahler's Symphony.
And what did you think of the conductor,
Dudamel?
Do you feel that a conductor in moving
can help the listener, can help us?
Enjoy the piece more,
get into the piece more, or
do you find that kind of
conducting to be a distraction?
I like that approach.
It's more likely to get you,
the audience and me, energized and
emotionally engaged with the performance.
If you like that Mahler and
wanna hear more, here's a suggestion.
For the listener, Gustav Mahler is
often a challenging composer and
his symphonies are long.
And sometimes diffuse,
something of a labyrinth.
But there's a logical path
through this labyrinth of Mahler.
If you start with the more
easily accessible symphonies and
move out from there.
Here's what I'd recommend,
a path to follow.
I'd start, well, with Symphony Number 1.
The Titan as it's called and
we heard a bit of the end of that.
Then I'd go onto Symphony number four,
particularly the fourth movement there,
the finale that has some beautiful vocal
music sung by a soprano as part of it.
Then I'd go on to what we heard at
the opening slide of this segment,
the beautiful adagietto
of the fifth symphony.
Then the spectacular Symphony of
a Thousand, the eighth symphony and so on.
You can see chronologically that
these all range from 1888 to 1910.
But I'd like to end our brief
sample of the symphonies of Mahler
with a piece that isn't a symphony.
Remember we said, Mahler would usually
compose an orchestral song first and
then, in one way or another.
Bring some of that music into a new
symphony that he was creating.
So here's the song,
Ich bin der Welt abhanden gekommen,
I'm lost to the world,
I've become detached from the world.
Parts of which he later used
in his Symphony Number 5.
The song was written in 1901 and
it was one of the set of five
composed on text by the German poet,
Friedrich Rückert.
So what you're about to hear then again,
is an orchestral song, an orchestral lead.
The text is a melancholy one, indeed,
Mahler was a melancholy person.
A melancholy Mahler if you will.
Here both poet and
composer express isolation,
solitude, distance, a sense of the past,
perhaps a lost past.
But ultimately, a certain resolution
indeed, certain satisfaction,
solace, that music can provide
a refuge for each human being.
As the text that the inn says, I'd escaped
into my solitary world of love and music.
A love for music,
in [FOREIGN], in [FOREIGN].
In my love and in my song, my music song
here being a metaphor for all music.
Let's listen to this
exquisitely beautiful piece as
conducted by Claudio Abbado and
sung by Magdalena Kozena.
[MUSIC]
Purpose of music, indeed of all art,
is nothing less and to search for
an explanation of the meaning of life.
And to create a medium for
reengaging all of the sensations and
sensibilities of life.
But one thing I don't understand
is one of the mysteries of life.
How does someone hear?
How does someone create sounds like
that simply inside one's head?
Alas, I have no idea.
It's simply a gift.