[MUSIC]
Today we leave the music of
the romantic period, and German orbit,
and return to France and engage
impressionism, impressionism in art.
And who doesn't like the viewer
friendly style of French Impressionism?
As we see in this
painting by Claude Monet.
But I'd like to move back a bit
to two other paintings that show
no matter how benign impressionism
seems today, at the time
it was a radical turning away from
established art, the art of the academy.
And to make this point,
let's look at the kind of paintings
that you would then see in the Louvre,
and indeed, this one's still there today.
It's by Jean Auguste Ingres, and it's a
portrait of the composer Luigi Cherubini,
Berlioz's teacher at
the Paris Conservatory.
Notice the classical lines and
the classical imagery with the muse of the
music and the liar behind the composer.
This is the sort of officially
sanctioned art that the Parisian
public expected at that time.
The type of art that would
have been taught and
exhibited at the École des Beaux-Arts.
The fine arts school,
the official showing place of the academy,
the academy of art on
the left bank of Paris.
Then and now, official art.
Now, here's another example,
the official, very realistic art,
then in favor at the Academy in
the second half of the 19th century.
Notice how carefully
the figures are executed.
This painting is so
realistic it's almost like a photograph.
But next,
a radically different approach to art.
Impressionist at Sunrise.
Or An Impression of Sunrise on the
Thames River in London by Claude Monet.
Can you make sense out of,
can you see a sun?
Well, yes,
I can see a sun there pretty clearly.
A city and boats, well, maybe.
I guess, I see the boats there.
But the rest of this is
pretty much just a haze,
an impression of what
a sunrise might have been.
Now in 1874, Monet asked to
have this paint exhibited at the Salon
of the Academy of Fine Arts.
Monet's painting was rejected.
Said one art critic at the time quote,
wallpaper in its more,em,
most embryonic state.
Wallpaper in its most embryonic state
is more finished than this seascape,
end quote.
But this was the painting
that started it all.
The Impressionist movement.
Monet and his friend Renoir and
other kindred spirits were derisively
referred to as Impressionists.
And the label stuck.
Their paintings did not
offer photographic realism,
a photo-like reproduction of a subject or
a scene but
rather a sensation of it,
a momentary fleeting feeling of it.
More mood than realism.
Here's another example.
One of my favorites called
A Portrait of a Woman with Umbrella.
But its less a portrait of a woman
than it is a sensation of some
bright spring day with its sunlight and
its fresh air and its invigorating breeze.
Impression of an experience.
Oddly, this kind of painting,
which was initially rejected and
despised by the academy,
became, over time,
the most publicly popular of all
styles of painting, all styles of art.
If your local museum needs
to raise some money,
just put on an exhibition
of impressionism.
It will be a block buster, and
the public will come flocking in.
Another quick example.
Here we see, Monet's La Grenouilliere,
The Frog Pond.
We sense the shimmering of
the water seen from a distance.
But as we approach the painting, we see
how this sensation, this impression,
is effective or brought on by Monet
through individual dabs of color.
Individual dabs close up,
but an overall sensation or
impression experienced as the viewer
will experience it from a distance.
Individual dabs of color
produce this shimmering effect.
And that's what we'll be talking
about today, color and music and
how music is broken down
into dabs of sound.
Rather than tied to one long,
one color melody.
As we move from romanticism to modernism
in the arts, especially music,
melody is being broken down and
color and texture are being foreground.
Now, the seminal figure in this transition
for music is the composer Claude Debussy.
Exemplified by a shimmering moment from
his Prelude to the Afternoon of a Faun.
[MUSIC]
Well, that's a very
different kind of sound.
One very different than
what we've been hearing and
what we've been experiencing
with romantic music.
But who were these Impressionists?
Well, here we have a list.
A list of Painters on the left, Manet,
Monet, Renoir, Sisley, Pissaro, Cassatt.
And they are sort of precursor
of the Impressionists.
And then the symbolist Poets, of course,
Baudelaire, Verlaine, Rimbaud, Mallarme.
We'll be talking a bit
more about them later on.
And then the Composers,
Claude Debussy, Maurice Ravel, and
perhaps principle to, but also Gabriel
Faure, the Italian, Ottorino Respighi,
and the American, Charles Griffes, and
while we're on the subject of Americans,
let's not forget over there to
left at the bottom, of the pa,
the painters, the American woman painter,
Mary Cassatt.
To see this transition from romanticism to
impressionism in context let's contrast
the French Impressionists with
the mainline of German Composers.
With the Germans of course we have Bach
and Handel and the incomparable Haydn and
Mozart and so
on down through Gustav Mahler.
And note that although Tchaikovsky and
Dvorak, well,
well they were in fact Russian and Czech.
Of course they composed generally in
this dominant, mainline German style.
Okay, well,
how did a German tradition differ
from the one that emerged in
France in the late 19th century.
Well, as you can see here over on the
left, the Germans preferred symphonies and
concertos, while the French composers were
more inclined to engage in tone poems,
as we described them before.
So the Germans tended to
prefer narrative music.
The French mood music.
The German's tended to write
music that was goal oriented.
And what I mean by that was not only for
te, theological from beginning to end but
it was based on cord progressions.
Here would be a typical chord
progression in a German tradition.
>> [MUSIC]
Whereas the French might prefer music that
harmonically is far more static,
static, static.
And engage it so by means of ostinato.
[MUSIC]
It's repeating over and over again.
An ostinato pattern there.
Contrary motion as opposed
to parallel motion.
This contrary motion is, we will see with
just a moment, is a German specialty,
parody motion, is something
the French introduce at this point.
Major and minor scales.
Well they've been the basis
of all Western music.
Since we began talking about it.
Really from the 16th century on,
as opposed to new scales,
we'll experience today.
The whole tone scale.
And the pen, pentatonic scale.
But just to exemplify this
now through the music,
let's turn to an example by Gustav Mahler.
We'll hear a bit of the symphony of
Gustav Mahler, his first symphony.
[MUSIC]
Okay, so that was Mahler.
Now Debussy, just six years later.
[MUSIC]
As I say, the German style seems to march
along goal oriented through functional
chord progression.
The French style, on the other hand,
seems to be perfectly content
to live with the moment, to languish and
enjoy the musical mood of the moment.
Let's go on now to meet the principle com,
proponent of Impressionist music,
Claude Debussy.