[MUSIC]
To be direct, the biography of
Claude Debussy isn't very interesting.
He didn't have 19 children like Bach.
He didn't overcome a disability
like Beethoven and
he didn't possess the eccentric
brilliance of Mozart.
So let's just say that Debussy was
born in the area of Paris in 1862,
was educated at the Paris Conservatory,
and
died in Paris toward the end of
the First World War in 1918.
But he did write great music,
a bit of which you just heard.
I'd like to focus this
segment on just one piece,
Debussy's famous Clair de Lune,
Moonlight, written in 1890.
It's something of a bridge
between romanticism and
hard core impressionism, a middle ground.
And we have the same thing in the painting
of the period, the paintings,
for example, by Edouard Manet.
Is this one romantic,
or is it impressionist,
or is it a little bit of both?
Well, a little bit of both.
But moving to the music,
let's look at a score.
I'll play a bit.
But first I want to ask you how do
you feel as you listen to this music?
Do you feel relaxed or energized?
Do you want to go jogging,
go to the gym and pump some iron, or
perhaps lie down and take a nap.
You decide how you feel.
[MUSIC]
Well, fooling around a bit I know,
but you get the point.
I think we all feel very relaxed.
Why is it we that feel relaxed?
Well there are three reasons for it.
First of all,
the music has no beat or pulse to it.
It doesn't start on the downbeat.
If you look at the score which we we'll
see shortly, you can see that the melody
is being carried across over the bar,
so we don't have strong downbeats.
And sometimes there are,
[MUSIC]
twos alternating with threes, so
it's hard to figure out exactly
where the pulse of this is.
And secondly,
the music is all going down, downward.
And generally speaking in music,
when music goes down, we feel relaxed.
When music goes up, we get upward,
there's a sense of growing tension,
growing anxiety.
But here, again, it's going down.
It's going down this way.
[MUSIC]
Now, those sounds that we heard going
down are particular kind of sound,
called seventh chords.
And let's take a look at the next slide
and see what we, see what we see here.
So here we have a 7th chord,
and it's part and
partial of the beginning
of the Claire de lune here.
So we've got this suppressed beat and
meter, and we've got the 7th chord.
7th chord here,
[MUSIC]
a triad, we see that by the brace.
And then we add one more 3rd up on top.
[MUSIC]
And it has the tendency of creating
a kind of jazz-type sound.
[MUSIC]
That sort of sound,
sounds a bit like cocktail music.
Or if you're in a bar somewhere,
cocktail, cocktail lounge.
Well, that wasn't Debussy's fault.
He was the first one to
think of this idea of
stringing together this descending
chains of seventh chords.
Well anyway, after this long
descent of the seventh chords,
we get to this moment at the bottom where
suddenly we've come along this way.
Well, let me back it up just a little bit,
pick it up here.
[MUSIC]
Bottom, and then it rises up.
Any time our music rises up, our
spirits soar at that particular moment.
[MUSIC]
And then this chord.
Something about that chord.
It's a subdominant chord.
Subdominant chords,
as opposed to dominant chords,
subdominant chords
are always very restful.
[MUSIC]
Rising on the time subdominantly.
And then the music continues.
[MUSIC]
Okay, now we're about down there at
the bottom system where you see the area,
arrow, and we're going to get a good
example of parallelism in music.
[MUSIC]
See all of the parts.
I'll play that again.
All the parts moving together.
[MUSIC]
One last time.
And then on it goes.
[MUSIC]
And so on, so
a good example of parallelism there.
And this brings to the, us to the issue
of contrary motion, which is part and
parcel of the German style,
the German tradition,
as opposed to parallel motion, part of
the new French impressionist style.
So let's go on here and take an example.
I've constructed a diagram for
you using as an example the Star Spangled
Banner, stripping out the harmony and
just leaving the bass and the melody,
the essential framework of the piece.
As you can see, although the bass
doesn't move as often as the melody, but
every time the melody goes down,
the bass goes up, and vice versa.
This creates counterpoint,
voices going in opposite directions.
Counterpoint has provided the framework
of music, especially German music,
ever since Bach and indeed before Bach.
Let's hear the audio
clip that goes with this.
[MUSIC]
Okay, now by contrast,
let's hear an example of parallel motion,
a radically new, untraditional idea,
all of the parts moving in lock step.
It's the opposite of contrary motion, and
let's play this audio clip.
[MUSIC]
And maybe again.
Let's recap now what we've seen so
far about Clair de lune.
Well, we've seen suppressed beat and
meter.
We've seen seventh chords,
particularly descending seventh chords.
We've seen parallel motion, and
now we're going to meet a new chord,
the augmented triad.
And to hear that, we need to dig deeper,
go further into the piece.
[MUSIC]
There's the red star.
Okay, let's hear that again.
So that bracing sound at
the end there at the red star,
well, that's an augmented triad.
Now as you know, we've got major triads.
They sound, usually sound bright.
And we've got minor triads,
more darker sounding.
And diminished triads, well,
they usually sound tense.
And what we just met there,
that was an augmented triad
with two major thirds in it.
We'll talk about that in just a second.
It sounds very strange in a way,
very bracing.
I would sub, say that it
contains a certain shock almost,
a certain [FOREIGN] as
the French would say.
So let me play these for you on the
keyboard, and as you can see on the screen
up there Mm means that you get
your big major third first and
then up above that comes the minor third,
big, little.
And then with the minor triad you
get the little third first and
the big one up on top.
And in the diminished you
get two minor thirds, and
with the augmented triad
you get two major thirds.
So here's the major triad, of course.
[MUSIC]
Play it again.
Here's the minor triad.
[MUSIC]
Here's the diminished triad.
A certain tension to it.
[MUSIC]
And the augmented triad.
Okay, one more time in succession.
Major.
[MUSIC]
Again.
Major, minor, diminished, augmented.
[MUSIC]
Well, let's have a little quiz.
Let's have a little quiz.
I'll play four triads for you in a row,
and you identify what they are.
Here we go.
[MUSIC]
Let's do that again.
Now I'm sure you found that so
much fun, you'd like to do it again.
So here's another quiz to test your skill.