[MUSIC]
The composer, Claude Debussy, spent more
of his time in the company of poets and
painters than he did musicians.
His principal mentor was
the poet Stephane Mallarme
who in 1876 penned a long
work in the symbolist style
of poetry called the Afternoon of a Faun,
[FOREIGN].
Well, the faun in this case is not
a young deer, but rather a sadder,
a mythological beast half man,
usually the top half is man, half goat,
who spends his days in the lustful pursuit
of the nymphs who inhabit the deep forest.
Here are two images that
suggest the nature of the faun.
Note on the left the pan pipes,
a rustic flute from Greek antiquity,
that the faun plays.
On this afternoon,
we see the faun, exhausted from
the mornings escapades reclining in
the still air, of the midday heat.
Now poem as we've said is
an example of symbolist poetry.
The emphasis is not so much on a sequence
of sounds, that makes in tactical sense.
But on setting a context in which
certain words stand out, pop out.
And these words are frated
with special resonance.
Just the sensuous sound of the word.
And all of the associations that
come with this word in our mind,
sounds and associations.
That's what symbolist
poetry was all about and
oddly that's exactly
what music is all about.
Sounds and associations.
Let me read just a short
passage of this 103 line poem.
[FOREIGN].
Well, let's hear what this
artificial puff of sound,
sounds like on the keyboard.
Let me play it for you.
[MUSIC]
And now, Debussy's score.
And as we listen, I want you to tap
your foot to the music and conduct.
Conduct in either two or three.
Here we go.
[MUSIC]
Well now that's different.
How well did you do with your
foot tapping and conducting?
Not well, neither did I.
It's impossible to feel a beat or
to conduct.
Again, because of the suppressed or
hidden nature of the beat and meet.
Let's move on further into the piece.
[MUSIC]
Here we are now, in the middle section,
B part of the form.
[MUSIC]
This sounds like romantic music,
dominated not by the by the strings,
the lush strings playing vibrato here.
[MUSIC]
Okay, that's the middle part and
now the next slide will take us to
the conclusion of Debussy's piece.
[MUSIC]
Note that the music doesn't so
much end, climax.
As it does sort of quietly and
very beautifully disappear.
It's difficult to overestimate
the originality of this work by
Claude Debussy.
It was so different.
Anything else that any composer
was creating at that time and
certainly different from what
the Germans were creating at this time.
As they say, this piece by Debussy
is completely outside the box and
it changed the nature of what
the western musical box sounded like.
Opening our ears to new sounds,
new chords and new scales.
But by way of review,
let's just reprise what we've learned so
far about Debussy's Afternoon of a Faun.
Again, the beat is suppressed.
This is not foot stomping music here.
To say that there's no melody,
well that's a bit of an exaggeration.
Maybe closer to mark to say
that we hear here flourishes.
Arabesque, Phillips of sound if you will.
But not melody as we traditionally known,
traditionally understood it.
And of course we have this
new found importance.
This new found sense of color splotches or
dabs of color in the orchestra.
The musical form however is traditional.
Traditional ternary ABA.
Indeed, that's true of Debussy's Clair
de Lune that we heard earlier as well.
New sounds but traditional form.
At the time of the first performance of
the Prelude to The Afternoon of a Faun,
Debussy said the following
about the piece.
Quote, my prelude is really
a sequence of mood paintings,
throughout which the desire and
the dreams of the fallen move in
the heat of the midday sun, end quote.
And when the poet
Mallarme heard the music,
he in turn said the following
about Debussy's music, quote,
I never expected anything like it, the
music prolongs the emotion of my poem and
paints its scenery more
passionately than could colors.
So go back and listen to this piece on
your streaming music with the textbook or,
if you wish, on YouTube.
Is it poetry, painting, or music?