[MUSIC]
Nice glissando sound there,
those rushing ascents.
The glissando of course, is one of
the fingerprints that help us identify,
help us recognize music in
the impressionist style.
Having met some new chords,
augmented triads and
sundry seventh chords,
let's go on now to meet some new scales.
And to get into the mood, let's take
a look at a painting by Claude Monet,
Ships at Harbor on
the Seine River at Rouen.
And with it, shortly,
some music by Claude Debussy.
Debussy wrote to a friend in 1916 quote,
you do me great honor by calling
me a pupil of Claude Monet.
Here's a musical counterpart of this
painting about ships and sails by Monet.
It's a piece called Sails,
Voiles, Sails by Debussy.
But for this piece, to make sense,
we've got to meet a new scale
that Debussy employs here.
The whole-tone scale.
So here, the beginning of Voiles,
you see the piano score up above there.
And below it,
we have the whole-tone scale.
Starting on the pitch c, just as Debussy
wrote it in, in the composition.
And at the end, we'll play the usual
C major scale by way of contrast.
So, let's play the audio clip now.
[MUSIC]
Okay, and now the beginning
of the piece with the score.
[MUSIC]
All parallel motion, but all notes of
the whole-tone scale used an ostinato.
A bass ostinato.
Parallel motion.
[MUSIC]
Whole-tone scale.
As we move into the next
segment of the piece,
we'll see that things get complicated.
First note the ostinato.
And of course an ostinato is a pattern
that repeats, whether in the bass or
the melody, even a rhythm again and
again and again.
I'll start by playing the right hand of
the ostinato to call your attention to it.
And then morphed into the music
the way that Debussy wrote it.
[MUSIC]
Well, at the end of this,
you heard a somewhat different sound.
Debussy had changed there,
almost imperceptibly morphed scale.
From the whole tone scale,
as the basis of the piece to
the pentatonic scale, a five pitch scale.
As you see here.
So here's the 5 note pentatonic
scale plus the octave.
Compare to the seven
note western major scale.
And of course it goes
[MUSIC]
Pentatonic or.
On the black notes, black keys,
as compared to the major scale.
[MUSIC]
Now, the pentatonic scale has
a decidedly non-western sound to it.
When combined with parallel motion,
that sense of the non-western,
the non-European sound,
is particularly magnified.
[MUSIC]
Pentatonic scale in parallel
fifths in that particular case.
Alright, Let's review
what we've learned so
far about Debussy's piano piece, Voiles.
As you saw there,
we began with the whole-tone scale.
[MUSIC]
Six note scale.
In that fashion there was an ostinato.
[MUSIC]
Many ostinatos in fact.
or
[MUSIC]
that kind of thing,
you heard the parallelism.
[MUSIC]
Frequently, the Glissando, how's that go?
That kind of thing, the Glissando,
and, ultimately, toward the end,
the Pentatonic Scale.
[MUSIC]
Well I'm intrigued by what
we might have learned so
far about Debussy and impressionism and
his use of new scale.
New at least within the tradition
of Western classical music.
Mozart and Beethoven, well they
certainly didn't use these scales.
But can we recognize them?
Can we recognize the difference?
Is the general educated listener
able to differentiate between,
say, the major scale
from a pentatonic scale.
Well, let's see.
I've put together a quiz here.
I'll play the audio clip
that I've prepared.
You'll see ten blanks on the screen, and
then you'll hear ten
scales that go with it.
They'll be played for you.
So we've got ten blanks, ten audio
clips exhibiting each of these scales.
There are ten blanks and
five scales, so each type of scale,
each type of scale is heard twice.
Let's take a look.
Okay?
So we've got the ten blanks,
you'll hear ten audio clips.
You match the scale with the blank.
One.
[MUSIC]
Two.
Three.
[MUSIC]
Four.
Five.
[MUSIC]
Six.
Seven.
[MUSIC]
Eight.
Nine.
[MUSIC]
And ten.