[MUSIC]
We just had a quiz on musical scales,
some traditional Western scales and
some more exotic.
The word of the impressionist,
Debussy in particular,
get to know these non-Western scales.
Did he travel to the Orient or
further afield to the Far East?
No, the Far East came to him.
Came to him in Paris in 1889.
Here we see a photograph
of the famous Eiffel Tower,
it was being constructed in 1888.
There were all sorts of
new fangled inventions,
some of them from the United States that
were on display here at this World's Fair,
including the electric lightbulb and
mechanical elevator.
Now because it was a World's Fair, and
this was the era of
Western Colonial Imperialism in the East,
displays including a giant reproduction
of a temple in Cambodia were created.
And Cambodian musicians imported to Paris,
as were those from Indonesia.
Here we see dancers from the island
of Java, Indonesia accompanied,
as you can see by the arrow there on
the left, accompanied by a Gamelan.
Debussy, i think, pretty,
pretty much everyone else in Paris, at,
at this time, went to the exposition.
And it was here that he heard this
exotic music, as he recalled,
quote, don't you remember the Japanese
music that was capable of expressing
every nuance of meaning?
In expressible shades,
which make our tonic and
dominant sounds seem weak and
empty, end quote.
Well, here's the type of music
that Debussy would have heard.
And as you listen, ask yourself,
what kind of scale,
which type of scale rest behind,
or is the heart of this music?
[MUSIC]
What did you think?
Good.
Pentatonic scale.
And the musicians weren't the only ones
affected by the Far East in this period.
So were the painters.
Here we see the rather
spectacular portrait
done by Claude Monet, of his wife,
Madame Monet [FOREIGN].
Museum of Fine Arts in Boston.
But if you go to Giverny and
visit Monet's home there, Giverny,
France, little bit north of Paris,.
You'll be struck,
surely, by the fact that the art that
Monet displayed there was not his own.
Not his own impressionist art.
But both in the kitchen and,
as we see here in the parlor,
it was flat, two dimensional Chinese art.
And at the same time did Monet had this
in his home, Debussy had this sort
of Chinese piece overlooking his desk,
in his study.
His goldfish, Poisson d'or, it's called.
But the odd thing is,
that the impressionist and
the pre-impressionist
saw the exotic not only
in distant places, but
near to home in contiguous Spain.
Here are the names of some of
the pieces with Spanish connections,
influenced by Spanish sounds that French
composers of the period composed.
Édouard Lalo, Symphonie espanole,
Debussy, Iberia, Ravel,
Rapsodie espanole and,
of course, his famous Bolero.
Now Ravel actually had some Spanish roots,
having been born in the bask
region of northern Spain.
But no one was influenced by Spanish art
more than the painter Édouard Manet,
as is seen in his spectacular
Death of the Bull Fighter in
The Frick Gallery in New York,
one of my favorite paintings.
the exhibits an early two dimensional
flat plain and a focus on color.
And when a troupe of Spanish
dancers visited Paris in the 1860's
many responded with this image of
the flamenco dancer Lola de Valence.
And even the American's got
into the act judging from
John Singer Sargent's Spanish Dancer.
More Flamenco dancing here,
which was exhibited in Paris by
the official academy in 1882.
Here we see, not only the dancer but
the guitars that accompanied her,
being played and hung on the wall, and
the importance of the guitar as an emblem
of Spanish exoticism wasn't lost on Manet
as we see here in his guitar player.
All of which brings us
to our guitar player,
our guest,
classical guitarist Solomon Silber.