[MUSIC]
I want to start this segment with
a slide to make what I think is
an important point.
Our historians have long recognized
that with the impressionist and
post impressions color, as distinct and
different from the line in painting
became increasingly important.
But what we need to recognize is that
the same thing happened in music.
With the impressionist such as Debussy,
color became so
important that it was
gradually separated from line.
Up to this point in history of music,
color was subservient to line or
melody, it reinforced melody.
Indeed, how do we
recognize when listening.
What is melody?
Well, often we're given a clue, a hint,
because when a new distinctive collection
of pitches comes into play,
it is presented by,
it's highlighted by a new and
distinctive sound.
Let me give you an example
here by using 2 audio clips.
Examples of the traditional way,
the way of Western romantic music,
actually all Western music,
classical romantic.
The first one here is by Dvorak and
then one by Brahms.
Actually we've heard of
both of these before.
The Dvorak clip comes from
the New World Symphony.
You'll hear here a bit of introduction and
then a distinct aggregate,
distinct collection of pitches.
But the thing that really catches our
ear is the sound of the instrument,
the English Horn.
Melody and color work together here.
They are unified with the aim of making us
hear this as a distinctive melody.
[MUSIC]
Okay.
All right, so melody and instrument come
in together, they reinforce one another.
Now, another example,
this one from Brahms.
We'll hear a distinctive dying out and
then some new pitches.
But again, auditorially,
we're paying attention
to this melody because it's presented,
it's tied to a French Horn.
When the melody comes in,
so does a new instrument.
It's almost as if the French Horn is
saying, hey, here comes the melody.
[MUSIC]
Vibration.
Okay, but now a different approach
by Debussy, colors enter but
they don't seem to be tied to a string or
a line of distinct pitches.
They seem to float.
Float, just as color.
[MUSIC]
Let's try to drive this point home
by means of a few more images.
We'll go back to a clear example
of realism by Gustave Courbet.
The colors work with the lines.
But most important,
they stay within the lines.
With the next image,
the distinction between line and
color is a good deal less clear.
Line seems to be taking
a back seat to color.
Now here, with Henri Matisse's,
The Red Studio, the intensity
of the red begins to overrun,
go beyond the lines of the object.
And the same thing is true of the,
somewhat later painting by Raoul Dufy,
The Red Violin.
Color is now seen to
have its own intensity.
This point can be clearly made by turning,
again, to Henri Matisse and
to a composition he created in 1909.
La Danse, The Dance,
we see here the flesh
tones of the dancers.
But Matisse did this same
composition two years later.
And now look at the difference.
Here the angles of the limbs of
the dancers are slightly more acute,
but the real difference lies
in the emotional impact.
The intensity of the color red.
Pure color is carrying the day.
And of course with modernism and
post modernism, color alone and
the power of pure abstract color
becomes a chief means of expression.
And this is true of
modernist music as well.
New textures and colors seize the day.
They override the melody as we
have traditionally understood it.
Let's end with some modernist art,
painting by ro, Mark Rothko, and
here's some modernist music by
contemporary American composer John Adams.
[MUSIC]
On we go to the bracing
sounds of modernism.