[MUSIC]
Boy, those were bracing sounds.
That'll wake you up from the warm
security blanket of romanticism.
So, we've come to modern music,
modernism in music.
Modernism, individual arts.
Modernism in music began
shortly after 1900, just before
the beginning of the first world war, and
continued until after the second word war.
And in some ways,
it continues even to today.
So there's an irony here.
What we call modern music or modernist
music is now more than a hundred years
old, so modernism is no longer
modern in a chronological sense.
But if modern means a radical
departure from traditional values
then this description holds true.
Again, it's a radical departure
from traditional values.
This music shocks us even more
intensely than does the recent art
of the post-modernist period,
roughly 1945 down to the present.
So modernist art was shocking too, but
not quiet to the same
degree as modernist music.
To make the point we're gonna do
a little test, a little quiz here.
We're going to place you
in a dark room for a day.
Well not really for a day, for a little
while, and have you engage in an activity.
You'll have one of two choices,
you can choose to sit with only this
painting by Wassily Kandinsky or
sit and listen to this music
by Arnold Schoenberg of 1911.
Which do you choose?
As you can see, here's the painting.
[MUSIC].
Well, which did you prefer.
Well, not long ago I gave this
same choice to exactly one hundred
undergraduate students.
And do you know how many
choose the modernist music?
Exactly two, yes only two.
[LAUGH]
Why didn't they choose the music?
Well the first point,
it's an intriguing one.
Is it possible that we have
a more visceral reaction,
a more intense response to sound
than we do to visual images?
Maybe images don't move us,
don't frighten us to the same degree
as do sounds, musical or otherwise.
As I'm fond of saying, you don't get
frightened at horror films until the music
starts to get really creepy, but
let's move to the more obvious point.
Why does almost no one among this body of
general listeners choose the Shermberg?
Well through our listening to music
we peoples all around the world
have developed various templates for
music that have things in common.
In our templates for example, is the
expectation or the desire for consonants.
Schoenberg was also a painter.
We have in this music of Arnold
Schoenberg, no scale, no melody, chords,
meter for example, as we think of a scale,
melody, chords, and meter.
Now this transition to Schoenberg's music,
which forces us to rethink our template,
wasn't as abrupt as his
music might suggest.
Back in the 1850's, Wagner and
Liszt began to use chromaticism,
which obscured the scale and the triad.
And there was a similar gradual
evolution in the visual arts,
as we'll see by our next little quiz.
I'll show you five images, ranging
from roughly 1850 to 1915, 65 years,
and you arrange them in
correct chronological order.
They represent in order photographic
realism, impressionism,
cubist's style, expressionist style,
and purely abstract art.
There is one image of each style,
again, realism, impressionism, cubism,
expressionism, and abstract art.
The images will be numbered for
you, one, two, three, four, five,
and you put them in correct
order chronologically.
Okay.
Here we go.
Slide number one.
Slide number two.
Slide number three.
Slide number four.
Slide number five.
Okay and
the correct order chronologically is four,
two, one, five, three.
Correct order would be Courbet,
Monet, Picasso,
Kokoschka, and Malevich in that order.
So in this period of fewer than 65 years,
we went from art as we know it
to art as we don't know it.
Obviously, styles change.
An absence of stylistic change would
denote an absence of creativity.
A period of intellectual sterility and
that wouldn't happen.
So styles change and
they overlap as you can see.
So romanticism overlaps with impressionism
and impressionism with modernism and
modernism with post modernism,
each in succession.
Now modernism transformed, distorted,
disrupted, whatever you wanna use
by way of a term, the tradition
of 19th century romantic music.
Modernist composers were aware of that
tradition, maybe even fearful of it.
The so called anxiety of influence.
So modernism rebels against romanticism,
but in so doing, it has to engage it.
It has to establish a counterpoint,
a dialogue with tradition.
Post modernism seems consciously,
consciously unaware of tradition.
It takes art on its own terms,
on everyone's terms.
We'll get to post-modernism next time.
Here we want to dive deep into modernism.
And don't worry,
don't be afraid, you'll be fine.
We'll start with Igor Stravinsky.