[MUSIC]
Here's a collage or
dip dish that I've put together and
a question, in the photo on the right,
is Igor Stravinsky and
to his left, is a drawing of
Stravinsky w ho created this drawing.
Well, the person standing
next to Stravinsky
is his good buddy Pablo Picasso.
Wait a minute, you'll say.
I thought Stravinsky was Russian.
How did he get here with Spaniard Picasso?
Well the common point of union was Paris.
Both Picasso and Stravinsky were drawn
to Paris in the early 20th century.
Paris before New York,
was the artist capital of the world.
Stravinsky came to Paris
because of this person,
the person that we see in the center of
the next photos here, of this triptych.
In the center, we see the arts
impresario Serge Diaghilev.
And on the right you see the famous
choreographer, modernism Vaslav Nijinsky.
Back in Russia, Diaghilev had formed
a dance company that he called
the ballet russes or Russian Ballet.
But the point of it was
to export Russian art and
especially ballet to the West,
to artistic Paris.
He, Diaghilev,
formed an idea for a ballet and
then he pulled together scenic designers,
choreographers such as Nijinsky,
composers such as Stravinsky
all to create the show.
What Diaghilev wanted to sell
the Parisians in effect was imported
Russian exoticism.
Let's look at these two posters for
productions by Diaghilev
involving his ballets russes,
one of 1914 and one of 1910.
You can see the stereotypical
image of what
dancers from the steppes of Russia
were supposed to look like.
In quick succession,
Stravinsky was commissioned to create and
the he executed three ballet scores for
Diaghilev's dance troupe,
the Firebird, Petrushka and
the Rite of Spring.
Here's a bit of music from the first
of these, the Firebird of 1910.
What do you think of this music,
does it sound like modernism to you?
Is it romantic or is it modern?
[MUSIC]
Well, it's really romantic.
That's over the top romanticism
of the sort created in Russia
by Rimsky-Korsakov as heard in
his beautiful Scheherazade.
It is not surprising Firebird sounds
much like Scheherazade because
Rimsky-Korsakov was Stravinsky's
teacher in St. Petersburg.
But with Stravinsky's next ballet russes,
Petrushka of 1911 we
have a different sound.
A different world of sound.
We're taken to a village fair and
a puppet show in rural Russia.
You can see on the image
here of the puppet show,
up above the stage the title Petrushka,
spelled out in the Cyrillic alphabet.
As you listen to the music, try to
identify three things that you're hearing
that are not part of musical romanticism.
Things that take us away
from the romantic aesthetic.
Try to conduct this in two or
three as we go.
[MUSIC]
Well, the first thing that we notice is
a different sort of orchestral texture,
a much more brittle, more metallic sound.
We don't hear the warm, lush [SOUND]
bravado rich sound of the violins.
Instead, we hear the woodwinds and
a lot of percussion.
Metallic, percussive equals
a more modern sound.
And how did we do conducting this?
Well for me, it's impossible.
Of course, there's a lot of syncopation,
but it's impossible
because the meters are always changing,
so we have irregular meters.
Groups of two, and then groups of
three are continually alternating.
And we have,
now only more than one in succession,
but more than one meter simultaneously.
And thus, polymeters.
As we can see on the slide here,
we're coming along
in a three four meter in one part but
a seven eight meter in another part.
So in effect we have seven eighth
notes against six eighth notes.
Seven against six in succession but
we also simultaneous meters here,
polymeters, because we have five eight
time up here and then two four times.
So we have really five against
four eighth notes there.
And then a succession,
you can see over here,
of running five eight, seven eight,
five eight, eight eight, and
sometimes that's going five against
four eighth notes and so on.
So it's very complex.
Let me try to follow along here
as we listen to the audio,
we'll see how we'll do,
we'll have at a run at this.
We'll follow along here
with the melody and
see how complex rhythmically this sounds.
[MUSIC]
So we'll pause it there.
And as you see I didn't do
a great job of following there.
It's very complex.
It's racing along.
And this is a reduced piano score, so
the full score that Stravinsky
created is even more complex.
So it's the orchestral texture,
more metallic and
percussive, and it's especially
the rhythm, this complex rhythm,
that is the innovative quality
of this modernism here.
Now, with the next ballet
score that Stravinsky wrote,
it's not the texture and
the rhythm alone but
also the revolutionary harmonic
dissonance that we experience.