[MUSIC]
Let's take a trip to Paris,
and who wouldn't like that?
Paris, New York, Vienna,
what's not to like?
So here we are in Paris with
an overview thanks to Google Earth.
We see the river Seine and
on the right bank,
the area leading to the Champs-Elysee.
And at A on the Avenue Montaigne,
the Theatre des Champs-Elysees.
In Stravinsky's day and still today,
this was a very fashionable area,
tres chic, with lots of expensive shops,
Hermes and Louis Vuitton for example.
And on this Avenue Montaigne,
as mentioned, was and
is the Theatre de Champs-Elysees,
with its art deco exterior and
its art deco interior.
And it was here, on this stage, still one
of he major concert halls of Paris today,
that Stravinsky's Rite of Spring
premiered on an unseasonably hot night,
29 May, 1913.
Stravinsky had actually written
the score not in Russia, or in Paris,
but in Switzerland, working away at
a small piano in a small apartment.
As he tells us in some remarkable
footage shot, I would guess, about 1955.
I can't trace the origins of this so
I can't give the copyright
information here, but let's watch it.
>> Room where I composed
the Le Sacre du Pritemps.
>> The composition of the Le Sacre was
completed by the beginning of 1912.
>> When I composed the first
part of the Le Sacre,
Djagilev invited me to Venice and
I started to play him these chords.
59 times the same chord.
Diagilev was a little bit surprised.
He asked me only one thing,
which was [INAUDIBLE],
he asked me,
will it last a very long time this way?
And I said to the end my dear.
And he was silent because he
understood that the answer was serious.
[MUSIC]
After the big,
incredible scandal of the first
performance of Le Sacre du Pritemps,
he was delighted.
>> So, there we heard Stravinsky's
reaction to Diagilev's reaction to
Stravinsky's score.
Indeed, this was going to be a modernist
statement from beginning to end, so
radical in fact that it caused a riot and
the police had to be called in.
Stravinsky, as we'll see here,
had to go backstage and help the
choreographer Nijinsky keep the dancers
going over the noise of the yelling and
screaming of the audience.
>> Petrujka was the first thing
I wrote after the Firebird.
And that was written In France and
then Rome.
And then to Rome was a Russian ballet.
Diagliev asked me to come and
to assist him.
Petrusjka was a immense
advance after [INAUDIBLE].
Third advance was of course the Le Sacre
du Pritemps, that was a scandal.
A big scandal of [INAUDIBLE],
it was a historical scandal.
The public, they shouted,
this event, and son.
Just from the beginning and
then they sold [INAUDIBLE].
[LAUGH] The scandal doubled.
Then the curtain opened on
a group of knock-kneed and
long [INAUDIBLE] lolitas,
jumping up and down.
[FOREIGN], the storm broke.
It's a spoof, a very noisy [INAUDIBLE].
I went up and said, go to Hell.
Excuse me [INAUDIBLE].
They came for Sheherazade or
for Cleopatra, and
they saw the Le Sacre du
Pritemps they were very shocked.
>> As Stravinsky says here in the video,
the public was expecting one kind
of Russian ballet, Rimsky-Korsakov,
or perhaps the style of Tchaikovsky.
[MUSIC]
But instead, they got this.
Now if there's one moment that
constitutes the beginning of modernism,
the opening salvo,
opening cannon shot of modernism,
it's this beginning section of
Stravinsky's, the Rite of Spring.
The story isn't so radical, it's a bit
of nationalistic Russian primitivism.
Pagan tribes express traditional
rituals through dance and
sacrifice at the arrival of spring.
Again, the modern take
on Russian primitivism.
We can see it here in
Henri Matisse's interpretation of
such primitive dance in
the Hermitage in St. Petersburg.
But Stravinsky's musical score
as you see and as you heard,
is a massive one with lots of percussion
and brasses and divided strings.
Here are the divided strings
down at this part of the score.
And the percussion and
brasses in the center of the score here.
And look at the size of it.
I count vertically 28 parts in all.
The revolutionary aspect of this,
as we first heard, is the rhythm.
It's complex because different parts
are playing rhythms simultaneously,
hence the term polyrhythms.
And you can see on the screen there,
and I'll tap maybe on my trusty table.
[MUSIC]
That's one rhythm, and then.
That's another, and.
[MUSIC]
That's the third.
And then the trumpets are playing.
[MUSIC]
The violins.
And the cellos at the bottom
have the syncopation.
[MUSIC]
We saw this sort of thing with
Stravinsky's Petrushka, and
in addition, here we have
different meters simultaneously.
Different meters, and we can see on
the screen here again, 6/8 against 7/8.
Against, what's that down there?
5/8 6/8 against 7/8 against 5/8.
And again, as with Patruska,
we have irregular meters.
Here you can see the following groups,
let me count them for you.
1 2 3 4, 1 2 3 4 5, 1 2, 1,
2 3 4 5 6, 1 2 3, 1 2 3 4, 1 2 3 4 5.
But what makes this almost a brutal
brutalist passage is the fact that
although the strings are played much
of this, they're not using bravado.
Instead, they're striking
each pitch with a down bow,
which creates a percussive effect.
Down bow down down,
down down down down, down down.
And so on.
The violin is no longer a warm,
melodic instrument.
But it's become a percussive instrument.
And this is also true of
the piano in this period as well.
It's more of a percussive
instrument than a lyrical one.
Let's review how this sounds now,
with an audio clip using a real orchestra.
[MUSIC]
Having reviewed this iconic moment
from the point of view of rhythm,
let's do so now with regard to pitch.
Not only is this passage disrupted
rhythmically, the harmony,
the chords are distinctive as well.
And actually, there's only one chord here,
one harmony at this point.
And Stravinsky has created
it in an interesting way.
He took a major triad,
which you see on the right here.
Here's our major triad over here.
And put it with a seventh chord over here.
And note that this major triad is actually
only a half step built on a half step,
on a degree that is only a half step
away from the basis of this chord here.
So it's slightly off the triad, and then
sounded together, they produce this sound.
So here's the basic triad.
[MUSIC]
Here's the triad,
here's the seventh chord.
[MUSIC]
Here, but once you put them together,
you get this kind of sound.
[MUSIC]
A very dissonant sound
[LAUGH] to say the least.
Oddly, this slightly disjointed sound,
it was being created between 1910 and
1920,
also had an exact analogue in
the visual arts at the time in cubism.
Let me show you three paintings by three
great cubist painters of the period,
Juan Gris, George Braque and
Pablo Picasso.
As we look at these,
notice that all three have music and
musical instruments as the subject matter.
First, Three Musicians of Picasso
at the Philadelphia Museum of Art.
Next, Woman with Guitar in
the Pompidou Center in Paris.
And third and last, The Violin of
Juan Gris at the Kunstmuseum in Basel.
Now, about this time
another cubist painter,
Albert Gleizes, wrote a book, Le Cubism.
That tells, and also graphically shows,
how the cubist artists did it.
They would take an object, and
then repeat it slightly off center, and
then repeat it slightly off center again.
And then maybe take a section of it, and
then put that section at
right angles to that section.
And by the end, voila.
A cubist construction with
a disjunctive effect.
Well, as we saw, Stravinsky was creating
a similarly disruptive sound in
music by putting triads slightly off
center, slightly against themselves.
All right, let's take a moment now
to review what we've seen thus far.
Style elements of modern music as
exemplified in the Rite of Spring.
Well, first of all, we've heard both in
the Rite of Spring, and in earlier in
Petrushka, a great number of percussion
instruments and percussive sound.
Secondly the use of strings
as percussion instruments and
not lush sounds here but
harsh sounds, harsh playing.
Third, more woodwinds to create
this bright brittle orchestration.
Fourth, irregular meters and polymeters.
Well, they contribute as well.
And finally, heavy dissonances created by
polychords, chords slightly off center.
As Stravinsky said,
this all causes a sensation.
Here's the report of one
eyewitness observer,
a reporter who worked for
the New York paper, the New York Press.
Now, defunked New York Press.
The critic is Carl van Vechten.
I was sitting in a box in
which I had rented one seat.
Three ladies sat in front of me and
a young man occupied the place behind me.
He stood up during
the course of the ballet to
enable himself to see more clearly.
The intense excitement under
which he was laboring,
thanks to the potent force of the music,
betrayed itself presently
when he began to beat rhythmically on
the top of my head with his fists.
Well, a potent rhythmic force indeed.
But in truth,
it was the choreography, as much as
the music that provoked the outrage.
The novelty of irregular dance
steps was equally disruptive,
as we'll see in the next video.
This is Millicent Hodson's and
Robert Joffrey's recreation
of Stravinsky's ballet.
With the costumes and choreography as
close as possible to the original.
[MUSIC]
Well, maybe we'll stop there.
But of course,
you can watch the rest on YouTube.
As Stravinsky said,
it was a scandal but a huge success,
the kind of [LAUGH] scandal
we should all hope for.
The classic [FOREIGN], the [FOREIGN].
What happened to the Rite of Spring?
This radical statement of modernism
that had caused such a scandal?
Well in 1930s, the music had caught
the ear of Walt Disney, who as you know,
used the Rite of Spring
as the centerpiece for
the worlds first full length
animated film, Fantasia.
[MUSIC]
Stravinsky's wild music had become
becalmed through this cartoon film.
Radical modernism had become mainstream.