[MUSIC]
Welcome back.
I enjoyed our last quiz in which you and
I had a chance to choose
a work of modern art or
one of modern music.
And most of you chose the art.
And we tried to explain why.
But let's have another quiz, now,
choosing just between two pieces of music.
Let's say, you're stranded on a beautiful
desert island but have only one piece,
only one piece of music to
listen to in perpetuity.
Time immemorial.
Which piece would you choose?
Piece one or piece two?
Here's piece one.
[MUSIC]
And now piece two.
Well, I would submit that most
of us would choose piece one.
Piece two seems a little unnatural for
reasons that we'll get into later.
Piece one was by Mozart.
Piece two by Arnold Schoenberg.
Who was this seminal figure to whom
I keep referencing or referring?
Who was Arnold Schoenberg?
Well, Schoenberg was born in Vienna, and
was essentially self-taught in music.
In the 1920s, Schoenberg moved to Berlin.
And then in the 1930s, when the Nazis took
over Germany and Austria, he, as with so
many other Jews and artists and
intellectuals, fled and
came to the United States.
Indeed, Schoenberg settled and
ultimately died in Los Angeles, in 1951.
And the Schoenberg family is
still prominent in Los Angeles,
in legal circles, legal profession today,
having played a role in
the infamous OJ Simpson trial.
Small world.
Anyway, as a young man,
Schoenberg wasn't sure if he was
going to be a musician or a painter.
As you can see, he was skilled in painting
in the expressionist style of art,
as practiced in Vienna and Munich and
Berlin, around this time, around 1910.
Actually, the prototype of
expressionist art might be the creation
of Norwegian artist Edvard Munch and
his famous, The Scream.
You can see the similarities
to Schoenberg's art here.
German or Nordic expressionism is very
different from French impressionism.
With impressionism, it's the receiver,
the viewer, who fashions the ultimate
effect of the painting in his or
her own mind.
With expressionism, it's the artist alone
attempting not to create a scene or
mood of some external subject or
object, but
rather the mood of the artist exporting
the inner feelings of the artist.
Expressionist art is full of anxiety,
fear, intensity, angst,
as the Germans would say.
And we've got plenty of
angst in Schoenberg's
iconic work of musical
expressionism Pierrot Lunaire.
Premiered in 1912,
Pierrot Lunaire is Schoenberg's setting
of 21 poems by poet Albert Giraud.
Pierrot is a clown, a clown from
traditional italian puppet and
carnival shows, Commedia dell'Arte.
But here, Pierrot is not just any clown,
but a sad clown.
And a clown who is slightly crazy,
indeed loony.
A clown who has,
like the werewolf, come under the spell
of the full moon, la lune, in French.
Loony.
So, this clown borders on the hysterical.
Schoenberg's music will
sound a bit hysterical, too.
This is atonal music,
music without a tonal center.
If we take scales away, as we know them,
and take away triads and
take away functional chord progressions,
we end up with music without a key.
Music without a tonal center.
Atonal music.
This feeling of disruption, disjunction
is affected by something called octave
displacement, which destroys
a sense of melody as we know it.
Or perhaps,
challenges us to hear melody in a new way.
Let me play a tune.
Can you identify this tune?
So let me play this for you.
[MUSIC]
Okay, let's do it again.
Can you hear that?
Yeah, that really was.
[MUSIC]
Something as simple as
Mary Had A Little Lamb.
But each of the pitches was taken and
removed,
was displaced an octave from one another.
And that's what makes this music hard
to recognize, hard to understand.
Here, we see a passage through
Pierrot Lunaire as Schoenberg wrote it
on the left, and
as he might have written it.
He could have written it if he wanted to,
to make it more readily understandable.
So let me see if I can duplicate
this on the screen here.
Here's what Schoenberg wrote.
[MUSIC]
And here's what we probably
would have preferred to hear.
[MUSIC]
And finally, the sense of disjunction and
hysteria is magnified here by a new
kind of vocal delivery that Schoenberg
created, called Sprechstimme, speech/song.
Something that's neither speech nor
song, but halfway between the two.
The little X's that you see on the notes
here are Schoenberg's signs or
commands to use Sprechstimme.
Okay, let's focus now on song number
six of Pierrot Lunaire, Madonna.
Here's the full text.
Our hysterical clown has
a vision of the mother of Christ,
Madonna, at the cross,
gazing upon her crucified son.
She is expressing her inner feelings
at this excruciating moment.
Notice that the text here refers
to her eyes as rot und offen.
Surely, the line in the text
caused Schoenberg to create
this sort of music here.
But also, to recreate it in his painting
at about the same time, Red Gaze, of 1910.
So we have the hallucination
of the clown gazing upon Mary
at the cross who looks down
at us with eyes red and open.
Did we realize that the human
in the red gaze is a female?
Perhaps that's why Schoenberg
created this setting of songs,
created Pierrot Lunaire for female voice.
Let's listen to unique
approach to text and music.
[MUSIC]
And now, an instrumental interlude.
The text continues.
[MUSIC]
Did you like that last chord?
When Arnold Schoenberg created
atonal music such as this,
he entered a brave new land.
But it was a lawless land,
there were no rules.
In tonal music, we knew that this
set of pitches was to be followed by
this set of pitches, and
then onto this next set of pitches.
There was a hierarchy.
Sub-dominant chord would go
to the dominant chord, and
that would then move on
to the final tonic chord.
Now, with atonal music,
there is no hierarchy.
And all 12 pitches are equal.
But if all 12 pitches are equal, why
choose any one pitch at any given time?
The composer had absolute freedom.
But as Igor Stravinsky observed
in his poetics of music, nothing,
nothing is more frightening for the
creator and maybe for every individual.
Nothing is more frightening
than absolute freedom.
At least with tonal music,
the composer had a template of tried and
true tonal chord progressions and
tried and true musical forms.
So Schoenberg had created
a conundrum of sorts.
[LAUGH] He was a prisoner
of absolute freedom.
How did he solve the problem?
He invented a new system of rules,
and thereby created 12-tone music.