[MUSIC]
When Arnold Schoenberg and
others created atonal music,
he also created a problem, as we've seen.
With no guide or game plan for
musical structure, how to proceed?
Well Schoenberg came up with a system, a
set of rules that gave structure to music.
A kind of music called 12-tone
music because it uses,
in sequence,
all 12 tones of the chromatic scale.
It's also called serial music because
the 12 pitches come in a fixed series.
Here's how the game is played.
First, the composer can choose
any pleasing sequence of pitches,
but all 12 pitches, all chromatic notes
within the octave have to be used, and
have to come in a series,
or in a sequence of 12.
This is called the row.
The row many start on any pitch.
You could start on C, or E, or
F sharp, or B flat, whatever.
The pitches in the row may
sound vertically as a chord.
You could have one, two,
three come in succession, or one, two,
three sound simultaneously.
The rows may overlap.
The row may go backward.
We call that retrograde motion.
The row may go upside down,
be inverted, or an exact mirror image.
That's called inversion.
The row may go upside down and
backward, retrograde inversion.
And finally, the composer can
use any meters and rhythms.
Rhythm is not a primary issue here.
Well, as they say, a picture is worth
a thousand words, and if that's true,
maybe a video is worth a 100,000.
So that's what we're gonna do.
We're gonna turn to a video now, and
try to simplify all this by
visualizing how 12-tone music works.
We've got a good video here.
It's posted on YouTube by one Nava Glick.
I can't find out anything about our
Nava Glick, but she says that she hopes
someone will find this useful,
and we thank her for sharing.
>> This means that every single
note in an octave is played.
>> So you can see, she's color
coded the pitches of the scale.
Now just running up the chromatic scale.
>> These notes are then rearranged
to make a row or series,
where each of the 12 notes is used,
and no note is played twice.
>> The composer uses any series he or
she wishes.
[MUSIC]
>> The series can then be reversed
to create a different sound.
[MUSIC]
>> Retrograde, going backwards.
And the row can go backward and
forward simultaneously against itself.
But isn't this all a little bit strange, a
little bit crazy, a little bit unmusical?
Just modern mathematical games?
Well, no.
Actually, JS Bach did the same
thing in this piece from
his musical offering back in the 1740s.
[MUSIC]
And this is called a crab canon,
as you can see here,
because the crab looks forward
while walking backwards.
The back is getting
closer to the middle now,
the beginning of the melody is now at
the midpoint and heading toward the end,
and my end is becoming my beginning,
my beginning my end.
[MUSIC]
And musicians from the Renaissance also
used these permutations of the melody,
forward, backwards, upside down, whatever.
So if Josquin and Bach could do it,
so too could Arnold Schoenberg.
So let's continue with our presentation
of the permutations of the 12-tone row.
>> Inversion is like creating
a mirror image of the original row.
Each note of the inversion directly
matches up with the note of the series.
Okay, if the row goes up,
the inversion goes down.
If the row goes down,
the inversion goes up.
[MUSIC]
>> Together, they sound like this.
>> Then, we can get a harmony of
chords by doing row, with inversion.
>> Retrograde inversion is literally
just the inversion backwards.
[MUSIC]
>> All right, that's the theory.
Let's see how it plays out
in a real piece, and for
that we turn to a suite, a succession
of pieces that Schoenberg wrote for
piano in 1924 in the 12-tone idiom.
He selected a sequence of pitches,
12 pitches, to form his row,
and then as you can see here, rearranged
them in retrograde form, in inverted form,
and in retrograde-inversion form.
The row starts on E and works to B flat.
The retrograde, of course,
starts on B flat and
works its way back to the beginning E.
The row starts by moving up a half-step,
and then up a full step.
The inversion starts by going down a half
step and then down a full step, and so on.
Let's look at the score now.
So there is the trio section
of a minuet of the suite.
I've gone through it and
numbered the pitches in the row.
Obviously, that's what all the one, two,
three, fours, and so on, are about.
In the boxes, you can see all the various
permutations that Schoenberg applies,
retrograde, inversion,
retrograde-inversion, and so on.
And remember that the row can start
on any pitch within the octave.
Schoenberg likes to start it here, not
only on the pitch E, but also on B flat.
Well, with all this having been said,
let's hear the music, and
we'll follow along.
[MUSIC]
Repeat.
Second ending.
[MUSIC]
Second section.
First ending.
[MUSIC]
Repeat.
Second ending, and retard.
[MUSIC]
Well this is a short piece, but Schoenberg
wrote an opera that lasts three hours,
Moses und Aron,
using this same 12-tone technique,
and for a while, serial technique or
12-tone music was all the rage.
Even composers as different as
Igor Stravinsky and Aaron Copland
wrote in 12-tone style, but then,
in the 1970s, they all stopped.
And for the rest of us, the general
listening public, we never got going.
12-tone music never really caught on
with the general listening public.
Why?
Well, it went against the grain.
It went against nature,
as we'll now explain.