[MUSIC]
The challenge that Modernism places
before the general listener is
to open our ears and
accept a new level of oral dissonance.
And we have.
Much film music and much music by heavy
metal bands such as Metallica wouldn't
have been possible before the brittle
metallic sounds of Stravinsky and
the dissonances of Schoenberg.
But still, Schoenberg's version of
modernism goes against the grain.
It's unnatural in one important way.
It runs contrary to our notion
of consonants and harmony.
And not just in the western world,
not just in western music, but
in music all around the world.
Remember that the fundamental principle
of acoustics of nature
was the Overtone Series.
And that the earliest and
most primary notes of the Overtone Series
were consonant notes.
Here on the left,
we see the fundamental pitch.
And then, the first seven overtones.
And these overtones, along with
the fundamental, create a beautiful chord,
no matter on which pitch
you place the fundamental.
Notes higher in a series are dissonance,
but their volume is very little,
very slight.
So here, let me play these chords for you.
We can start here, fundamental.
[MUSIC]
Again.
Let me take it down an octave.
[MUSIC]
Or we can start the fundamental here.
Or we could start it here.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
And no matter what fundamental we
start on, we get this beautiful chord.
It's baked into the universe.
Composers for centuries in the west wrote
music based on consonant overtones.
Yes, dissonance was used, but it got
quickly pulled back into consonance.
Here's a Mozart dissonance
resolving to a consonance.
[MUSIC]
Here's one by Chopin
Again.
[MUSIC]
And actually, two, now by Gustav Mahler
where he has this configuration.
[MUSIC]
Pulling that dissonance back in.
No matter how long these dissonances hold,
eventually they get reeled
back into the consonants.
Consonance is like a load star,
it pulls the smaller moons back into it.
Schoenberg of course, didn't resolve
the dissonance to consonance.
He loaded up entirely on dissonance.
The emancipation of
dissonance as he called it.
But again, emancipation or
absolute freedom can be a problem.
Turns out, we like our world of
sound to be ruled by consonants.
Remember the very first piece we explored
in our course, Also Sprach Zarathrustra
of Richard Strauss and how it runs up and
along the overtone series?
[MUSIC]
Here we go.
And then momentarily falls back.
[MUSIC]
And focuses on two of the overtones.
Starting again.
[MUSIC]
We've only gone that far
along the overtone series.
And the point is that Strauss built
the beginning of this piece, Zarathustra,
on the harmonic series, and he did the
same thing in another piece, another tone
poem, of about the same period that
he wrote Death and Transfiguration.
Now, Death and
Transfiguration concludes in the same
key as Zarathustra begins in C major.
So in some ways, the two are a twin.
Here we see the overtone
series built on C.
All the blue pitches are consonants and
the red ones higher up in
the spectrum are dissonances.
And these, the red outliers,
are going get pulled in,
owing to the force of musical nature.
As we follow the graphics
here that I've constructed,
you'll see the blue consonants.
You'll see yellow pitches
that are mostly constant
because the composer walks his
theme along the harmonic series.
And from time to time we'll
see red dissonance pitches,
red dissonance of sound.
Schoenberg emancipates
the red dissonances,
allowing them to multiply and
take over the entire tonal universe.
Strauss never did that.
He never allowed that.
He stuck with the old, natural order
of things, the old natural universe.
As we'll now hear, by just watching and
listening as the red is
absorbed by the bigger blue.
[MUSIC]