[MUSIC]
Today we move from Modernism
to Postmodernism and beyond.
What's Postmodernism?
Well, obviously an artistic
movement that came after Modernism.
Now in our last session,
we saw how 20th century Modernism
was a reaction against tradition,
especially against traditional Romantic
music, the style that preceded Modernism.
Let's review these styles by period.
Romanticism, late romantic music,
the large, lush,
rich harmonic sounds of Liszt,
Brahms, Mahler, and Richard Strauss.
Impressionism, a precursor of
both Modernism and Postmodernism,
centered in the music of Impressionist
composer Claude Debussy.
Modernism, well we focused mainly on
the bracing music of Stravinsky and
Schoenberg.
And finally, Postmodernism.
We'll get to that later.
Let's revisit the sound of these
first three style periods by means of
an audio quiz.
I've got three piano clips teed up here.
As you listen, identify the period from
which each of these excerpts is drawn.
Is the music Romantic,
Impressionist or Modernist?
Let's play clip A.
[MUSIC]
Okay, now clip B.
And, finally clip C.
[MUSIC]
Did you identify these style periods?
Good.
The excerpts were, in order,
first, the Impressionist style,
you heard the glissandos in parallel
motion in a pentatonic scale.
Second, well that was music of Stravinsky
from the Rite of String, Spring,
with it's pounding dissonance.
And finally, the music of
the Romantic period represented
by Liszt with those lush chords.
They, they, they were all consonant.
And there's a deep bass sound
as you heard at the end,
demonstrating the expansion of the piano.
And again,
we'll get to Postmodernism shortly.
In our previous session on Modernism we
dealt mainly with the music of Stravinsky
and Schoenberg, as said.
It was invigorating, bracing,
brash, dissonant, difficult, and
sometimes disorienting.
It was also highly complex.
And this learned, difficult Modernism
continued after Stravinsky and
Schoenberg with the music of
Stockhausen and Berio and Boulez.
And this Modernism was based
in European musical centers,
in Vienna, Berlin, and Paris among them.
After World War II however, in the 1950s,
the center of the arts in the West
shifted, shifted to New York City.
When abstract painters such as
Jackson Pollock, and Robert Motherwell,
and Willem de Kooning, and
Mark Rothko gained prominence.
To suggest a sense of this, here
are paintings by Pollock, de Kooning, and
Rothko from
the Yale University Art Gallery.
Each painting is highly esteemed and
highly valued today.
At the same time these American artists
came to the fore, these American painters,
so too did American composers,
in New York City.
Of these, the composer of
perhaps most lasting importance,
judging from his continuing
popularity today, is Aaron Copland.
Now, as you see here,
Copland composing at a piano in 1962.
Copland was born in Brooklyn in 1900, but
he was trained in the European tradition
and studied under and
with the famous Nadia Boulanger in Paris.
Copland, almost like anyone who's
traveled extensively abroad,
came to see his own country
more clearly from a distance.
As Copland said in 1939,
in Paris we all discovered America.
What Copland discovered about European
Modernism was that it was too complex,
too difficult for most European and
American audiences.
It had no relevance to the average
American listener, especially during
the 1930s and 1940s, during the Great
Depression and the Second World War.
So Copland turned away to
a simpler kind of Modernism.
As Copland said at the time, and
here's the direct quote on this screen,
it made no sense to ignore them,
meaning the general listening public, and
to continue writing as
if they did not exist.
I felt that it was worth the effort
to see if I couldn't say
what I had to say in
the simplest possible terms.
So instead of complex European Modernism,
Copland turned to a more
listener-friendly American Modernism.
You might call it Modernism Lite, or
Modernism made simple and practical.
By way of example,
Copland created Fanfare For
The Common Man and Appalachian Spring
with its signature tune,
A Gift To Be Simple, that you hear
now playing in the background.
So, before moving on to Postmodernism,
let's explore Copland's Gift To Be Simple.
[MUSIC]