[MUSIC]
Let's get right into
Aaron Copland's Appalachian Spring.
It's a ballet score that he wrote for
the choreographer, Martha Graham, in 1944.
As we listen to the opening sounds
of scene one or tableau one,
I'm going to ask you to engage three
questions that you see here on the screen.
Where's the dissonance?
Is the dissonance up above,
in the higher pitches?
While, the consonants,
with its fundamental and
long, long held,
simple overtones, are down below.
Is the dissonance up above and
the consonant is down below?
Or, is the dissonance down in the base,
in the lower pitches, while the consonance
and the simple fundamental overtones are
sound up above, at a higher pitch level?
Question two,
does the dissonance sound immediately and
aggressively and is therefore displeasing?
Or B, does the dissonance unfold gradually
and is therefore not displeasing?
And finally question three.
A seemingly odd question I suppose.
Which of the pieces that we've studied,
Beethoven's Symphony Number five,
the opening of that the famous dum,
dum, dum, dum opening or
Richard Strauss's perhaps equally
famous also Sprach Zarathustra.
Does Copland's piece share much in common?
Which of these two pieces is the Copland
closer to Strauss or to Beethoven?
All right, those are our questions.
Now let's listen to the music
following the orchestral score.
Remember that in a modern
conductor's score,
the woodwinds are up on top, with
the flute usually in the highest part.
So here's our two flutes up here, and
then ours, we have our clarinet
there that we will hear.
So the high woodwinds are up here.
The strings are all down here
with the first violin in
particular playing high pitches over here.
So we actually have two high pitch playing
sets of instruments, first violins here
and the flutes and clarinets up,
up here above, so you have to watch that.
As for the low instruments,
well here we go all the way down here
with the low strings holding
low notes underneath.
Okay, that's the, the general layout.
Here we go.
We have Dawn Rising on a Spring Morning
on a Farm in Appalachia.
[MUSIC]
A clarinet.
Strings.
[MUSIC]
Now.
High first violins,
dissonant note there, low note.
[MUSIC]
Here.
Clarinet.
Low strings.
Flute and first violin together in unison.
[MUSIC]
Triad, played as arpeggio.
Trumpet will enter.
[MUSIC]
And now the flute solo melody.
Passing off shortly to the oboe.
[MUSIC]
Bassoon.
Oboe, descending.
[MUSIC]
And then lots of low notes.
Clarinet.
[MUSIC]
And that's where we'll stop at.
So that's the first tableau,
or the first scene.
And, as I hope you heard, the dissonance
is actually in the higher parts,
the first violin and the clarinet, and
sometimes in the flute, while the low
strings hold the fundamental pitch and
the earliest notes of the overtone series.
Dissonance above, consonance below.
That's the way music usually works.
And that's why we like this approach.
And you heard from the very beginning
here, the slow, relaxed tempo.
And thus, the dissonance doesn't sound
threatening, because it enfolds slowly.
The answer to question three.
Copland here is following a plan,
not like Beethoven's Fifth Symphony,
which represents an obvious theme or
motive.
You've heard Beethoven present dah,
dah, dah, dum, bah, bah, bum.
That's a theme in a kind of,
kind of bowls us over.
But what we've got instead is
something much more akin to beginning
of Straus' [FOREIGN] where
the fundamental note is way down here.
[MUSIC]
And starting to come up with the overtones
And then.
[MUSIC]
Then a little bit of dissonance begins to
creep in, in the upper, upper register.
So, notice here,
as we go to our next slide.
Notice here that Copland
is using polychords.
We talked about polychords before,
with Stravinsky.
Here we have one chord down here, and
another chord all the way up here.
[MUSIC]
Doesn't sound that dissonant
because they're spaced out.
And they unfold over time.
We could've had Copland do this.
He could've taken those two triads and
placed them right over top of each other.
[MUSIC]
And sound much more biting, but he spaces
them out in terms of time, slowly.
[MUSIC]
And in terms of registers,
spaced them out.
So for the average listener
the spacing over time and the spacing
over the sonic spectrum both low to
high creates a much more relaxed sound.
We won't say that it's more
pleasing than the Stravinsky,
because the Stravinsky is pleasing too.
Just in a different way.
So we've experienced two springs here.
Actually, we've experienced three
springs if we, if we count Vivaldi.
We've got Vivaldi's Spring Concerto
with its consonant spritely sounds at
the beginning of spring.
We have Stravinsky, and it sort of
bursts forth with energetic dissonance.
And the other, the third Spring
here is Aaron Copland's Spring,
which unfolds gently and gradually.
All right, now onto the most famous
movement of Copland's Appalachian Spring,
using the tune A Gift To Be Simple.
Surprisingly, Copland's tune,
which is now famous was not famous
before Copland got his hands on it.
He stumbled upon it and
he plucked it from obscurity.
He found it in a book of Shaker songs.
Now the Shakers were a religious
sect that had grown up
in the east coast of the United States
in the 19th century.
So Copland discovered this tune in a book
of Shaker songs published in 1848.
Here's how that original looks.
Notation's a bit different
than contemporary notation.
But, again, Copland's ballet music made,
this tune that you see on the screen,
a gift to be simple, made it famous.
Copland's music was arranged by
none other than John Williams and
it was even played at
President Obama's first inauguration.
Next, we see the tune in
its original version.
This is just a modern transcription of
what you saw in the previous slide.
And you can see that it's in four phrases,
and each phrase is four bars long.
And, if you look carefully we'll
see that it begins with a,
a classic statement of antecedent,
consequent phrase structure,
phrase a and phrase b,
followed by an extension.
We'll call that x, and then a return
to the concluding consequent phrase.
Phrase b in a slightly different form.
Okay.
So, let's see what this sounds like.
I think I've got it here at the keyboard.
Let me play this quickly for you.
And as we play, you'll notice that this
actually sounds a bit different than what
you might remember from the Copland.
So, here's the original.
[MUSIC]
Okay, so as we heard here we've got
this simple structure of antecedent,
consequent, extension,
and return to consequence,
it's a very classical,
classical structure.
It goes back actually to the Classical
period, because simple folk song structure
came to be adopted in the Classical period
with composers such as Mozart, and Haydn,
and Beethoven.
Beethoven, you should have of course,
as you know in the famous Ode to Joy,
a, b, x, b.
So Copland's music is modernist here,
not post modern.
It plays off of,
it plays against musical tradition.
There is indeed still a dialogue here
in Copland with musical tradition.
So Aaron Copland, he took this tune and
altered it just slightly.
Here's his version of this phrase.
And you can see here that Copland is now
writing it two four times, not four for
times, and he has the pitches
moving along briskly in 16th notes.
And there's a long pick-up, and
then a solo clarinet races off.
[MUSIC]
So now let's hear this entire tableau,
or scene, or
section seven, scene seven of the ballet.
But before we do,
let's take a look at an overview.
So here you see how we
have the Shaker tune
set out in it's 16 bar entirety.
First with the clarinet solo and
then a modulation.
And let me switch over here to
the cursor and the image on the screen.
So here's the tune here, and it unfolds
antecedent, consequent, extension,
consequent, all 16 bars.
Then we get a modulation.
Remember, modulation is like
a change of musical scenery.
We're going from one place, sonic place,
sonic home, sonic context to another.
We're going to modulate.
And I think we'll be able
to hear that the music
actually runs up to
a different pitch level.
A slightly higher pitch level then the
oboe, not the clarinet the oboe will start
all over again with the antecedent
phrase it will go for
four bars then the consequent phrase and
then all the woodwinds will come in and
finish that, this off.
So let's start out now,
let's start out now.
And I'm going to follow with my cue,
cursor here and
let's que the music and here we will go.
[MUSIC]
Four, two, consequent, two, two,
three, two, four, two.
Extension.
Two, two, three, two, four, two.
Consequent.
Two, three, two, three, two, four, two.
Modulation.
[MUSIC]
Oboe, two, two, three, two,
four, two, three, two.
[MUSIC]
Full woodwinds.
Consequent.
[MUSIC]
Okay now we're going to break
into a variation of this theme.
We've got theme variation form.
Notice as we've seen before
with barely for example.
The durations are double so
we have rhythmic augmentation.
What is now the theme is being brought
in an imitation against itself.
A little fugato,
a few light moments of imitation.
Starts out low.
Imitated a little bit higher up.
[MUSIC]
Okay, get ready for
another change of musical scenery here.
going to race up, new key.
Trumpet will lead the way.
New key,
now we're going the other direction.
The duration's are half.
The tempo is slightly faster so,
we've got rhythmic diminution
here with a trumpet solo.
[MUSIC]
Extension, with this part
of the melody up here,
now we're back to the consequent phrase,
now we're going to ratchet rhythmically
in the other direction, once again.
Rhythmic augmentation.
And the tempo is really slowed down.
And in just a moment we'll
hear the full orchestra
come in with a very augmented
presentation of the theme.
Here we go.
[MUSIC]
Notice the very strong bass.
Love this bass.
Mostly just walking down by step.
[MUSIC]
Why is it the tonic?
All right.
That's the end of that particular tempo.
And one final point,
how do we end this, how do we end this?
Well, let me, let me go over here,
and we're going to ask you a,
a couple of questions as we
see on the next slide here.
What kind of cadence do we
have here at the very end?
He's coming down in this fashion.
[MUSIC]
Do we get this kind of ending?
Well, that would be an authentic cadence.
Again.
[MUSIC]
Would be ended that way
supposing you did this.
[MUSIC]
Well that would be a surprise right?
So we, that would be a deceptive cadence.
Or he might have done this.
[MUSIC]
Which is actually what he called an amen
cadence because ever since the 16th
century all back, way back in the time of
Shakespeare composers would end religious
pieces in this fashion with one chord
[SOUND] a top soprano line being held.
[MUSIC]
In that fashion, so
it's called an amen cadence.
And then finally of course because it
is religious, he didn't get this out
of a playbook, or an ebook, or
an ordinal, he took it out of a hymnal.
So that's the signature movement
of Copland's Appalachian Spring
using the tune A Gift to be Simple.
Simple music for all.
Now things really get simple and
user friendly as we progress to
post modernism and minimalism.
[MUSIC]