[MUSIC]
What is style?
Well, likely the distinctive attributes,
the noteworthy characteristics
of any object or entity.
What two styles are represented here?
Well before us,
obviously we have architecture.
Architecture in the classical style,
classical antiquity.
The antiquity of ancient Greece and
Rome with its columns,
ionic capitals and triangular pediment.
And behind it is a representation
of a much more contemporary image,
the exaggerated face of film star, Marilyn
Monroe, created by artist, Andy Warhol.
Now, a movie star,
in this case Marilyn Monroe,
is something from everyday culture,
and so, too, is a tennis shoe.
Here we see an approximately 8 by
12 foot version of a tennis shoe
by this same pop artist, Andy Warhol.
What could be more commonplace
than a tennis shoe?
I used to wear Converse All Star
tennis shoes when I played basketball.
Everyone did.
So this is pop art, because it's popular.
Everyone can relate to it.
Like it as art or not.
It is also what we would
call postmodernist art.
Why postmodernism?
Well, postmodernist art is art
that has gone beyond, that has
gotten beyond the anxiety of influence of
modernism, and indeed of all tradition.
To understand modernists like Copeland we,
that we just heard a moment or so
ago, it's useful to know something
about traditional musical form.
It makes more sense to us if we understand
antecedent consequent phrase structure,
idea of the fugue theme and variations,
rhythmic diminution, that sort of thing.
With traditional painting, similarly,
it's helpful to know something about
perspective, and brush technique,
and visual symbolism.
But with postmodernism,
you don't have to know anything.
And everyone is equal.
In this case,
everyone is literally on an equal footing.
Everyone can be an art lover.
Everyone can be an art critic.
So, postmodernism embraces the everyday,
the mundane,
even the kitsch, and it glorifies it.
Now, here's a collage that,
that I've put together, a Warhol,
a Roy Lichtenstein, and
a Warhol composite.
Cows, cartoon figures, Campbell soup cans.
But, some of this down-to-earth art,
postmodernist art, can sell for
prices that are absolutely stratospheric,
as you can see by this next collage.
Why is this art worth so much?
Why is it art?
What is art?
Well, these are some of the questions
that postmodernist art and
music require that we engage.
At the very least,
postmodernist art asks us to stop and
pay more attention to the little,
minimal, everyday things around us.
[MUSIC]