[MUSIC]
Who's honored in the Lincoln Memorial?
Well, Abraham Lincoln, of course.
What is minimalism?
Well, equally obvious,
minimalist art is art constructed out of
only the most minimal about the material,
which, in order to generate length,
has to be repeated again and again.
So, minimalist art takes a line, a
gesture, a phrase and repeats it over and
over, either in the same position or
in a slightly different position.
Minimalism started in New York City
in the 1960s and 1970s with
such visual artists as Donald Judd and
Sol LeWitt.
Minimalism is a distinctive kind of
postmodernism, a subset of postmodernism.
Here's a minimalist construction by
Sol LeWitt, where simple lines and
primary colors are set out and
then go at right angles to one another.
In another LeWitt construction,
a drawing for
a wall in the Yale Art Gallery,
a very few, simple modules,
here rectangles,
grow to cover a larger space.
Minimalism in music began at
the same time, in the 1960s.
And although there was a percolation of
it in California, it was mostly again,
a New York City experience.
Two composers stand out in particular,
Steve Reich and Philip Glass.
As both Reich and
Glass have said at different times,
American composers in the 1960s and
70s didn't see the need to engage,
didn't see the need to do battle
with the European tradition.
There was enough energy in America itself.
So, the minimalist turned away from what
Glass called the creepy-crawly
music of Schoenberg.
And composed using
the simplest of materials.
And here's an example.
It's a piano reduction of the opening
piece of a suite of pieces for
chamber ensemble called
Glassworks by Philip Glass.
It's built on only triads and
basic seventh chords.
The arrows here indicate where repeated
music occurs, let me play just a bit.
[MUSIC]
Sounds pretty radical because
of the constant repetition.
But in the history of classical music,
there have been similar
examples of musical minimalism.
Remember this of course.
[MUSIC]
The difference here is that in the Bach,
we have more direction harmonically
in the functional chord progressions
that seem to be going somewhere.
The Bach is goal-oriented, teleological,
to use that fancy word again.
The Glass piece goes nowhere.
It sits in the moment.
It relishes the moment forever and
then abruptly stops.
It is not teleological but
more trance-inducing.
It's sort of hypnotic.
It creates a different kind
of listening pleasure.
Now here's another piece by Glass,
again from Glassworks, called Flow.
It has an additive quality to it,
as more and
more layers of sound,
are added to the texture.
Before we hear it,
let's analyze what makes it work.
Let me play again,
a bit here at the piano.
We start out with this sound.
There's a, [SOUND] a french horn,
I think, is up here playing this.
[MUSIC]
So we have just this repeated
note [SOUND] and then this.
[MUSIC]
And then, slowly.
Seventh chord will be introduced.
And then another one, but
another one going against it.
Opposite direction.
One coming down as one goes up.
[MUSIC]
And then he will double the tempo, and
run them both up and down simultaneously.
[MUSIC]
In that fashion.
So, let's hear a bit of the original
composition Flow, by Phillip Glass.
And as we do so,
as these arpeggios are going up and
down against themselves,
we'll look at this visual image.
Each of these squares is
a rectangle against itself.
You can study these rectangles or
these near images as the music plays.
[MUSIC]
Okay, now maybe we'll pause it or
fade it out here.
And this same kind of repetitive
pattern process is also paramount
in the art of British artist,
Bridget Riley.
Again, the emotional effect
is not teleological.
Tha art doesn't work to one, grand climax,
doesn't progress to a great
apotheosis climax at the end,
but rather, it's repetitive, it's
reiterative, it's trance-like in a way.
You can get lost in this art.
You can get lost in this music.
And here's another example
of minimalist visual art.
But actually, it's a musical score,
the score John Adams,
Short Ride in a Fast Machine,
but seen up close.
Is it minimalist art, or
a prescriptive musical score?
Well, it could be both.
Let's back out here just a bit.
Take a look at this score.
There we go.
And we see it as we hear the music here,
playing in the background.
It's going back, both forwards and
backwards, simultaneously, right side up,
and right side down, down.
[MUSIC]
Okay, and with that little bit,
that little teaser.
We'll move on to engage the music of
postmodernist composer, John Adams.
[MUSIC]