[MUSIC]
I like talking about the music of
John Adams because he's a friend of mine.
I had lunch with him about a year or
so ago.
In fact we go way back.
Nearly fifty years ago we were
in a class together at Harvard.
I was a fledgling graduate assistant and
he was a gifted undergraduate.
We even played on the same
softball team together.
Adams was very talented so I watched him.
I paid attention.
His composition teacher,
normally, was Leon Kirschner,
who had been a student of Schoenberg, the
famous Arnold Schoenberg in Los Angeles,
but in Harvard, John Adams seemed more
captivated by The Beatles than Schoenberg.
And he sensed that there were
fresh new sounds to be written.
Now, we just heard a bit of
John Adams lively instrumental piece,
Short Ride and a Fast Machine.
It's an early piece by Adam now.
It's almost 30,
maybe even more, 30 years old.
It's in a minimalist style, but in a style
more complex than most minimalist music.
Indeed, ironically,
Adam's minimalist music can be anything
other than minimalist in length.
He has written several full length operas,
Nixon In China, The Death of Klinghoffer
and most recently, Doctor Atomic,
to name just three.
Let's see how minimalist music or
expanded minimalist music might
inform an entire three-hour opera.
And we'll do so with a quick
look at Adams' Nixon In China.
Richard Nixon, 37th President
of the United States in China?
How could you possibly
make an opera out of that?
Richard Nixon was anything but
charismatic and
the focal point of this opera was to
be a diplomatic mission to China.
The beginning of the taunt between
the US and China, the thawing of
the Cold War in 1972,
how could Richard Nixon be exciting?
How could diplomacy be dramatic?
We need drama in opera.
How could minimalist musical style,
which is built on static reiteration and
repetition, move forward in a compelling
way to a compelling end
as every good opera must?
I'm not kidding when I heard the title of
this, Nixon in China I said this is nuts.
This will not work, but it does and
let me show you how it works
in just one scene in this opera,
in one recitative and aria.
The President's plane,
Richard Nixon's plane,
lands in Peking, now called Beijing.
Who knew?
Nixon walks out stiffly to be greeted
by the waiting Chinese dignitaries,
led by Chou En-lai.
On the left you see an historical photo
taken by the Presidential Press Corps
showing the actual arrival
of Nixon's plane in Beijing.
And here on the bottom right
is how this same scene
was recreated recently at
the Metropolitan Opera in New York.
As the plane lands, and
Nixon and his wife, Pat,
descend, a recitative begins.
[MUSIC]
You hear the repeated patterns.
Typical, minimalist music,
but there's more here.
[MUSIC]
There are other repeated
patterns going against repeated,
and a lot of syncopation, and
it's all happening simultaneously.
It's actually very complex.
Maximal minimalism we'll call it.
Adam's music always sounds intentionally
slightly out of phase with itself.
Beginning to hear pulsating triads.
Hear it rising in the bass there.
[SOUND] And they will come up triad
like passing to a trumpet sound.
And here comes the royalty
of the president.
[MUSIC]
[APPLAUSE]
Nixon descends.
Chou En-lai greets him.
[MUSIC].
And hear them pulsating
minimalism in the background.
[MUSIC]
They exchange pleasantries.
Kissinger slumps down the stairs.
[MUSIC]
Mostly just speech.
Musically, but plain speech.
Okay, maybe we'll pause it right there.
That's enough to give us a sense of
the recitative that the stage for
the aria that follows.
Aria is entitled News Has
a Kind of Mystery.
The libretto for this opera was
created by poet Alice Goodman.
Remember, except for Wagner, composers
have almost always had a literary
person fashion or
generate the libretto for him or her.
And here's the text that
Alice Goodman created for this aria.
It's written in blank verse
with an occasional rhyme.
News, news has a kind of mystery when I
shook hands with Chou En-lai on this bare
field outside Peking just now.
The whole world was listening and
then periodically we'll hear lots of text
repetition for emphasis and emotion.
That is part of, of, of an aria,
as opposed to a recitative and then again,
for emotional impact,
long moments of melismatic singing,
where the soloist will take branch out,
hold forth on just one
syllable to express emotion.
Okay, with this quick
look at the text now,
let's go on to hear this aria
News Has a Kind of Mystery.
[MUSIC]
Repeated text.
Really only two chords pulsating in there,
just rocking back and
forth between the two.
[MUSIC]
We said of course.
Listening.
[MUSIC]
Is one.
As we, transfixed, made history.
So that recitative and
aria together takes nearly ten minutes.
And I think we'd all agree that
they make compelling drama.
And show that in a creative
mind like that of John Adams,
it would be possible to sustain
the minimalist aesthetic over
the course of a long and
very pleasing opera.
[MUSIC]