[MUSIC].
So here we are, at the last segment
of the last session of our course
Introduction to Classical Music.
Today we live in the second
decade of the 21st Century.
And from our vantage point it might seem
like classical music is on the decline,
playing less and
less a role in public life.
There's less teaching of music in the
home, less music education in the schools,
and less about classical music on
the front page of the newspaper.
But there are hopeful signs today.
Technology is changing things.
Ticket sales for high-definition HD
broadcasts of the Metropolitan Opera
are being sold.
Executed around the world.
A hundred years ago, you had to buy large,
expensive, acoustic instrument, Piano.
Today, most people are more
likely to have this gadget.
A keyboard synthesizer.
The fidelity isn't as good,
but it's small, portable and
you can do a lot of things with it.
A hundred years ago to
hear a classical concert,
to hear classical music you
had to go to a live concert.
Nowadays, all you have to do
is reach in your pocket and
pull out one of these things.
The fidelity is as not as good,
but it's small and
portable, and
you can do a lot of things with it.
It used to be that to have
a university course in classical music
you had to go to a university,
enroll as a student.
Now, well, nowadays as we have seen
you can do that within the comfort and
convenience of your own home.
At last count nearly 50,000
people had watched all or part.
Of the material here on our course,
"Introduction to Classical Music."
.
That's more people that I've taught
in my entire career here at Yale.
And we did that with just one course.
Here's another change.
Western classical music is no
longer just a Western phenomenon.
Today there are people from 187 countries
around the world watching the sessions of
this course on western classical music.
The largest number is
in the United States.
The second largest number,
by country, is in China.
And here's a modern concert
hall in central Beijing
in which western classical
music is completely at home,
as you can see by the large western
style organ situated over the stage.
But some new concert halls
are also being built
in traditional western centers of culture.
Another hopeful sign for
the future of classical music.
Here's the newest one.
It just opened in Paris, 2015.
The new home of the Orchestre de Paris.
This new surround sound design
makes the listener feel like he or
she is right in the middle of things.
This is like having a ringside
seat at a boxing match or
a basketball game, except here
everyone is quiet and listening.
So this is an exciting development for
classical music.
Here you could more easily
bond with the performers and
tacitly with the members of the audience,
re-affirming your cultural values.
But what are your cultural values?
Are there such things as
universal cultural values?
is music a universal language?
Should music be experienced
in a group setting
to re-affirm cultural values
in a concert hall, or
ultimately does music speak to us
most intensely when we are alone?
What do you think?
We've had an entire course
now on classical music.
What have we learned?
A lot of facts, surely and
I hope we've gained insights as to
how classical music works and
how composers communicate meaning.
But, ultimately, when we listen to music,
what music means is what the listener,
you and I, wants it to mean.
And one of the beauties of art, is that
each receiver of art can derive meaning
from his or her personal experience.
In this case, and
make sense of the mysteries.
Of the beautifully organized sound.
Mysteries of sound as beautiful
as the universe itself.
So let's try a final thought experiment.
I want to place you alone
with a piece of music.
In deep musical space.
The composer's name and
the title will appear on the screen.
Where does this music come from?
Is its frame of reference medieval music,
or modern music, or post-modernist music?
Does it evoke sounds of
popular music in any way?
Or perhaps, music from another world?
Finally, what does this music say to you?
What thoughts come into
your mind as you hear this?
Where do you see yourself being?
Where does your memory go?
What emotions do you
experience as you listen?
Why, perhaps, do you experience?
Interesting questions, all.
Having said this, I'll say no more.
Let's just listen now in the dark
to just two minutes of pure music.
[MUSIC]