[MUSIC]
Dreaming, by Robert Schuman,
and what a lovely melody.
So today,
we're going to talk about melody.
And, how long did it take old
Schuman to think up that idea?
Probably not very long,
judging from his work habits.
That kind of creativity is another
of the mysteries of the arts and
music in particular.
How does that happen?
But, on to melody.
In music, melody is the star.
A melody, simply said, is the tune.
A coherent collection of
pitches animated by a rhythm.
It literally gets top billing.
It's up there on the top
of the musical firmament,
and it's almost always on the top of the
musical texture, top of the musical score.
The harmony underneath it acts
like a supporting character,
the harmony plays
a supporting role to melody.
Here's the Schuman again,
now played on another kind of keyboard.
[MUSIC]
Notice, melody on the top and
the right hand.
Harmony, underneath it, in the left.
When we listen to music,
most of us hear music only as the melody.
We don't focus on the inner parts or
the bass.
There may be an acoustical reason for
this.
High pitches may be more easy to perceive
than lower and potentially murkier ones.
I can play a melody with
accompaniment here in one range, and
you can hear it rather clearly.
[MUSIC]
But, if I take that same melody and
play it all the way down here.
[MUSIC]
It gets a little bit murky.
Higher frequencies, we shall see,
disappear more quickly.
But, they sound more clear.
So, the melody sounds clearly above and
for
that reason we tend to
hear it more readily.