[MUSIC]
A melody, as we have said, is a coherent
collection of pitches animated by
a rhythm and
usually supported by a harmony.
We can simply remember a melody or,
in the western tradition,
we may wanna write it down, capture it,
preserve it, using musical notation.
Written notation of melodies in the west,
again, goes back to the ninth century.
We talked this a little bit last time.
Here are a few images showing how pitch
notation developed for western music.
So on the screen to the left side you see
an early manuscript with neumes up above,
just squiggles, and with some letters
representing both pitch indication and
the Latin text of this particular chant.
On the right we have
the text of the chant and
then the neumes,
the prototypes of our musical notes.
As you can see on the next slide,
here we begin to get
horizontal lines to help us with pitch
indicators, a grid of some sort,
that allows us to specify particular
pitches, and you can see off to the left
hand side there the letters C and F,
indicating where the pitch C and F appear.
On the right side we begin to see these
neumes become increasingly separated, and
now, as mentioned last time,
with a different symbols to indicate
the rhythms that are involved.
In the next slide,
we see that system of a grid supporting
pitches being confirmed
in four red lines there.
And on the right we see it
progressing to what we have today,
five lines on the stand,
again with pitch indicators out there to
the left to signify what those
particular pitches are supposed to be.
Moving on to the next slide,
here again we see more signs for
clefs indicating what those lines on
which the notes sit are meant to be.
On the left,
we have a very deluxe manuscript from
my own Yale University rare book library.
And on the right a sort of,
we'll call it, a more middle level
volume for an average music
consumer of the 16th century.
But again, we have a time signature there,
we have pitch indicators and
the notes sitting on a grid.
Finally, we're going to come to
an example of some printed music.
A volume here,
actually by Martin Luther on the left,
with his famous hymn tune [FOREIGN]
there,
and you can see Martin Luther's
name actually on the printed copy.
And this is the soprano part,
and we see that same
music on the right now with all four
parts set one on top of the other and
the music ending up towards
the bottom right there.
[MUSIC]
So that's the way our notation developed,
and at the very end as you heard again.
[MUSIC]
What Martin Luther is doing there
is simply coming down the scale.
Right down the scale.
So let's talk about scales for a moment.
Scale in music is simply a pattern
of adjacent pitches going up or
down the keyboard.
Different cultures have different scales.
Much of Chinese music is written in a five
note scale, so called pentatonic scale.
[MUSIC]
That sort of sound.
Indian Ragas sometimes
use a six note scale.
[MUSIC]
That's a six note scale used by
Ravi Shankar in a piece called [FOREIGN].
Melodies in western music, however,
are written not in patterns of five or
six pitches, but
in scales of seven pitches.
Did you ever wonder why we in the west
have seven pitches in our scale?
And why there's an irregularity
in the western keyboard?
Why there is no key at two
spots on the keyboard.
If you look here on the screen you can see
that we're missing an effective black key
between B and C, and E and F.
How did this come about?
It has to do with the way the ancient
Greeks back in the time of Plato and
Aristotle set up their melodies.
They privileged mathematics
above all else, and
as a result,
we end up with seven pitches in our scale.
A class video will explain
how this happened.
Okay, so we have this whole
idea of octave duplication,
sometimes six notes, sometimes five notes.
We in the west have settled
on a seven note scale.
Why did that happen?
Well, we had this idea
of a seven note major
[MUSIC]
and seven note minor.
Why seven notes?
Well for the answer to that we have to go
back to ancient Greek music theory, and
you read about this,
it's really turgid stuff.
But believe it or not, I teach a course
on this at the graduate level.
We have to read and
poor Linda has to take this kind of stuff.
We're reading Aristoxenus and
things like this.
So what we're dealing here with is
a situation where the ancient Greeks were
very much into mathematics as
a way of explaining the world and
explaining music in particular.
And they thought these
ratios were primary,
so they had the ratio of two to one, which
gave them the octave, and three to two,
which gave them the fifth, and
four to three, which gave them the fourth.
They also, because the system worked
out better for their purposes,
then jumped to nine to eight,
which gave them the whole tone.
So they started out there and
let's say they're working down here.
They filled in the octave up above,
and then they filled in the fifth, and
then they filled in the fourth, and
then they came down a whole step.
Then they went up a fourth from that whole
step and then up a fourth from that,
and they were filing in, in this fashion.
Interestingly enough, and
you ever wonder this?
Sometimes someone wandered by a keyboard,
said that's odd.
What's the great oddity
about the keyboard?
What's strange about this keyboard?
It's very asymmetrical, right?
Marcus?
Yeah it's missing some notes in there.
It's missing something in here.
Well what these are were the cracks.
After the Greeks laid out their fifths and
fourths and whole steps they
had these little leftovers.
They called them lainmas, and they had
these little leftovers in there, and
that's why we end up with these
small distances between B and C.
[MUSIC]
That's a big step.
That's a small step there.
So the scale is actually not equal.
A to B is one distance,
which is a large one, and
B to C is only half that distance, and
that's because of the way the Greeks laid
this thing out with their two to one
ratios, three to one ratios and so on.
But in any event, we end up with this.
Now, the Greeks had a whole series of
patterns, and they called them myxolydian
and hypomyxolydian and Phrygian and
hypophrygian and stuff like this.
A lot of different patterns, but
in the course of history, we settled,
beginning in the 16th and
17th Century down into just two patterns.
What we call the major pattern and
the minor pattern.
So, let's talk about that just for
a moment,
and before we do it I
should add one other thing.
How, then,
do we get these other notes up here?
Well, what we know call the black notes,
although historically
keyboards could be either way.
You could have these added notes,
black or white and
then these underneath would be black.
So we fill these out.
Sort of in the 14th century
all of this got filled in.
These between B and C and E and F didn't
get filled in because they were already
just the smallest amount that they
wanted to deal with, just half steps.
So we end up here within an octave,
we end up with 12 equal pitches.
But we still use this term of seven note
scale, cuz we have seven notes within
the scale of the major scale and seven
notes within the scale of the minor scale.