[MUSIC]
Our class video showed us how it came
about that we in the west have a seven
pitch or seven note scale.
It was given to us by the ancient Greeks,
owing to their love for
mathematically pure musical intervals.
They used math to explain the entire
universe, including music.
The Greeks had several
different kinds of scales, and
you heard all their funny names
there in the class video.
And this held true for about 2,000 years.
But by the 17th century, Western
musicians had reduced these down to just
two kinds of seven pitch patterns,
a major pattern and a minor pattern.
The major pattern went this way.
[MUSIC]
And the minor this way.
Each follows a particular pattern
of steps on the keyboard.
You can look all this up in your textbook
to see what the two patterns are.
Whole and half steps.
The smallest distances on the keyboard.
But the important thing
is to hear the keyboard.
And hear the major and
minor when played on the keyboard.
[MUSIC]
Major.
Ever notice on a piano that we have two
pitches that sound rather identical?
Almost,
[MUSIC]
The same thing.
If we start on this pitch.
[MUSIC]
Go up and down the scale,
we get that arrangement.
If we start here,
[MUSIC]
A-B-C-D-E-F-G-H.
No we don't have Hs.
Why don't we have Hs?
[MUSIC]
A-B-C-D-E-F-G.
Because this is duplicating,
in essence, the one down below.
Octave duplication.
[MUSIC]
The eighth note is the same as the first.
Therefore the eighth note's
simply called the octave.
You know about octaves.
You've been hearing them all of your life.
I'm gonna sing a pitch.
And you're going to sing the octave above.
I'll do one first and then you do one.
I'll take this.
[SOUND] Okay, now you do one.
[MUSIC]
There we go.
That's right.
[SOUND] So we have the octave in our ear.
This is the two to one ratio that we
discussed before, in our first session.
The upper pitch,
the octave above is vibrating.
My vocal chords here
are vibrating twice as fast.
[SOUND] As the lower octave.
[SOUND] The eighth pitch of the scale
duplicates the first pitch.
Eight and one are the same and thereafter
all of the intervals are the same.
[MUSIC]
The intervals In that higher octave that
I just played are exactly the same as
the lower one.
For this reason we have only
seven letter names in the scale.
A-B-C-D-E-F-G, no, H-I-J-K-L-M-N-O-P,
because we start all over again.
This is the phenomenon
of octave duplication.
And it is part of nature not nurture.
Octave duplication is at work in
musical cultures around the globe.
Whether in Chinese music, Indian music,
Indonesian music or African music.
So we in the west have
a major scale pattern and
a minor scale pattern,
each with seven different pitches.
But the distance between the adjacent
pitches in those two scales
is not the same.
The major and minor scales involve
two different sequences of intervals.
Again, an interval of music is simply
the distance from one pitch to another.
In each major and minor scale
there are five adjacent intervals
that we call whole tones and
two intervals of half tones or half steps.
Think of the scale as a ladder with rungs,
but
as you go up the ladder five of
the rungs are a foot apart and
two rungs are just six inches apart.
So here are our ladders and
they're irregular.
But if they are irregular blame
the ancient Greeks who put
mathematics ahead of symmetry.
Why is this important?
This whole and half step business?
This idea of rungs of different
sizes within the scale?
Well, it's because of the position
of the half steps within the scale
that makes the major scale
sound the way it does and
makes the minor scale
sound the way it does.
Here is the beginning of
the major scale ladder.
[MUSIC]
And here's the beginning
of the minor scale ladder.
[MUSIC]
All major scales sound the same way
because they have the same pattern of
whole and half steps.
All minor scales sound the same way for
the same reason.
We can begin a major scale, or a minor
scale, on any pitch of the keyboard.
We can move the pattern,
transpose the pattern, as it is called,
to begin on another pitch.
[MUSIC]
Scales are extremely important
when listening to music.
Far more so than we realize.
We've grown up with scales.
Even if you've never had a moment
of instruction in music theory and
you've never heard of the idea
of major scale before today,
I could prove to you that
know a great deal, a lot,
about scales because you've been
hearing them all your life.
So I'm gonna begin to play here,
and you finish off a major scale.
So here we go.
La, la, la,
la, la, la.
See there?
Good.
You did it.