[MUSIC]
Finally, there's a third
type of scale in the west.
One that is neither major, nor minor.
It's the chromatic scale.
Instead of using just seven
pitches within the octave,
the chromatic scale uses
all 12 possible pitches.
Well, wait a minute, you say,
I thought we only had seven pitches
in the scale that the Greeks gave us.
That's basically true.
But in the course of time,
particularly during the 14th century,
the rungs of what we call
the white keys of the keyboard.
The whole steps came to be filled
in with additional half steps.
Here you can see them being filled in.
Notice that the two short rungs of the
ladder couldn't be filled in between E and
F, and B and C.
Those are those little gaps that
we heard about in the class video.
They couldn't be filled in
because there was no space.
So we had seven pitches initially and
gradually added five more.
Here, the black keys, to get us to
the total of 12 that we have today.
Okay, back to the chromatic scale.
The Greek word chroma,
from whence we get chromatic,
the Greek word chroma means simply color.
And indeed this is a colorful scale
because it has more pitches in it.
On the screen you see
an ascending chromatic scale
with the added pitches
indicated by a sharp sign.
Below, let me play that
[MUSIC]
So that's the ascending chromatic scale.
Below you see the well known
White Christmas written by Irving Berlin.
[MUSIC]
Notice that it's only
the beginning of White Christmas.
[MUSIC]
That is chromatic.
Indeed, only very rarely
is an entire piece written
in the chromatic scale
from beginning to end.
Usually it's just a portion of
the piece that's chromatic.
Irving Berlin begins here,
as we heard with chromaticism and
then returns to a rising major scale
[MUSIC]
Chromaticism adds richness, and
it can add tension to the music.
Here's how Mozart used chromaticism and
the chromatic scale in his
Requiem Mass to build tension.
[MUSIC]
So here he was coming up the scale,
minor scale,
then last little bit is all chromatic.
Here's how Beethoven used
chromaticism going the other way.
Coming down the scale.
[MUSIC]
Descending a chromatic scale.
So that's what chromaticism does.
It adds richness, variety, and
often tension to the music.
Or it releases tension from the music.