[MUSIC]
Scales in music provide
an oral context for us.
They tell us where we are in the melody.
Oddly, most of the time when we listen
to music, we aren't aware of this scale.
Particularly those two little
half steps that are in the scale.
But a scale provides something akin to
a global positioning system for us.
A musical GPS for
recognizing where we are in a melody.
If I play or sing this for you,
You can sing the next note.
[MUSIC]
There, [SOUND].
You've intuited that we have in this
little piece that we've created here.
A major scale and
you have intuited where we are in that
scale, indeed where we should go next.
To the bottom, at note one.
Using our scalar GPS,
we recognize the grid, the scale.
And we have oriented ourselves within it.
Indeed, when we listen to music,
our brain orients us automatically.
Because we've been brought up
with music that works this way.
We now process music instantaneously,
indeed
subconsciously because that's part of the
musical nurturing that we have received.
It's part of our musical template that
we talked about in our first session.
And a final point About
the scales that make up melodies.
Scales encourage us to feel
a particular way about the music.
Generally speaking in Western music, we
associate happy, bright sounds with major.
And sad, somber ones,
possibly exotic ones, with minor.
And we've been doing this
since the 16th century.
Here's a piece by Robert Schumann.
[MUSIC]
It's called The Merry Farmer.
Here's one, as we heard, by Chopin.
[MUSIC]
Major happy, minor sad.
But there's nothing in the physics
of music that causes this to be so.
Indeed it's culture.
I recently spent a week in Poland,
in Krakow, Poland, and
I was surprised to find how
many of the dance tunes,
the happy dance tunes of
the Polish people we in minor.
So it's not nature it's nurture.
Let's have a little fun here and
see if we can change things and
if we change things up, how we can
change how we feel about the music.
And we're gonna throw in a new term here,
we're gonna throw in the term mode.
We have a major mode scale and
a minor mode scale.
So let's go back to our image now with the
scale of the major pattern on the left,
labeled major mode, and
the scale of the minor on the right.
Notice the bottom left that
the major mode has a large interval
at the very beginning.
And that the minor mode has
a smaller one at the beginning.
That's why the french who first coined
the terms majeur and mineur in the 17th
century called this one on the left
the larger, major, majeur.
Here's a familiar happy tune.
But now it's been switched.
Well we'll make it switch here.
So here we are with
the familiar holiday tune.
[MUSIC]
And now you can see at the arrow
I'm gonna switch it up.
[MUSIC]
Well not much joy there, how'd we do that?
Well, I just lowered the third
pitch of the scale by a half step,
changing it from the major
mode to the minor mode.
We can do the same thing
with You Are My Sunshine.
[MUSIC]
It doesn't sound very sunny.
Same thing with Happy Birthday.
[MUSIC]
That doesn't sound very happy.
All we're doing there.
[MUSIC]
Just lowering that first
third of the scale.
So that first interval of a third in
the scale is very important in determining
the mode, major versus minor.
If we change the mode from major to minor,
we change the mood of the music entirely.