[MUSIC]
How do you create a great melody?
Well if I knew I wouldn't be sitting here.
I'd be on Broadway composing musicals or
in Hollywood writing films,
just shaking great music out of my sleeve.
Indeed, no one knows what
makes a great melody.
There's no magic formula.
And because of the number
of pitches in the scale and
the many rhythms to which they can be set,
there's an almost limitless number
of melodies that can be created.
Although there's no formula or recipe for
making a great melody, there are,
however, some commonalities among them.
Almost all melodies in western music,
as we have said, are written in
either a major or a minor mode.
All melodies have a sense of tonality,
they are organized around
a primary pitch or tone.
That primary pitch is called the tonic.
The tonic is always the first
note of the scale, and
because of octave duplication,
it's also the last note of the scale.
We can go up to the tonic, or
we can come down to the tonic.
Up to eight down to one.
Here's a melody going up to eight,
an old Scottish folk song.
[MUSIC]
You hear it going up to eight, the tonic.
Here's a melody where we go down,
down to the tonic.
[MUSIC]
So there we come down to the tonic.
When we make or we hear music,
we hear the tonic.
Here's twinkle, twinkle.
[MUSIC]
And of course we can all
sing that tonic pitch.
How is it that we feel or hear the tonic?
We do so because subconsciously, again,
we are mapping a scale, either major or
minor as we listen and instinctively
we know where we are in that scale.
And where it begins and
where it ends, on the tonic.
All melodies end on the tonic,
one way or another.
The word tonality, and the word key
are used interchangeably in music.
I'm in the tonality of C,
I'm in the key of C.
Doesn't matter which you choose,
either way, you're using a scale, major or
minor, beginning on C.
So a scale, and a sense of the tonic of
the scale create a sense of tonality,
a general context for pitch,
a sonic landscape, if you will.