[MUSIC]
When we communicate we do so
in sonic form.
Spoken words.
If we want to record what we said or
what we're thinking we can
write it down as words.
Strung together,
these individual words form phrases, and
taken together,
the individual phrases form larger units.
Sentences.
And sentences form paragraphs, and so on.
That's how language is constructed.
The same thing happens in
the language of music.
Pictures can be joined
to form musical phrases
that can be joined to flesh
out a complete melody.
To demonstrate this, we turn to
a simple melody, one from the famous
Broadway musical, Oklahoma, by Rodgers and
Hammerstein, Oh, What a Beautiful Morning.
Let's look at it.
Here we see the melody, and
we'll talk mostly about the melody here.
Next time we'll talk about the harmony.
So the melody is on top,
where we would expect it.
The harmony is below in the chords
that are holding there.
The rhythm is in a meter, triple meter,
three-quarter notes to each measure.
The measures come in
symmetrical units 4 plus 4.
Two short phrases make a longer phrase.
One of eight measures.
Then come two more short
phrases that are similar but
not identical to the first eight.
Notice too that our melody
stays pretty much within
one octave with the tonic pitch,
on either end, high and low.
Finally, notice that the first long phrase
doesn't end on the tonic but
the second long phrase does.
The first long phrase opens the music,
the second
phrase closes it back down away home,
is another way of thinking
of this auditory experience.
Musicians, however,
tend to use a fancier term.
Instead of a way home structure,
they say antecedent and
consequent phrase structure.
Let me play this for you.
So here is our antecedent,
or our away phrase,
[MUSIC]
Not ending on the tonic.
That's the end of the antecedent,
or away phrase.
Let's go back home.
[MUSIC]
So there we are.
Back home, and in the tonic.
But whatever you call it, a way home, or
antecedent consequent phrase structure.
This structure is quite common in music.
You hear it everywhere.
Be it in the Broadway show
tune that we just heard,
a pop song, or in a Beethoven symphony or
a Puccini aria.
As we'll hear shortly in
one of our later sessions.
Antecedent and consequent phrase structure
is endemic to melody in all Western music.
And one last point about melodies,
some are easy to sing, some are difficult.
The New York Times recently ran a story
about the difficulty of singing
the American national anthem,
the Star-Spangled Banner.
At the beginning of sporting events,
this is where we usually encounter
this in the United States.
What makes the Star Spangled Banner or
any melody difficult to sing?
Usually it's the amount of jumping
around in a melody that causes it to be
easy or difficult.
The more leaping or jumping,
the greater the difficulty.
Here's a very easy melody.
Easy because the pitches are one
right next to the other.
[MUSIC]
Here's a more difficult one in a different
kind of notation, a graphic notation.
Actually, it's another Broadway show tune,
written in New York City in 1908 and
it's something of an anthem also.
An anthem for American baseball.
Take Me Out to the Ballgame.
Let's play that just to
remind you how it goes.
[MUSIC]
And you can see visually and
hear orally how difficult, or
how many jumps this thing has.
It's difficult.
But maybe we've heard it so
many times that we've just
gotten used to the difficulty.
Now let's look at this
visually by comparing
Take Me Out To The Ball Game with
another well known melody, Ode to Joy.
Which Beethoven composed and
incorporated in his Ninth Symphony.
So here comes Ode To Joy.
And here's the way it goes,
I'm sure you know this too.
[MUSIC]
Notice there that all the pitches
are right next to each other.
We call a melody with many leaps such as
Take Me Out To The Ball Game a disjunct
melody.
We call one that moves smoothly up and
down the scale a conjunct melody.
Take Me Out To The Ball Game, disjunct.
Ode to Joy, conjunct.
Disjunct, conjunct.
The two melodies are very different.
But each has been with us for a long time.
In a way, each is a classic.
But both have a clear sense of scale and
a sense of the tonic and they are both
made up of units of four bar phrases.
And both involve antecedent and
consequent phrase structure.
But let's see how melodic phrase structure
plays out in this Beethoven melody.
Again, we're going to stay with
the famous Beethoven Ode To Joy.
Which today serves not as
the anthem of American baseball but
as the anthem of the European Union.
And to do this we turn
now to a class video.
>> So melodies can be conjunct or
disjunct.
And possibly the most conjunct of all
melodies [COUGH] in the history of music
was the melody that we looked at very
briefly in the first gathering and
that is Beethoven's famous Ode to Joy.
Now, once again, Beethoven was in his 50's
when he was working on his last symphony
or proved to be his last symphony.
His ninth symphony and
he'd been tinkering with this particular
melody all the way back to, probably 1803.
So it's about 20 years or so.
The ninth symphony is 1823, '24.
As early as 1823, we know he's working on
>> [MUSIC]
>> Trying to get this to work just right.
And eventually, over this 20 year period,
he did get it to work just right.
Let me swing this board around.
Here's the famous melody.
I've put it in the key,
it's called the bass cleft here.
And it's in a major key.
We don't need to know what the particular
notes are, but let's look at this just for
a moment because it works well
as a prototype of melody.
It does something that
a lot of melodies do.
First of all, as you can see by
the trajectory here, it's very conjunct.
Neighboring notes here.
If you look at the German in the text
it has to do with [FOREIGN].
Millions B embraced.
And this, I believe is the sort
of the national anthem for
the United Nations, so this has to
be something that we can all sing.
And if you have conjunct motion,
that makes it easier.
It's also very symmetrical.
As you can see, it's nothing but
a pattern of four bars plus four
bars plus four bars plus four bars.
And as we said before, music has a syntax.
So that these phrases have to be arranged
in a particular way that makes sense.
So we start out here with an opening
phrase, ya, ta, ta, ta,ti, ta, ta, ta, ta,
ta, ta, ta, ta, ta, tam.
Is that the tonic, ta tam?
>> Down.
>> Can anybody sing the tonic?
>> Yeah, yeah, [SOUND].
The tonic is actually over here,
it's a little bit lower than that.
That was a really hard question,
I'm amazed anybody got it, good for you.
So what happens here is this
opening phrase that we'll call A.
Musicians like to label stuff just with
alphabetical labels to keep it simple.
We'll call this phrase A.
It sort of opens things up.
And we refer to this as
the antecedent phrase.
The next phrase, B,
[MUSIC]
is very similar.
But here it takes the deviation
[MUSIC]
and gets it back,
gets us back to the tonic.
Now we could walk out the door
at that point, right?
We're feeling totally stable there.
We've got it all together for
the rest of the day.
However, it would be
a pretty short melody.
So what he then does
is write an extension.
We'll call this C.
[MUSIC]
Very interesting, put an asterisk by this.
Beethoven, in a way, saved this melody,
he rescued this melody
which was in danger of becoming
excessively four square by doing what.
If I had been writing it.
Da da da da da da da da.
Da, da, da, da.
What did Beethoven do here, we talked
about it last time, a rhythmic device?
Syncopation.
He brings his opening note,
that F sharp, in a beat early.
This should, you would think, be a half
note and this would start on the down beat
over here, but he brings, in effect, the
sound of the down beat in a beat early.
Gives it a little bit of pep
there at that particular point.
And then what is this here?
[MUSIC]
Well of course, it's a replication of B.
We've got to end on the tonic.
All pieces, classical or pop,
one way or the other end on the tonic.
Okay.
So let's have us now, let me put
a fermata over this, let's all sing this.
We don't have to read the notes,
you don't have to sing any text.
We're just going to sing la.
I'll conduct in four.
So sit back
[MUSIC]
Everybody vocally prepared here?
Here we go.
I'll give you one, two, ready, sing.
La, la, la, la louder louder, la,
la, la, la, la, la, la, good.
La, la, la, la, la, la,
la la la la la la la la la.
la, la, la, la, la, la,
la, la, la, la, la.
La, la, la, la, la, la, la, la,
la, la, la, la, la, la, la.
We'll put a big ritard on it there.
So, we wanted to bang that syncopation,
and then of course,
there's no sound on the downbeat
here to make the syncopation work.
So that's the melody, seems very simple,
but it took Beethoven a long time to sort
of iron all this out, make his perfect
melody, the prototypical melody, in a way.
>> And contrary to what my Doppelganger
on the screen in that class video said,
this is not the anthem
of the United Nations.
It's the anthem of today's European Union.
And indeed, it has a great deal to do
with the history of contemporary Europe.
In 1989, the Berlin Wall fell.
And the world, at least the free world,
[LAUGH] celebrated that event.
And they celebrated it with
the music of Beethoven.
And the principle conductor that was
brought to Europe at that time to lead
this singing of the Ode to Joy around
Europe was actually an American,
Leonard Bernstein.
So we're gonna end with
Leonard Bernstein conducting
an orchestra in a German
speaking city of Vienna.
Just a portion of a professional
group singing Beethoven's Ode to Joy.
[MUSIC]