[MUSIC]
Today we'll be talking about harmony.
The piece you just heard was
the piano part a work by Beethoven.
It has a melody yes, but
the element that gives the music it's
richness is the accompanying harmony.
Here's the melody alone.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
It's fine, though the rhythm might
possibly be a little bit repetition.
But now here it is again with the harmony.
[MUSIC]
As Beethoven himself is
reported to have said in 1810,
every thought in music is
ultimately related to the whole of
the harmony which is oneness end quote.
Well, here's a wildly different
way of thinking of it.
In the 1990s, a recruiting slogan for
the US Army famously said quote
be all that you can be end quote.
Harmony supports the melody and
allows it to be all that it can be.
Now here's another piece for
piano one by Chopin, a prelude by Chopin.
In the image on your screen you see
the melody in the red above, and
the harmony,
those are the notes underneath.
Let me play that.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
Melody above, harmony below.
Chordial accompany below.
Harmony seems to be very important
in music, and indeed it is.
But here's a question for you.
How many musical cultures around the world
do without harmony, almost entirely?
Actually most of them do without harmony,
or at least without much harmony.
Here's a rendering of the Adhan.
The Islamic call to prayer, sung around
the Muslim world five times a day.
But it's done without any kind
of accompanying voices or
instruments, without any sort of harmony.
Let's just listen.
[MUSIC]
All of the beauty of this
music lies in the melody.
And indeed in all the subtle
gradations between pitches and
what the singer does by way of varying the
intensity when he has landed on a pitch.
In a situation such as this,
likely the addition of harmony
would only obscure the chant and
obscure the beautiful melody.
Now some traditional music from Africa,
recorded in the country of Mali.
Again, there is little in the way
of accompanying harmony here.
There's just a call and
response melody sung between two ladies,
with drums pushing the rhythm forward.
[MUSIC]
So some musical cultures,
particularly those that of the East,
emphasize highly nuanced melody and
those of Africa and
African influenced
South America emphasize rhythm.
On the other hand, Western pop music and
Western classical music
prefer these sorts of sounds.
A melody plus a rich accompaniment.
Here's that Chopin prelude again.
Actually in the 1970s pop
singer Barry Manilow turned
this Chopin prelude into a pop hit,
It Could Be Magical.
[MUSIC]
And again, and so magical indeed.
Magical because of the harmony.
Harmonies are built upon
simultaneously sounding
aggregates of pitches called chords.
A chord is simply a group of two or
more pitches sounding at the same time.
Let's watch a class
video to see how chords,
specifically those chords called triads,
are built.
And how they form a foundation upon
which a melody can be constructed.
Let's talk for a moment about chords.
What's a chord?
Well a chord is just a simultaneous
sounding of two or more pitches.
That's a very basic,
general definition of a chord.
And a chord can be,
of course [SOUND] consonant or
it can be [SOUND] dissonant.
So let's stick with just consonant chords.
We'll be working with
consonant chords today and
the most fundamental of the consonant
chords is this idea of the triad.
This figure that we call the triad.
It's the building block really of all our
harmonies whether it's pop or classical.
And we're gonna use a lot
of pop music today and
we'll be pointing out triads
there in this pop music.
So what's a triad?
Well, obviously you get the idea
of three pitches, three pitches.
How does it work?
Let's go over to the keyboard and
the staff here.
Let's say we've got a scale.
And we do have a scale, C D E F G A B C,
and I wanted to construct a triad above
each of these notes of the scale.
Well, this happens to be a C,
middle C here.
So a triad is going to have three
pitches and it spans five letter names.
And we go one letter name,
two letter names, three letter names,
four letter names, five letter names.
We take one, three and five.
Here I'm taking C, skipping D,
taking E, skipping F, taking G.
And it gives me this three note aggregate.
Take one, skip, take one,
skip, take one, [SOUND].
And we can do the same thing.
[SOUND] And so on,
right up the scale in that fashion.
Notice as we said before,
we've got this scale,
we've got some notes rather important
in the scale, tonic is very important.
We said [SOUND] the leading tone is
important, so with chords and triads.
Some are very important.
The tonic is very important and
this dominant.
What we call the dominant.
It's not really the most important.
It sort of leads into,
pulls into particularly
important setting up the tonic.
It's the next important,
right below that is the subdominant.
It often pulls into the dominant which
then pulls into the tonic in that fashion.
So we would get this idea
of here's a chord here.
[SOUND] There's the tonic,
here's the dominant, [SOUND].
There's the subdominant,
[SOUND], and there's the tonic.
We can flip this just a little bit.
We could say alright
here's our tonic up here.
[MUSIC]
And go that way, tonic,
subdominant, dominant, tonic,
[MUSIC]
That way.
So we could come up from the tonic,
or go down from the tonic.
Generally speaking, composers are more
likely to go down from the tonic
than come back up to the tonic than
they are likely to go the other way.
So we've got these three basic
chords we're gonna talk about.
There are others there that
we've built on the second and
seventh degree of the scale, but
these are the most important.
And it's surprising how much music these
three basic chords can accommodate and
with all the things.
[MUSIC]
Dominant, tonic, dominant, tonic, finally,
Subdominant tonic,
[MUSIC],
dominant, tonic.
[MUSIC]
So a lot of music is made in that fashion.
So as the class video said we get a lot
of musical mileage out of just these
three chords.
[MUSIC]
So think about this the next time you
listen to music whether classical or pop.
I think you can hear the very least of
difference between the dominant and
the tonic chords.
[MUSIC]
Tonic, dominant, tonic, dominant, tonic.