[MUSIC]
Okay, so that's how chords work.
Let's talk more about these triads,
those essential building blocks of music.
We have three primary triads, as said,
the tonic, built on the first degree,
the scale, the dominant build on
the fifth pitch of the scale, and
the subdominant built on the fourth
pitch or degree of the scale.
These chords account for a surprising
amount of the harmony that we hear.
Let's take a common tune, Jingle Bells.
Let me just play Jingle Bells and keep
the chords steady underneath, the triads.
[MUSIC]
Tonic.
Subdominant.
[MUSIC]
Dominant.
Tonic.
So those triads keep changing
underneath the melody.
But why do they change
underneath the melody?
Why can't we just harmonize the melody
using one chord, one triad?
Well, if we did, here's what would happen.
[MUSIC]
And so, doesn't really work, does it?
We violated one of our
rules of musical syntax.
Harmony must change to fit the melody.
As a melody moves through the pitches
of the scale, it moves in and
out of the pitches at different triads.
If a melody pitch is part of a triad,
we have a consonance.
But if it moves out of that triad,
then we heard a dissonance.
We have a dissonance.
So the melody much change to be harmonious
with, sound good with the melody.
When triads change,
bringing a consonance support to a melody,
they build up a certain momentum,
they come in a purposeful way,
a purposeful march, that works in sync
with the direction of the melody.
Chords moving in this purposeful fashion
create what we call a chord progression.
They seem to pull along,
one to the next, moving toward and
eventually arriving at the tonic,
the tonic triad, the home triad.
Let me play a chord progression.
[MUSIC]
So that's a very straightforward
chord progression.
The end of a chord progression
is called a cadence, a fall,
the final move, built possibly on
the fourth degree of the scale that
goes to the fifth degree of the scale
that ultimately moves to the tonic.
As you can see on the screen
here called four, five,
one or subdominant, dominant, tonic.
Same sort of thing.
Let me play that for you.
[MUSIC]
So that's a cadence, a fall to the end.
Remember that flashy end of the opening
Richard Strauss's Zarathustra from our
first session.
It ends this way.
Remember this melody?
[MUSIC]
But the final cadence goes,
That's just another cadence,
another end of the musical phrase,
end of a passage with a chord progression.
Often in classical music,
the composer will signal the termination
of a piece by alternating five and
one triad, dominant and tonic triads.
It's a very simple cadence, goes this way.
[MUSIC]
Something like that.
The end, the end, the end.
You might just as well hold up a sign.
Hold up a sign like this.
The end.
So you can have a visual
sign that conveys meaning.
These letters allow us to generate
a sound that conveys meaning.
A word is part of a language.
Or you can have a musical sign
that also conveys meaning.
Music, too, is a language of music.
The end.
This kind of fifth degree to
tonic degree or one degree, five,
one cadence moving tonic to
dominant again or subdominant,
dominant, tonic is called
an authentic cadence and
is most common in Western classical music
and equally common in Western pop music.
Here's another kind of cadence,
it's called a deceptive cadence.
Here the composer fools you,
makes you think that you're going
to go home to the basic tonic.
But he sort of kidnaps you and takes you
away somewhere else by substituting at
the last moment another point of arrival
for the tonic that you expected.
Let me play a deceptive cadence here for
you.
Let's see.
[MUSIC]
Oh, that wasn't expected.
Or it could go,
[MUSIC]
Oh, that was even more unexpected.
So although you've been
aurally kidnapped here,
spirited away somewhat unexpectedly to
a new musical chord, there's good news.
You will be rescued.
A piece that moves to a deceptive
cadence invariably will
work its way back to the tonic.
After the deception,
the piece has to keep on going until it
reaches some kind of authentic cadence.
Almost all music has this
kind of happy ending.
Having been deceived by the musical world,
the musical traveler must
now arrive back at home.
So after a deceptive cadence,
[MUSIC]
Maybe continuing.
Ending up with some sort
of authentic cadence.
There's a third kind of cadence to which
we apply the nickname amen because it's
used in much religious music, particularly
music of the hymns of the church,
the ending of hymns, and
hymns in universities as well.
They're sung at commencement or whatever.
An amen cadence is one that
you'll likely recognize.
It moves from a chord build on the fourth
degree of the scale to one built on
the first degree of the scale.
[MUSIC]
And you can here people
singing the Hebrew word amen.
Finally, the last of our four
cadence types, the half cadence.
Here the music just seems to stop,
specifically on a dominant chord.
The music seems suspended,
but at the same,
it implies that we have to move on more.
Maybe we should call it
then a pause cadence
because that's really what it wants to do.
It pauses momentarily freezing the action.
Hold it right there, and then it moves on.
Let me play a half cadence.
Let me see if I can find that
Beethoven that we heard earlier.
So here's the Beethoven,
he's coming along.
[MUSIC]
And you want to hear,
And indeed, he gives us that.
But that moment we pause there, that's
a half cadence, that's a pause cadence.
So let's review, with me playing
a standard chord progression.
Indeed, the Pachelbel Canon Harmony, and
I'll work through all four cadential
types in one way or another.
Let me try this.
What key?
Let's try this key.
[MUSIC]
Mm.
Well, that would be our deceptive cadence.
We could try it again.
[MUSIC]
Just stop there, and that would be
our pause cadence, our half cadence.
Or we could continue on.
[MUSIC]
Come back home, that'd be our
authentic cadence, or we could go,
[MUSIC]
So cadences have their own
emotional vibe to them.
But they also help tell you
where you are in the music.
If you hear this,
[MUSIC]
Or this.
You know darn well that you're at the end.