[MUSIC]
>> In the background,
you hear playing another famous melody,
the aria O Meo Babino Caro, from
Giacomo Puccini's opera premiered in 1918.
It's been used in many ways,
as a background score for
TV commercials, films and the like.
It's a favorite, not only of opera lovers,
but of video game lovers too.
It was the background music for
the first edition of Grand Theft Auto,
of all things.
But why this popularity?
Let's take a look at it.
I'm going to simplify and at the same
time switch to a concert grand.
All right, let's have a demonstration
now with the four cadence types we
have been discussing.
Authentic, half cadence,
deceptive cadence and amen cadence and
we're going to do it in a famous area
from an Opera by Puccini [FOREIGN].
So let's start here, you know the melodies
I'll use all different sorts of
things around the world.
[MUSIC]
So here we are at the end of the first
phrase ending on a half cadence.
Well the half cadence we're not settled.
We want to be here.
So we're singing here.
That requires of course
that the melody continue.
[MUSIC]
And we expect it to go here but
that's not what he does.
What he does is this.
[MUSIC]
See there, now when we have a deceptive
table set it requires that we push on,
we can't end here, we gotta end back on
the time, we gotta do as they would say in
the airplane world, we gotta do a flyover,
so here comes a musical flyover.
[MUSIC]
Now we are back home on our timing.
And he is not quite satisfied with that,
he's going to extended it
just a little bit, orchestra comes in,
then the voice comes back
[MUSIC]
So notice there at the end
we get our amen cadence.
[MUSIC]
So again, couple things to note here.
First, our traditional, antecedent and
consequent phrase structure.
[MUSIC]
That's the antecedent,
opens things up, we go away.
Now we gotta pull that back in,
come back home.
[MUSIC]
but surprise there's a deceptive cadence,
you've got to push on then.
[MUSIC]
And we could stop there,
but he doesn't allow us.
To do that he wants to extend
it just a bit further.
[MUSIC]
With that amen sound.
And there's a reason for that.
Has to do with the text.
And we'll explain that back in the studio.
Why the Amen Cadence there at the end?
The sound of the church at the end?
Well it works well with
the notion of a need for mercy.
Have mercy.
Hear the character [FOREIGN] the soprano
voice, is asking her father for mercy.
The words at the end
are oh father have pity.
Have pity.
[FOREIGN] We can even think of the,
be atop Michael Angelo's in St.
Peter's in Rome.
So, a religious ending here.
An Amen ending might be
entirely appropriate.
Obviously, this is a beautiful melody.
But the rich harmonies and
the varied cadences, they too also
make this an effective composition.
A classical favorite as we've said.
This is a quick analysis of this famous
aria, but let me make one final point.
When we analyze music we have a tendency
to suck all the joy out of it.
And we don't want to forget
that this is beauty,
there is much beauty in this music and
we should focus on that.
Analysis of the sort
we've been doing here,
is just a help mate to understanding
how the beauty is created.
In truth, when we listen, there
are three kinds of listening that go on.
Analytical listening, technical listening,
and emotional listening.
First, analytical listening.
Simply said, what's going on?
Well that's what we just worked through
with our quick analysis of the harmony and
the cadences in the Puccini aria.
Then there's the technical.
How well's it going?
How are the performers doing?
In this case,
how well is the singer singing?
And then, finally, there is the emotional.
How do I feel about the music and
the performance of it?
We won't, mustn't forget this
latter element, the emotional.
These are gorgeous sounds in
this aria by Puccini, and
we mustn't be afraid to say just that.
So let's listen to this beautiful aria
one last time, just for pleasure.
You can find you favorite recording
of it on YouTube or iTunes, Spotify,
but let me start by playing mine
with the incomparable Renee Fleming,
singing O Meo Babino Caro.
Enjoy.
[MUSIC]