[MUSIC]
As we have seen, just as we have major and
minor scales so to we have major and
minor triads.
Let's review just for a moment.
Let's create a C Major Scale.
Scale beginning on the pitch C.
Now, let's add some thirds to it,
intervals of thirds.
Above each of these
pitches to create triads.
All of the triads build
upon the scale with
one exception that we need not go into,
is either a major or a minor triad.
Here's what they look
like now on a keyboard.
Major on top, minor beneath it.
Notice that we have two perimeter pitches,
the outer edges, the outer pitches.
And it's really only the center pitch,
the middle note that varies
from one triad to the other.
To create a minor triad for
example we simply move the middle
pitch down a half step.
Move it, in this case, from E down to
E flat, as you can see by the arrows.
[MUSIC]
But the immediate shift between major and
minor triads is something
of a sensual sensation.
It's sensational.
Play this again, this way.
[MUSIC]
Or, this way.
Composers have recognized
this over the centuries.
One of the best examples is to be found
in a piece by the American composer
John Adams.
We'll deal with the music of Adams at
the end of our course when we get to
modernism and post modernism.
But for now let's just listen to what he
does in a work called Black Gondolas.
It was inspired -- Adams
piece was inspired,
by the 19th century Composer Franz Liszt.
Who in turn was inspired by
the image of a black coffin
that of his son-in-law
composer Ricard Wagner.
When Wagner's body was transported
from Venice back to Germany in 1883,
a long story we don't need
to go into in any detail.
Anyway, let's just listen to
the rocking of the gondola here.
We'll perceive it that way
because of the rocking,
or at least the alternation back and
forth between major and minor triads.
Again, John Adams, Black Gondolas.
[MUSIC]
Major, minor,
major, minor,
changes pitch level,
major, minor Major.
Minor.
Again, another pitch level change.
Major, and so on.
[MUSIC]
Very beautiful.
But it's really just built on
the alternation of major and minor triad.
This same emotional tug-of-war,
this yin and yang between major and
minor, can also be felt in
a famous piece by Beethoven.
The first movement of
his Moonlight Sonata.
You see the score on this screen.
Beethoven has written a melody and
an accompanying harmony.
But instead of playing the accompanying
harmony as block chords,
block triads,
he plays the notes in succession.
Playing the notes of a chord in
succession instead of all at once creates
what's called an arpeggio,
derived from the Italian word, arpa.
Harps do a lot of this sort of thing,
arpeggio.
Let me play one for you.
[MUSIC]
So to be here, but we can spin
out these notes as an arpeggio.
And that's what Beethoven does at
the beginning of his 'Moonlight Sonata'.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
But these sounds of Beethoven deserve
the richness of an old Steinway piano,
so let's turn to that.
[MUSIC]
Towards the end of the passage,
you get a sense of what Beethoven
might have been intending.
Lets imagine that we were
outside on a moonlit night.
Clouds intermittently block
our view of the moon.
But as they do so the umbra of
the movement is alternately light or dark.
Let me see if I can play this now on
an electronic keyboard over here.
[MUSIC]
Minor.
Major.
[MUSIC]
Minor.
And so on it goes.
So that's how major minor triads work.
By the way, this lovely movement
Is only the first movement
of a three movement sonata,
a three part sonata.
We'll talk about sonata
later in our course.
But let's see how arpeggios
are used in the final movement.
Here arpeggios race up and
down the keyboard.
[MUSIC]
Now I made hash of that just then but
it reminds me of a personal story.
When I was about 20, studying piano
at the Eastman School of Music,
I realized that I could never play this
piece of to speed without breaking down.
And that was an aha moment for me.
I knew that at that point,
I'd better find another line of work.
That I was never gonna make a dime as
a professional concert pianist, and I did.
Anyway.
Anyway, you'll enjoy watching someone play
this a bit more correctly than I'm able
to, and certainly able to now.
As we turn to a YouTube clip,
the last movement of Beethoven's
famous Moonlight Sonata.
[MUSIC]
Minor.
Major, arpeggio, racing up.
[MUSIC]
Playing that was like an exhilarating
ride on the back of a wild stallion.
Unfortunately for me,
most of the time I fell off.
[LAUGH]