[MUSIC]
As mentioned, when most of us listen
to music, we listen to the top line,
where the melody resides.
That's where the clearest and
most memorable music is to be found.
But to hear the harmony and
the structure of the piece it's
best to get down with the base.
Chords are build upon a base pitch.
The base determines
the foundation of the chord and
the direction of the harmonic progression.
Some pop musicians such as
Paul McCartney and Sting, well,
they sing the melody at the same time
they lay down the basis of the harmony
by playing the electric bass,
the electric bass guitar.
To hear the base and
to begin to focus on the harmony,
let's build out three musical examples.
We'll start with a piece that
has only four chords in it, but
they repeat over and over so that
makes the harmony even easier to hear.
Any harmony or melody or
even rhythm that repeats again and
again is called an ostinato, from
the Italian word meaning obstinate thing.
The piece in question is an old
favorite of mine from the 1960s.
It features voices,
this style called doo wop.
Here's what the bass sings as
you can see on the screen.
[MUSIC]
And of course we can add chords to that.
In that fashion, notice major,
[MUSIC]
minor,
major,
[MUSIC]
major triads.
And then it just keeps on looping.
[MUSIC]
Now, let's listen to
a bit of this recording.
Notice that a new chord
comes on each downbeat.
That's one of the reasons, as we've said,
that we hear these as downbeats.
Chord changes often signal downbeats.
So why don't you sing along as we enjoy
Gene Chandler and the Duke of Earl?
[MUSIC]
Great fun.
All right, so you're now fully qualified
to join an a cappella doo-wop group
because you can sing the baseline and
track the harmony.
But let's move on to a more complicated
example of hearing a harmony
from the realm of classical music.
Likely, you've heard of this piece also.
It's the Canon of Johann Pachelbel,
Pachelbel's Canon.
The term canon in music is
simply a fancy word for round.
A piece in which one voice starts out and
then the others duplicate it exactly,
as in the well-known Three Blind Mice or
Row, Row, Row Your Boat.
With Pachelbel's Canon,
we have a double delight,
because although there is a canon,
or round, in the upper three parts,
the canon is supported by
an ostinato bass underneath.
A harmony that repeats again and again.
Let's talk first about the bass.
Here it is on your screen
at one pitch level.
But I'll play it actually at a pitch
level that Pachelbel wrote it.
[MUSIC]
Okay, eight chord ostinato bass that
repeats over and over and over.
So let's now focus on the upper
three parts of the score.
Again, as produced courtesy of our
California friend Steve Malinowski.
You don't have to read or understand
the specifics of musical notation to
get a sense of what's going on here.
Pretty simple.
One voice, the leader, starts out,
and then the other voice follows along
immediately thereafter,
at the time interval of one measure,
playing exactly the same thing in terms
of rhythm and pitches as the leader.
And then the third voice comes in and
does the same.
That's what creates the canon or
the round.
The irony is that in the Pachelbel Canon
you don't hear the canon, or
at least it's not as
obvious as one would think,
because all three of the upper parts
are played by the same instrument.
They're assigned to the violin, so they
have the same musical timbre or sound.
They're in the same range.
They're sort of right
on top of each other.
So there's no separation
of the individual parts,
which makes it difficult for
the listener to actually hear the canon.
But if we look at the music as we listen,
we can see the unfolding of the canon.
Let's watch.
[MUSIC]
Bass line with implied
harmony being played above.
Now, leader voice.
[MUSIC]
Follower one.
Follower two as leader goes
on to play quarter notes.
Shorter vowels.
[MUSIC]
Follower picks up the quarter lengths.
As follower two picks
up the quarter lengths,
reader goes on to play eighth notes.
[MUSIC]
Follower one, eighth notes.
Follower two picks up the eighth notes.
[MUSIC]
Hey, heads up because the leader's
going to begin with 16th notes.
[MUSIC]
Gives the impression that they're all
[INAUDIBLE] but the music is gathering
momentum, even though the tempo is
completely stable, completely steady.
As you can see by the pulse
of the notes above.
Finally, the most sophisticated
example yet, of harmony,
a piece by JS Bach,
a prelude for keyboard.
Here, ironically, there's no melody.
There's just a harmony.
[MUSIC]
But what he's done is taken
those chords of the harmony and
spread them out as arpeggios.
[MUSIC]
This independent harmony does not repeat.
It's not an ostinato bass harmony,
as in our previous two examples.
It unfolds continually.
This is one long chord
progression in the tonality of C.
And I might add that
the original version of this,
arguably one of Bach's most famous
pieces and in Bach's hand, for
the most part is actually in our
own Yale University library.
Bach was trying to teach his first child,
Wilhelm Friedeman Bach, how to play and
how to compose and
here's the way it originally looked as
you see on the left side of the screen.
The hand on the upper left,
that's the hand of the son,
Wilhelm Friedemann, and
Bach came along and
tried to move things along by
just prescribing chords that
should be played toward
the bottom right of the score.
With the implication that they were
to then be executed as arpeggios.
So, again,
this is Bach's harmony without any melody.
But, more than 100 years later
a French composer, Charles Gounod,
came along and
added a melody to Bach's harmony,
the two together being even more rich and
pleasing than Bach's original harmony.
A text was added to it, Ave Maria,
turning it into a religious work,
the Bach Gounod Ave Maria.
And Bach's piece,
originally just a harmony,
is sung today at weddings and
funerals around the world.
In the YouTube clip that
you're about to hear,
Bach's harmony is being
played on the piano.
And you will see Gounod's
melody as a score.
I will play the melody, so
we've got YouTube playing the harmony and
I'm playing the melody.
YouTube is playing Bach,
I am playing Gounod.
Let's see if we can pull this off.
[MUSIC]
Darn.
[LAUGH] Almost a shame to stop,
but we've got to.
So, there we were,
we were hearing the best of both worlds.
Bach's original harmony
supporting Gounod's later melody.
Pretty amazing.