[MUSIC]
Notice today I'm not playing the piano but
the violin.
Haha, actually just kidding.
I don't really play the violin.
This is my daughter's violin.
But I did go to a lot of violin lessons
during the 12 years that she studied it.
I am holding the violin because this
session is devoted to tone color.
Primarily, the colors or
sounds of the instruments of
the Western symphony orchestra.
The music we will be listening to and
indeed music that we just heard,
was by Rossini, his William Tell Overture.
There are trumpet and
french horns, and then violins.
Ever wonder why one instrument
sounds differently than another?
Okay sure,
they're made from different materials and
have different shapes, and
that really is the answer.
But the sound coming out of these
instruments is actually different.
It has to do with the acoustics of music,
and
that's what I'd like to explore for
a moment.
Let's go back to a topic that we broached
in our first session, the overtone series.
Remember, when a column of air is
vibrating within the chamber of
a musical instrument, inside a flute or
trumpet, or a string is vibrating,
as on a violin,
many subparts of that column or
that string are also vibrating,
as we see in this diagram.
This shows the whole
string vibrating in red,
halves of the string vibrating in blue,
and thirds of it vibrating in green.
Now let's look at these same subsections
in a different way, standing them upright.
The lowest pitch is on the left,
that we call the fundamental.
That's the one that we actually hear,
it's basic sound.
And the successively smaller sections
of the string are to the right.
They're the overtones.
We hear them, but only very,
very faintly, almost subconsciously.
Okay.
Freeze that idea.
Because we're going to go, work in
another concept, and that is volume.
All musical sounds have a pitch.
Also, sounds have a tone color,
or timbre as it's called.
And they also have a volume, or loudness.
Let's think of pitch as sound waves
operating horizontally, you have big sound
waves, which create low pitches, and you
have small ones that create high pitches.
But let's focus on volume for
just a moment.
We have these loud sounds and
we have soft sounds.
These are usually displayed vertically.
Loud ones go way up or down.
Soft ones up or down just a little bit.
To see this, let's return to our
Beethoven's Symphony Number Five, and
to the active listening guide that
accompanies it at the website that you
may choose to accompany this course.
Here, we see a scale of amplitude,
as it's called.
Amplitude is simply the measure
of loudness, louds spike.
With soft sound,
the needle doesn't move very much.
[MUSIC]
So watch the amplitude bars begin
growing here, begin to expand.
[MUSIC]
Then control.
Expand with the loud sections.
Contract.
Low volume, but it's beginning to grow.
And you can hear this crescendo.
And you can indeed see this crescendo,
because the amplitude bars increase.
[MUSIC]
Driving the final point of loudness and
sudden disappearance of sound.
Okay, now let's combine these two ideas,
pitch and volume.
But before we did do that,
I need to say one more thing.
All musical instruments generate
the same overtone series.
All overtones are halves of
the fundamental thirds of
the fundamental fourths of
the fundamental on down the line.
Again, we hear them only faintly,
but each instrument, the trumpet,
the violin, the oboe, whatever,
generates a different amplitude for
each of the overtones within the series.
The instruments have different patterns
of amplitude and these different
patterns determine the difference
in tone color of the instruments.
On the screen you see
the diagram of a violin.
Shows the overtones for the violin.
Now, the vertical bars not only reflect
the overtones moving left to right,
but also the loudness, the amplitude for
the instrument of each overtone.
Notice as we proceed down through the
overtones it's not a straight line decent.
Some of the overtones pop up quite loudly,
and others are very quiet.
And it's this mixing of loud overtones and
soft overtones, yet all these are very,
very quiet, mind you.
It's this mixing that creates
a particular tone color or
timbre for the instrument,
just like at Starbucks.
The coffee meister will mix a different
blend of coffees from different regions of
the world to form a holiday blend or
a bold, or whatever it might be.
So to here,
we have different amplitudes of
the different overtones creating
a distinctive tone color, or timbre.
Lets compare the overtone chart
of a violin to that of a trumpet.
You can see that's different,
again here, violin is on top,
trumpet is on the bottom.
Now watch a demonstration of how overtones
work on a trumpet as they are added in.
My friend Ed Doering at the Rose Hulman
Institute of Technology in Terre Haute,
Indiana created this and
has allowed us to make use of it.
Remember, in the discussion here,
frequency here refers to pitch,
amplitude to volume, and here, he uses
the word partial to refer to overtone.
Musicians and scientists use the terms
partial, a part of a string or part of
a column of air vibrating, and overtone,
partial and overtone, interchangeably.
On this demonstration, zero is
the fundamental, that's the sound we hear.
One the first overtone,
two the second and so on.
Watch as this scientist
creates the sound of
a trumpet in the lab by building
up the overtone series.
>> Here's an illustration of this
technique applied to a short burst on
a trumpet.
I'm indicating the frequency and
amplitude trajectories, and then I can
by using the slider, add or
subtract partials to build up the sound.
>> First [INAUDIBLE]?
>> This is only with the first partial.
And then we can see
the corresponding amplitude of our
sine domain signal quite nicely.
Here we see that the frequency
has a little bit of a, a jump at
the beginning transient, but it's mostly
[SOUND] the same frequency throughout.
So now I'm adding the next
partials at a higher frequency.
[SOUND].
This is the next one yet, even higher
frequency and as you look at the amplitude
you notice that the onset of the higher
frequency partial is a little bit delayed.
[SOUND].
>> Now is he adding in all the overtones?
>> So again you see each of these higher
frequency partials has a little bit of
a late entrance but
then they also decay faster as well.
>> Pretty cool.
The more the engineer adds in overtones,
the more we come to realize the instrument
in question is, in fact, a trumpet.
If he put them in using other proportions
of loudness, he could make this sound
like a clarinet or an oboe, and that's
what an electronic synthesizer does.
And that's what we have here.
On a synthesizer you can push a button and
program a particular amplitude series
to set up the sound of the strings,
for example, and then hit a key and
you get the sound of the instrument that
you've chosen, whatever instrument
you want to have produced.
You have in effect the entire
orchestra at your disposal.
Now let's see what I've got
over here at the moment.
[MUSIC]
Okay, that's programmed with the overtone
series of a modern grand piano.
Let's see if I push this button
over ,here what do I get?
Who knows?
[MUSIC]
Some kind of electronic organ.
Let's try this one.
[MUSIC]
That's a string sound.
String orchestra.
To sum up, in music it's the amplitude or
loudness of the various overtones
created by an instrument that produces
a particular blend of sound, and
thus the distinctive tone color or
the timbre of that instrument.
Miraculously our brain processes all
of this complicated information about
overtones and amplitudes and
tells us in a split second hey,
that's the sounds of a trumpet, or
hey, that's the sound of a violin.