[MUSIC]
Western classical orchestra is made
up of four primary families or
groups of instruments.
The strings, woodwinds,
brasses, and percussions.
Let's start with the string family.
In it we have the violin,
the slightly larger viola,
which sounds lower than the violin,
the cello and the double bass.
The double bass is called the because
early on in the 17th and 18th centuries,
that's essential what it did,
it doubled the bass line down an octave
below what the cellos were playing.
Strictly speaking,
the double bass is the descendant of the
old Viol family of stringed instruments.
Which had a slightly different
tuning of the instrument.
And we'll come back to the Viol
family when we get to the music of
the Renaissance.
But the double bass is still
very much a stringed instrument.
The cello is in baritone range
of the strings, in the mid base.
It can play high or low.
It's my favorite stringed instrument.
When I die, and get reborn, reincarnated,
I'm coming back as a cello.
No, just kidding of course,
but I do like that sound.
The sound of a well played cello
In its mid to upper range
is indescribably beautiful.
Well here in a moment a clip
of Yo-Yo Ma playing the cello.
And here's a photograph of him that I took
at a concert in New Haven some years ago.
Later I met him at the Tanglewood
Music Festival in the summer.
He's very smart and very funny.
Anyway, here's Yo-Yo Ma playing a bit of
the Saint-Saëns Carnival of the Animals.
The video part here isn't very good but
it's been viewed by more than two million
people on YouTube so the sound,
at least, must be awfully darn good.
[MUSIC]
Notice that as Mister Ma was playing,
his left hand was shaking constantly.
Was he nervous?
[LAUGH] No, with that kind of talent,
there's no reason to be nervous.
He was of course,
using a playing technique called vibrato.
It makes the pitch oscillate ever so
slightly actually,
a pure anything in music
is not as exciting
as something that is slightly off and
slightly on, off an on, and off and on.
It yields a richer emotional experience.
Let's listen now to a second
video clip of the same piece.
Notice here how Yo Yo Ma ever so
slightly slides into the pitch,
again giving us the sense of
a little emotional tug, and
how the tempo slows down and
then speeds back up here and there.
And again, notice how these slight
imperfections, quote, unquote,
create expression in music.
This is how a great performer
communicates emotion to us.
[MUSIC]
Gosh so beautiful.
Would if we could all do that.
Well we've heard a cello playing
a beautiful melody with bravado,
now we turn to another class
demonstration, using not a violin, but
the slightly larger and
slightly lower sounding viola.
Here we learn about other string
techniques in addition to vibrato namely
pizzicato and tremolo.
[MUSIC]
>> Well,
you did something there at the end,
did you have too much coffee this morning?
You started shaking
>> Probably, my hands.
>> So tell us about what you
were doing there at the end.
>> So there are all sorts of
different little technique things
you can do to create different colors and
sounds on all string instruments so
this applies to any of them.
One of them is the technique you saw me
do with my left hand where I wiggled it
a little bit, it's called vibrato.
You hear it in human voice as well and you
can do it on other instruments as well.
But on the string instrument
it is the difference.
I'll play a melody without vibrato and
then with vibrato so
you can see the difference.
[MUSIC]
So that's without bravado.
Not that interesting in my opinion.
So with bravado.
[MUSIC]
And you can vary the width and
the speed and the length.
There's a lot of variety with which.
>> Okay, and
then just quickly play a pizzicato for us.
>> Sure.
[MUSIC]
>> Okay, and then finally, tremolo.
>> Yes.
[MUSIC]
>> Adds a little excitement or
a little filler to the music sometimes.
>> All right, so
let's move on now to the woodwind family.
Here's a picture that gives you
a sense of the relative size of the,
you can see left to right,
what do we have?
Bassoon, clarinet, saxophone, which really
isn't part of the symphony orchestra.
But there it is anyway.
It most often plays in a band
of one sort or another.
Then, the English horn, a lower oboe,
and then the oboe itself.
And then finally, the flute.
You'll notice a couple of things here.
The flute is made of metal, but
originally it was made of wood.
Also, you'll see that the flute, like
its relative, the recorder has no reed.
You actually blow in the top of
the instrument, a hole on the top.
The other instruments have reeds.
So let's see some of these reeds
as we look at our next slide.
The clarinet is a single reed instrument,
while the bassoon, English horn and
oboe are double reed instruments.
The nature of the reed affects
the vibration of air within the column or
the tube of the instrument and
sets up the difference in overtones
that we discussed previously
in today's session.
Generally speaking, or
in point of fact, the violin and
the oboe and the flute, they all
play more or less in the same range.
The flute is slightly higher,
its bottom note is middle C, about a
fourth higher than the other instruments.
Okay, so let's go on now to watch
a demonstration of a woodwind instrument.
Specifically, the bassoon.
This is Linda Paul,
who will be one of our principle TAs here.
She is a PhD candidate in
the department of music,
just passed her qualifying
exam with flying colors.
So here she is to demonstrate
the bassoon for us,
lowest member of the woodwind family.
>> All right, so you probably read in
the book that the bassoon is a double
reed instrument and so
just to show you what that looks like.
You've probably seen it but
if you haven't,
two pieces of wood vibrate
together when I blow threw them.
[SOUND] Always check it out
before I play any notes and
as you will probably suspect by the length
of the bassoon,
it can play very low notes.
[MUSIC]
And if I put a little rag in the top
I can get it even a little bit lower.
And that, I didn't bring one.
But actually, amazingly,
it's a very versatile instrument.
It can also play very high notes, as you
can see, there are a lot of keys on it.
There are nine keys for
my left thumb alone.
So I'm switching between these on
the back here and many others, and
because of that, I can go very
high I'll just demonstrate that.
[MUSIC]
So that's just to give
you a sense of the range,
because of the sort of particular
character of the bassoon's sound, it's
often used to play sort of funny little
low note characters in the orchestra.
For example, if you're familiar with Peter
and the Wolf, different instruments play
different characters,
the bassoon is the grandfather.
[MUSIC]
>> You heard some of the strings and
some of the woodwinds.
Now we're gonna turn to the brass
instruments, and here again we have
instruments of various sizes,
various members of the brass family.
On this particular side we
can see from top to bottom.
Trumpet over there in the top left, french
horn in the middle, and trombone below.
And then two tubas to the right,
one large and one small.
The principle involved with
the brass instrument is simple.
Each has in one way or another a tube or
pipe that ultimately connects to a bell.
And that helps to disperse the sound.
To prove the point, I and
my trusty media coordinator
Guy Ontivella constructed
a brass instrument.
Well, sort of.
We took a mouthpiece, this is actually the
mouthpiece from his daughter's trombone,
and a funnel that I use in my
garage to funnel gasoline.
And we connected them through a tube
that we will pretend is made of metal.
Specifically of brass.
One a french horn, this tube of metal or
brass could be as long as 12 feet.
So you're about to hear and I'll have
to stand up for this world premier.
You're about to hear
Strauss' Also Sprach Zarathustra
played on a brand new instrument,
the trombone funnel
[SOUND] Oddly enough,
it was playing the first
overtone, [LAUGH] the second overtone and
the third overtone, and
we could fill in with.
[MUSIC]
Obviously, Yale University is at the
cutting edge of science and technology.
[LAUGH] And equally obvious,
as we look at this slide
once again, the longer the piece of pipe,
the lower the sound.
The player pulls in or out a slide,
makes the tubing longer or
shorter, raises or lowers the pitch.
Or he opens and
closes valves on a trumpet or
a French horn, thereby making
the length of pipe longer or shorter.
And the pitch is thereby adjusted.
To each of the brass instruments
is attached a mouthpiece.
Let's see if I can detach this.
I have no idea what's gonna happen,
yep, there it goes.
So here's the mouthpiece for a trombone.
And they come in various sizes according
to the instrument in question.
Lets watch a demonstration of
a real brass instrument here,
the french horn, from a class session.
This is my friend long time colleague
music library extraordinaire and
professional french horn player Ava Heder,
who will demonstrate here.
Come on over here right in the center.
Jean Kimball is in the basement
somewhere recording all of this.
>> Oh my.
>> Oh yes, very exciting here.
>> [LAUGH]
>> What a time to be alive, huh?
>> Yeah.
>> So, Eva's just going to demonstrate
the physical process of
playing the french horn.
>> The horn, obviously,
is a brass instrument, and
what makes the sound is
a vibrating column of air.
In this case, the basic column of air
is twelve and a half feet long and
there's something called partials or
the harmonic series that happens in
anything with a string instrument or
whatever.
But, on the horn, it's very distinct and
that's what makes the different note.
Let me demonstrate to
you the harmonic series.
[MUSIC]
No, I didn't use, no hands.
That was just the notes that
are naturally on the 12 and
a half foot length of a vibrating air.
That's the harmonic series.
That's on that And what the valves
do is they shorten and lengthen
that vibrating column of air, very much
like a cello string on a finger board.
You know a cellist is always
shortening and lengthening the strings.
I'm doing the same thing.
I'm just doing it with
a series of switches.
This instead of a fingerboard,
which we obviously don't have.
>> Okay.
That's fun.
That's great.
That's the principle.
And when she says she'd overblow it,
what that means is, and
we'll keep emphasizing this point today,
that.
And these partials that when I sounds
is made you have not just one sound but
that tube is divide it
up into sections and
all kinds of little sections
of that one tube are sounding.
Not just the big sound but
the partials, or the overtones.
The intervals of the harmonic series.
Finally the percussion family.
But I'm not gonna say too much about them.
Course we have the bass drum.
Boom.
And the snare drum.
Ratta-tat.
And the ding, the triangle.
These instruments for
the most part don't change pitch.
For the symphony orchestra, however,
the principal percussion instrument
is the timpani or kettle drums,
called kettle drums of course, because
they look like large kettles or pots.
They can sound different pitches.
They do change pitch.
On the screen here you
see four kettle drums.
Usually at the time of Mozart and Haydn,
in the period of classical music,
there would be only two on the stage.
They were tuned to play the tonic and
the dominant notes.
And to get them in tune you could push
the pedals that you see on the slide here.
That's what the pedals are for.
They make it possible to change the pitch.
The skin head or
the plastic head on the drum.
So back in the time of Haydn,
Mozart, and Beethoven you really
only used two of these and they were
tuned to the tonic and dominant and
they could emphasize the authentic
cadences at critical points in the music.
Bum bum bum bum bum bum bum bum.
That's what they would play.
But generally, what the percussions
instruments do is identity and
intensity and articulation to the music.
Yes, the bass drum and snare drum, they
can help keep a strong beat in the music.
And so can the symbol, crash, crash, cash,
crash, crash, cash, crash, crash, cash.
But the cymbal crashing music most
particularly in romantic music
often comes at the top
of a musical line and
the end of a long crescendo,
end of a big increase in volume.
This is what I mean by saying that
the percussion instrument gives definition
to the music and
helps tell us where we are.
>> In romantic music, when you hear a long
crescendo by the full orchestra, and
then [SOUND], cymbal crash,
that crash is signifying to
the listener that we are at the peak.
This is the top, this is the high point.
This is the emotional
high point of the piece.
When the symbol player
crashes the two together,
he might just as well be saying,
this is the climax.