[MUSIC]
I'd like to turn now to a very brief
overview of the development of the western
symphony orchestra.
Here's a seating plan for modern
symphony orchestra and its instruments.
It's just one of several
commonly used arrangements.
As we look at it,
let's think about how our modern
symphony orchestra began to take shape.
The nucleus was provided by
the strings during the 17th century,
when the violin came into prominence.
It and other members of the violin family,
a cousin,
came to form the core of the ensemble,
the string core.
Violins, violas, cellos,
double basses, and occasionally harps.
Soon, some woodwind
instruments were added.
Usually oboes and bassoons.
Often doubling, playing the same
pitches as doubling the string parts.
By the end of the 17th century,
French horns could be added to give
greater body or substance to the sound.
Around 1700, should a composer want to
create a particularly splendid sound,
he might add trumpets and tympani.
Flutes and clarinets didn't join
the orchestra until the 18th century, and
the trombone and tuba not until the 19th.
Other percussive instruments,
not until the 20th century.
Notice that the brass and
the percussion here, are all the way
at the back of the orchestra.
That's where they almost always go.
Because they can be very loud.
That's a quick thumbnail sketch of
how the orchestra developed for
classical music in the west.
It grew from a group of about
15 in the 17th century,
to more than a hundred by
the end of the 19th century.
Today the New York Philharmonic, a typical
well established orchestra has by contract
with the musicians union, exactly 106
members, not including the conductor.
But what does a conductor do?
Obviously, he or
she is something of a musical traffic cop.
Leading the orchestra, setting the tempo,
assuring the proper dynamic level,
waving in a soloist now and then,
balancing the various sections,
making sure that all
the pitches are in tune.
All of this so
that the essential message of the music
is heard in a convincing fashion.
Here's a picture of my friend
Toshi Shimada, whose conducted many first
line orchestras in the United States,
Europe, and the Far East.
The orchestra is a medium,
it's a medium between the creator and
the perceiver of a work of art,
between the composer and the listener.
It's the job of
the conductor to facilitate
the communication between these two,
between creator and receiver.
Notice the arrow pointing
to the conductor's score.
It's kind of a musical road map.
The conductor will glance at this
from time to time to remember
when to throw a cue to a player, or
perhaps to beat an especially clear
beat pattern to set an unambiguous tempo.
Let's zero in on what
a conductor's score looks like.
We could also call it the full score.
Conductor's score, full score, same thing.
Let's see what it looks like.
Here, the woodwinds are on top.
The first four lines at the top there,
the woodwind parts,
running down from flute to a bassoon.
Then we have in the middle the brasses,
followed by the percussion.
And the bottom four parts
are the string parts.
First and second violins and violas and
in this case cellos and basses together.
The players in the orchestra,
they have only their individual parts.
Just one line on their stands, but the
conductor has a composite of all of them.
Now I choose here an image from
Beethoven's Symphony Number 3.
Because that's what we're
about to hear next.
But notice in passing how many
different lines are playing at once.
Does the conductor hear all of this?
Well a good one will.
But even so, he or she is still
responsible for, still gotta concentrate
on the essential part of the musical
message, and that's usually the melody.
Having discussed the tone color of
the various orchestral instruments and
briefly how the orchestra
came to be formed,
let's see how they can work together
to create a glorious effect.
We turn now to a performance part of
the end of Beethoven's Symphony Number 3,
the Eroica symphony.
We'll talk more about the history of
this work when we get to Beethoven.
But for the moment,
let's just concentrate on the music.
Toward the end of this four movement,
and by that,
we simply mean four section symphony.
Movement is simply an independent section.
The end of this four movement symphony.
Toward the end of it,
we hear these sorts of sounds.
We'll be following along here
with the conductor's score.
[MUSIC]
This is a good example of a half-cadence.
We could call it a pause cadence
because that's what it does,
creates a sense of delay, an expectation.
The music stops here, but we really
want it to go on, we want to hear more.
And what we hear then is a beautiful soft,
melodious passage played
by the woodwinds and
you'll never believe what you're hearing.
These are students playing,
undergraduates.
This is the Undergraduate Yale
Symphony Orchestra, let's listen.
[MUSIC]
Then, across the page.
Then I ask the players to take this apart,
this same passage, to show the tone
colors of the various instruments, and
how the instruments blend their sounds.
We'll start with the oboe
as it plays the melody.
[MUSIC]
Next, the bassoon,
as it plays the bass line.
[MUSIC]
Then oboe and bassoon as they
play base and melody together.
[MUSIC]
Notice here, that they're often
going in opposite directions.
This is called counterpoint.
Points moving against each other or
pitches moving against each other.
This is the kind of thing they teach you
to do in basic music composition courses.
Make good counter points.
[MUSIC]
There are also two clarinets
playing in this passage.
They help fill out the harmony
in the middle of the texture.
[MUSIC]
Notice that they generally move together.
They're not creating the essential
counterpoint of the melody and bass.
Internal filler would be
closer to the mark here.
[MUSIC]
All right.
Now let's put this all
back together again.
Another bassoon is added, and
toward the end a French horn sneaks
in to give even more weight to the sound,
let's see if we can pick it up with
the woodwinds all together.
[MUSIC]
Here comes the french horn.
Now, at this point Beethoven extends
the music to the string section
with solos being inserted for
clarinet and then one for the oboe.
So, let's back up here, and
hear this entire section again.
Strings lead up to a pause, the half
cadence that we heard then the beautiful
soft passage for wood winds then the
strings take the lead take the music back
again, and out of it grows the solo
first for clarinet and then for oboe.
And again let's follow the full score
here just as the conductor would see it.
Almost no one can read
all this music at once,
but I thought you might enjoy a peek at
what the conductor actually sees.
[MUSIC]
Cadence.
Clarinet solo.
[MUSIC]
Oboe Solo
A beautiful passage by Beethoven, in which
we get to hear many of the tone colors of
the instruments of the orchestra.
All beautifully played by young people,
18, 19, 20, 21 years old.
Just students.
A soccer or
a football team, in an American football
team each has eleven players on it.
A baseball team, nine, and
a basketball team only five.
But a symphony orchestra has upward
of a hundred players participating,
all at once.
Playing as many as 25
different instruments.
It's intricate.
It's complex.
But as we have just heard it can also
be very powerful and very beautiful.