[MUSIC]
Music that you hear in the background is,
again,
a bit of Modest Musorgsky's Pictures
at an Exhibition as
orchestrated by Maurice Revell.
We've talked about rhythm,
melody, harmony,
tone color, in our course thus far.
Today we are going to talk about texture,
form, and style.
Let's begin with texture,
what's texture in music?
Well it's the disposition of
the materials, or otherwise said,
the placement of the sounds.
Following the theme of pictures at
an exhibition let's look at two.
To the left we have Pete Mondrian,
a more less equal distribution of
vertical and horizontal lines.
We'll be saying the same thing about
musical lines in musical textures
in a moment.
And while there are blotches
of colors around the side,
the middle has a wide open texture.
We'll be saying the same thing
about the music of Aaron Copeland,
composer of Appalachian Spring,
Aaron Copeland, later in our course.
Georgia O'Keeffe's Clouds is to the right.
Heavy and ponderous at the bottom,
light and airy and fast moving at the top.
Music too fast moving melody on top and
a slower base and harmony beneath.
That also is a common texture.
Musical sounds, too,
can be arranged in different ways.
In music we say that we have three kinds
of textures, three basic textures.
Monophonic, homophonic, and polyphonic.
In truth, the distinction between
the textures, is not always clearcut.
Sometimes the music is midway
between homophonic and
polyphonic texture, up in the gray area.
But understanding these basic types,
monophonic, homophonic, and polyphonic,
allows us to understand how texture
works in the most basic sort of ways.
Let's start with monophonic texture.
Monophonic conveys the idea of one, from
the Greek word monos, meaning just one.
With monophonic texture,
we get only one sound.
As we hear here with the tune,
Are You Sleeping, or Frere Jacques.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
If men and women sing the same tune
together in octaves, we still have,
[MUSIC].
We still have monophonic texture,
monophonic music,
because the same letter names
would be used for the pitches.
And the pitch intervals that
are involved would be exactly the same,
moving along higher or lower in lock step.
It's still monophonic texture.
Supposing now, I supported
the melody with chords beneath,
creating an accompanying harmony.
That gives us homophonic texture,
same sounding texture.
Homophonic texture is usually
generated by homorhythms,
rhythms with pitches of the same duration.
That gives the appearance of everything
changing at the same time in lockstep.
On the screen the same melody is
now supported by chords changing
at the same time.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
Lets see now how this sounds in music for
an orchestra.
Lets listen to the beginning of
Musorgsky's Pictures at an Exhibition.
We'll hear a solo instrument play
a melody, and then that instrument plays
again, but now joined by other members
of that same instrumental family.
As you listen, ask yourself, what's
the solo instrument that's playing here?
And what is the family of instruments
that responds to each solo call?
[MUSIC]
And you're right.
The melody is first played in monophonic
texture by a trumpet and then repeated
with support of the brass section,
in chords, homophonic texture again.
At the end,
the members of the string family entered,
but still playing in homophonic texture.
Finally, polyphonic texture.
Obviously here we have the idea
of many sounding texture.
Here the lines are much more independent
mainly because the rhythms are also
independent.
So let's go back to Frere Jacques.
And you can see the individual lines here.
I can try to play it.
[MUSIC]
And it gets a little bit tricky,
but you get the idea.
The fact that it is
a little more complicated
suggests that polyphonic texture
is the most complex texture.
For that reason, it was preferred by
composer J.S. Bach, whose music is
in many ways the most complex of
all the great classic composers.
Here's a slide image of old Bach,
painted toward the end of his life.
Actually, it's the only authentic
representation of Bach that we have.
And here's the way Bach
generates polyphonic texture
in a complex form called the fugue.
The fugue is an example of imitative
polyphonic texture because as
each line enters, it duplicates, at least
at the beginning, the preceding line.
Then each line breaks away and
goes in it's own direction.
If the voice is entered and
imitated exactly from beginning to end,
we would have a round,
like Frere Jacques, or Three Blind Mice.
In classical music,
we use the highfalutin word cannon
to mean round, cannon or
round, interchangeable.
But what you're about to hear is a fugue,
after the opening with the exact
imitation each voice goes its own way.
We'll come back to fugues
later on in our course.
But let's begin with one here by Bach.
[MUSIC]
These musical video creations are
wonderful, and I am indebted to my friend
Steve Malinowski,
creator of Music Animation Machine for
allowing me to put this up for free and
have everyone hear, see, and enjoy.
And we'll be using more of
Steve's creations as we proceed.
How do we recognize the difference between
these three essential musical textures?
Well, monophonic texture is
perhaps the easiest to hear.
It's just the melody.
Homophonic texture sounds
mainly like a melody but
here you have additional sounds.
The body of the music just sounds fuller,
sounds richer.
If you hear a lot going on in the music,
however,
indeed if your mind is really challenged,
maybe even confounded
by all that's going on,
then likely you have polyphonic texture.
It's the most complex.
As a test of our ability to hear musical
textures, let's turn to a famous piece.
Handel's Hallelujah chorus from
his curatorial Messiah, 1742.
Here we see Handel holding
the score of Messiah.
In the Hallelujah chorus the composer
quickly juxtaposes all three textures.
In fact, this piece is
something of a final exam for
identifying musical textures.
You heard it many times but
likely not thought about
the musical textures involved.
I'll call them out as we proceed.
[MUSIC]
So here we start with homophonic texture.
>> [MUSIC]
Monophonic texture.
>> Homophonic texture.
Back to monophonic in octaves.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Homophonic.
>> Polyphonic starting out, an imitation.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Homophonic.
>> Still homophonic.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Polyphonic.
>> Basses move to tenor.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Moving up higher and higher.
>> Finally, soprano.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Monophonic answered by homophonic.
>> Monophonic.
Homophoic.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Moving up step by step.
>> Homophonic
>> [MUSIC]
>> Polyphonic.
>> Monophonic, answered by homophonic.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Polyphonic.
>> Homophonic.
>> [MUSIC]
>> And homophonic.
>> Did you notice there at the end,
there was a forced texture,the
texture of silence,
actually that was a stroke of genius.
In the midst of all that glorious
sound Handel inserts no sound at all.
A thundering silence.