On the screen you see a picture
of a church in Munich, Germany,
right across the street from
the Munich Opera House.
Certainly it has a form to it, it is
very symmetrical, a symmetrical form.
You could fold the right half
back over the left half and
they would exactly overlap.
The point is that we have form,
of course, in architecture.
Here the facade of the church creates
something akin to A, B, A form.
Tower, pediment, tower.
Here now are three scenes of Madonna,
child and the young St. John the Baptist.
Clearly, each one is constructed
within the impetus of a triangle.
Here of course, there is form in painting.
But what about music?
You can't touch it.
You can't see it.
It's invisible.
So how can you have form in music?
Well you can create form in music
by arranging the musical events in
a particular order as
the piece unfolds in time.
In other words, you could repeat
blocks of sound, a melody,
a striking texture, an exciting chord
progression, these are all events.
And a composer can arrange them in
one of several different patterns and
thereby create an aural form.
Instead of seeing the form all at once,
you experience it,
you hear it as events pass by in time.
Form in music is fashioned by statement,
by repetition,
by contrast and by variation.
Statement, repetition,
contrast and variation.
Looking back over the history of music,
we see that using statement,
repetition, contrast and variation,
five common patterns of musical form,
have come to dominate
music over the centuries.
They are, as you can see here
on the screen, strophic, binary,
ternary, rondo, and theme and variations.
There are other forms in music.
Fugue and sonata allegro among them.
And we'll talk about these
later on in our course.
But for the moment, let's just stick
with these five basic very common forms.
Let's start with strophic form.
If we go all the way back to the very
earliest written secular music in
Western culture, we come to see the songs
of the troubadours and of the 12th and
13th centuries.
Already, at least 800 years ago, musicians
were singing songs in strophic form.
On the screen here we see
a troubadour manuscript.
There, at the top left, the title, though
it's a little faint, but I can read it.
Here Commence The Songs of Our Lord.
[FOREIGN].
We have five strophes of text.
The first of which, shown by the red
arrow, is set beneath the music.
The remaining four are just written
out as text that you can see here
indicated by the blue arrows, but
they get set to the same music.
Strophic form still works that way today.
You have a poem that consists of
the succession of strophes, or stanzas.
These words, strophes and
stanza are interchangeable.
And you set the first strophe to a song,
a melody.
Then you go on to set the next
strophe of your poem.
And you put that to the same melody and so
on throughout the remaining strophes or
stanzas.
So with strophic form, you set a text with
many strophes to one and the same music.
Actually we do the same with
hymns that are sung in church or
universities or
commencements, even weddings.
There are many stanza's of a hymn but
they are sung to the same music.
So strophic form can be represented as A,
A, A, A, A and so on.
Because all of the music is the same.
On the screen you see equivalent
of strophic form in architecture.
The outdoor rotunda of the Esterhazy
Estate where composer Josef Haydn
worked in the 18th century.
Each of the units, the columns,
repeats without a variation.
Let's explore a very simple
example of strophic form in music.
The famous Lullaby created by Johannes
Brahms in the middle of the 19th century.
It starts with a lilting
piano accompaniment,
a harmony, before the melody
enters with a female voice.
As if a mother were singing
her child to sleep.
[MUSIC]
Here's the introduction.
>> [MUSIC]
>> End this strophe,
piano introduction again, second strophe.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Watched over by angels indeed.
Very beautiful.
Surprisingly, although the form goes all
the way back to at least the middle ages,
most pop songs today are still
written in strophic form.
But often in a slightly more
complex version of strophic form.
The first part is what we've
come to call the verse, and
the second, the concluding part,
the chorus.
Originally, in the Middle Ages, it appears
that a chorus did join in for what came
to be called, [LAUGH] not unsurprisingly,
the chorus part of the song.
The chorus that ends each strophe is
always the same, it's a textural refrain.
But, the text of each verse is new.
Let's see how this works.
I've chosen a song that I've always liked,
The City of New Orleans,
made popular by modern day troubadour,
Arlo Guthrie.
Something, as they say,
of a modern day troubadour.
But the song was originally written
by a one Steven Goodwin, and
it's been covered by more
than 50 singers over time.
Arlo Guthrie, just producing the best
known version of these covers.
It's a great poem, actually, about
hard time in the heartland of America.
By the way, the beginning of the chorus,
good morning america, how are you was
taken and turned into the title of the ABC
morning show, Good Morning, America.
The song starts with
an instrumental lead in.
Once the train gets rolling you can
hear it rolling in the accompaniment.
[SOUND] in the background.
I've highlighted in red two
key moments of the chorus.
A great use of syncopation, that's the
first one and then an unexpected cortal
shift in the harmony which gives us a sort
of harmonic shiver on the word gone.
Let me see if I can reconstruct
some of this on the piano.
[MUSIC]
There's that chord.
So be on the lookout for
the syncopation and
[MUSIC]
that surprise chord there in the chorus.
Let's hear it.
[MUSIC]
>> Shift to the minor.
>> Syncopation.
[MUSIC]
That's just the first and chorus and
there are two others that follow.
It's a great song.
Indeed,
I submit that that song's belongs in
the pantheon of great American songs.
The heartland of America during
the decline of the railroads, but
oddly enough that train is
still running on Amtrak today,
900 miles from Chicago through Memphis,
to New Orleans.
So we've have two lullabies,
one written in strophic form,
by the 19th century German
composer Johann Brahms and
the other is by with verse and
chorus structure.
Which is better, which do you enjoy more?
I'd like to know, send me an email.
But every pop singer has sung songs
in this sort of strophic form,
verse plus chorus, Taylor Swift,
Lady Gaga, Brad Paisley, Adele, everyone.
To be sure, strophic form is
the world's most popular musical form.
All right.
On now to theme and variations.
Instead of having the music come back,
exactly the same way each time.
It changes with each appearance.
One and the same idea
continually modified or varied.
And as you can see here in the bottom, we
have that arranged in terms of shapes and
then we're going to turn to the Sydney
Opera House where I have labeled
the various sails of the roof
of the opera house A,
A prime, A double prime and so on.
Theme and variation also goes back
deep into a recorded history.
Classical composers have
frequently made used of it
as had instrumentalist playing popular
music, in jazz musicians in particular.
Here are two quick examples, the first
is a popular song from the Renaissance.
Greensleeves.
There was a melody built
on a recurring harmony and
as each time the harmony
appeared the performer
would alter the melody improvising
a new version each time.
So the harmony essentially goes.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
Well if I had any talent,
I could really do a good job with that.
But that's what jazz musicians do,
jazz trumpeters like Chris Botti and
Wynton Marsalis.
They take a well known tune,
called a standard, Greensleeves.
[MUSIC]
Is a standard of the 16th century.
They'd take a standard such as Somewhere
Over the Rainbow or When I Fall in Love,
and they'd repeat again and
again jazzing it up,
varying the melody at each appearance.
Now here's a second, very straightforward
version of theme and variation form.
It was created by Mozart.
In the setting of a song that
we all know today as Twinkle,
Twinkle Little Star or
maybe Bah, Bah Black Sheep.
Actually, it was originally
a french folk song
that Mozart heard on a trip to France.
To see what Mozart did
with this now famous tune,
lets turn to a live class demonstration.
>> And here is the melody.
[MUSIC]
And here's the first variation.
Now my question to you is this [COUGH].
With theme and variation, the composer
can keep the theme more or less exactly
as it is, and change the context
around it, or he can change the theme.
So which does Mozart do
in the first variation?
[MUSIC]
Thoughts about that?
Is he changing the theme or is he keeping
the theme and changing stuff around it.
What do you think?
Well, what he's doing
is changing the theme.
The theme would go.
[MUSIC]
But right at the beginning instead of.
I get.
[MUSIC]
So there's only really one note
that relates to the theme there.
And then.
[MUSIC]
Well, now I get.
So he sort of changing the theme by making
the notes go quicker in ornamenting
around those notes.
So that's variation one
what about variation two?
Does he change the theme or does he just
change all the stuff around the theme?
[MUSIC]
And so on.
So what's he doing there?
Caroline?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Changing what?
I'm sorry, I couldn't hear you.
>> Changing the context.
Changing the context.
The theme in the right hand
stays exactly the same.
[MUSIC]
Okay, here is the next one.
What's that?
Well, it goes with this.
[MUSIC]
So has he changed the theme?
Yeah, he's changed the theme
rather considerably there.
Indeed.
[MUSIC]
We wouldn't know that had anything to
do with Twinkle, Twinkle Little Star,
unless we had had given to us
previously as we have, the melody.
[MUSIC]
So we are hearing
in our inner ear.
[MUSIC]
So we know that's the basis of this.
And if he wants to deviate from that,
we can still say oh, yeah,
that's related to that.
That's getting rather far away from
the original because we sort of locked in
the original in our on
my ear at that point.
And then oddly the final,
the final variation, what does
he do to the meter in this last variation?
[MUSIC]
What happens there?
We were going.
[MUSIC]
So what's he done to the meter?
Well, let me strip away the bass.
[MUSIC]
Is changed into triple,
by throwing in an extra
bar of filler in between each
of his basic duple beats.
Then we come to, maybe,
let me just cut to the chase here.
At the end of this,
he's coming in.
[MUSIC]
What's this?
All the way to the end now.
What do we call
this formally?
[MUSIC]
We talked about that with
regard to Sonata-Allegro form.
It's one of the parts that shows
up also in Sonata-Allegro form
has nothing to do really
with the theme here.
It is a good example of a coda.
Right, just something thrown on at
the end to say this is the end.
[MUSIC]
And what's he doing here?
What is this?
How complex is this?
[MUSIC]
It's just a major triad.
He's just ornamenting a major triad.
So it's more cadential stuff.
Sort of very simple material at the end.
>> So there a there at the end
of that class session,
that guy was talking about
the idea of a coda in music.
Coda is the simple Italian word for
tail, end.
Okay, let's go on now to binary form.
Here on the screen you see two
sculptures of the late British sculptor,
Barbra Hepworth.
The one to the left is actually in the art
gallery of the Northwestern University
campus.
Although they are different,
each represents an example of binary form.
In each sculpture we have two parts,
but they're not the same.
They are equal entities that
compliment and complete one another.
As you can imagine, you get that same
idea, that same process in music as well.
In music, we call it just a b,
or binary form.
Let's listen to a famous
melody again by JS Bach.
Now in binary form.
It's his Air on a G string, so
titled because someone in the nineteenth
century arranged the melody to be
played entirely on the G string,
the lowest string of the violin.
Anyway, the piece is in
a clear binary form.
This animated music video that we
are about to see was, again, done and
made available to us by Steve Millonausky
and musical animation machine.
I'll comment as we go along.
[MUSIC]
We see that the bass has a steady
pulse proceeding in eighth notes.
That's neither here nor there, but
you can hear the steady beat underneath.
[MUSIC]
And the upper parts engage a light
sort of form of polyphonic texture.
Here's the end of the a section.
The bass now moves
a little bit more quickly.
Now he's going to repeat
the same material all over again.
[MUSIC]
First and second violins,
top and next to the top part,
engage in a musical dialogue.
[MUSIC]
End of the a section,
now onto the b section.
[MUSIC]
Part two.
Now the next to bottom part
is a little more aggressively
into the imitation and into the polyphony.
All the while, the bass just
keeps plodding along with it's
steady eighth note line.
[MUSIC]
Bringing into a climax.
And here's the end of
[MUSIC]
The B section, but
Bach wants to repeat that B section,
just as he had repeated the A section.
[MUSIC]
As we noted there, in this performance,
and as Bach wanted, both the A section and
the B section were repeated,
producing an A-A-B-B form, but
it's still thought of simply as binary or
A-B form.
But repeating the sections makes this
gorgeous piece by Bach last longer, and
who wouldn't like that?
Okay, on to Turner reform.
Firmly believing that a picture
is worth a thousand words,
here's an example of Turner
reform in architecture.
It's Mozart's church,
the Cathedral of Salzburg.
With Turner reform in music, it's helpful
to think of home, away, home, or A-B-A.
Now, for more complete explanation of
Turner reform, again with a change of key
in the middle B section, let's turn
to a class video where I talk about
Turner reform in a piece by Beethoven, the
beginning section of his famous Fur Elise.
So, we have this piece in
Turner reform by Beethoven, and
Turner reform conveys to us simply
the idea of presentation, diversion,
representation or statement digression,
restatement, anything like this, we like
to diagram these in terms of alphabetical
letters you can think just A-B-A.
[MUSIC]
All right, I'm going to pause here.
We started out here.
[MUSIC]
We are in this key.
Major or minor, what do you think?
Minor.
All right, so
we were coming to the end
of this A section.
Here the A section is very short.
[MUSIC]
But then,
we, major or minor?
Major, okay.
So, what happened there?
What do we call this?
It's a very quick modulation,
a very quick modulation.
We've changed keys.
And I'm going to digress here just for
a moment to talk about this,
which is this concept of
relative major and minor.
You may have noticed in music, and it's
discussed briefly in the textbook that
there are pairs of keys, pairs of
keys that have something in common.
The members of the pairs
have the same key signature.
We could take any key signature,
three flats, or two sharps, whatever, but
there's gonna be one major key with three
flats and one minor key with three flats.
And I think we have, up on the board here,
an example of just that, so you can see
written in here the three flats, and
this is a minor scale with three flats.
Now, we could also have
three flats over here, but
we encounter three flats when
we have the major scale.
This happens to work out,
so that it's pitched on C.
If we come up three half steps in
the keyboard, we come up to E flat.
So, the relative major, the major key in
this pair, is always three half steps.
One, two, three, three half
steps up above its paired minor.
Here's another one down at the bottom,
happens to have one sharp in it.
We have the key of G major
here with one sharp, but
if we come down three half steps,
we get it's relative minor down here.
And the reason I mention this is not
because we actually hear this very much.
I'm not sure that I hear modulations
to relative major, because I don't have
absolute pitch, and I'm not tracking
keys when I listen to pieces.
My guess is that you're not either.
So, for the average listener, we may not
hear the actual pitch relationship, but
we may hear that we've had a modulation,
and
you can kind of make an educated guess
that about 50% of the time if it's
going minor to major, it's coming
in this relative arrangement, or
major down to minor,
it's going in this relative arrangement.
So, this happens a lot.
So here we are in the mid section
of our Turner reform, A-B-A.
Here is the B part.
[MUSIC]
And then back to the minor A.
Now, that's just the opening
section of this piece,
it goes on to do other things, but it is
a very succinct example of Turner reform.
Finally, rondo form.
Rondo form involves a simple principle,
a refrain,
theme A,
alternates with contrasting music.
Usually in a rondo,
there are at least two contrasting
sections that we'll label B and C.
Classical composers and
even a few pop composers have written
pieces in a variety of rondo forms.
On the screen,
you can see three of them, A-B-A-C-A,
A-B-A-C-A-B-A, or
A-B-A-C-A-D-A, for example.
Rondo form also appears in architecture,
particularly the A-B-A-C-A-B-A structure,
which is a palindrome, something that goes
backward and forwards at the same time,
like race car or Madam, I am Adam.
Here is my favorite chateau,
actually it's not my favorite chateau, but
it's one of my favorite chateaus, and
it plays out in architecture, rondo form.
I took this picture many years
ago while leaning out of a bus.
It's the Renaissance Chateau,
built by Francis I,
King Francis I, in Chambord in France.
I put the letters on parts of
the chateau to show you the form.
Now, let's see how this plays
out in an example of pop music.
Sting and The Police,
Every Breath You Take.
You see a diagram up here on the screen,
and
I'm gonna talk through this
a little bit as we hear it.
So let's start it out, and
we'll begin here in the A section.
[MUSIC]
Here we are in our tonic.
One chord,
[MUSIC]
minor cord goes into the sixth degree of
the scale, and one goes on the fourth
degree of the scale, and comes back in,
but not back to the expected tonic.
There is deceived, a deceptive cadence,
but now it's gonna cycle again.
There's our six chord,
four chord built on the fifth degree.
Okay, back to the tonic.
Now here comes our B section.
[MUSIC]
>> Moving to a different
accompanying level,
coming around back to five chord here,
setting up for
return back to original tonic.
Six
[MUSIC]
four
five.
Okay, so that's how this plays out.
Now, let's go back to our
slide of the chateau.
Now we've worked our way
past the second day.
We're gonna go on to here
a radically different section,
C section,
where there's a bold harmonic shift.
So, let's listen to that, and
then we'll go on from there.
[MUSIC]
Now, it jumps back to the original tonic,
and
the A idea has returned, but
now there are no lyrics,
just the harmonic pattern,
and it fades out and
eventually ends,
after revisiting the B section and
a final return to the initial A.
Nice chateau, nice song.
Well, I find our segment on musical
form is already overly long, so
we'll postpone Mr. Mozart and his famous
Rondo alla Turca until our session
on musical form in the classical
era of Mozart and Haydn.
We'll listen to it then.