We'll come back to this monk again later.
But let's talk about where all of this
medieval chant for the church was created.
It was not created at urban churches,
cathedrals, but for rural monasteries.
What you see on the screen here from
the Basque region of Southern France.
Many in the sixth and
seventh centuries were on isolated
coasts particularly in Ireland.
We see the remains of one of them here,
and here are two more slides.
We have an image of Jumieges in France,
a large monastery that
flourished in the tenth century.
And then finally the Abbey, the
Benedictine Abbey Fontenay, where you can
still go and hear the service as sung
there in the church to your right today.
What did the monks and
nuns do at these monasteries and convents?
They worked and they prayed.
Laboro, oro.
I work, I pray.
They worked to feed their bodies and
they prayed to save their souls.
And they did this on a regular schedule as
set forth by the rule of Saint Benedict.
In a little book written again by
Saint Benedict in the sixth century.
Here's my copy of it,
at least more or less my copy,
the cover is sort of
fallen over through use.
It tells us that the monks and nuns
came together to pray eight times a day.
And, a ninth time to celebrate the mass,
the spiritual high point of the day.
Usually around nine o'clock in the morning
when they took communion with the Lord.
Let me take you to my monastery.
Here you see it on the screen.
I once stayed there many years ago.
Saint Pierre de Solesmes.
South, southwest of Paris.
About 100 miles away from Paris.
Here's the monastery that
you see very imposing.
I lived here actually in the first floor,
the closest windows.
I was allowed, no alarm clock,
no radio and certainly no cell phone.
But I had to attend all of
the services in the church.
How in the world did I wake up?
Well, the ringing of the bells.
Actually the french word for bell,
cloche, equals our or gives us our clock.
And the Latin horo, english for hour.
So the bells called me to make
my way over to the church.
Every guest who lives in the monastery
has to attend a services of the monks
in their church.
When I worked I went into the library
to study Gregorian chant and
I took my meals here in the refectory, the
dining hall no talking no conversation.
The Abby sits at one end and
someone reads the daily newspaper of
the Roman Catholic Church
L'Osservatore Romano,
The Roman Observer
published by The Vatican.
So as you sense, it was a very different
world, an entirely spiritual world.
Now there were also convents, of course,
where nuns lived and slept and worshiped.
Here we see the very large convent at
Fontevraud in Loire Valley in France.
In this church Richard the Lionheart and
Queen Eleanor of Aquitaine are buried.
This is no longer actually
a functioning church.
Here you see the cloister.
It's a cultural center for
the region of Tours, France.
But it was huge in its day.
That nonetheless gives you a sense
of the size of this content here.
All of these nuns sleeping
in this same room.
Perhaps the most famous nun
of the middle ages, and
the most famous female creator of
Gregorian chant, was Hildegard of Bingen,
who lived in Germany on the banks of
the Rhine River during the 12th century.
To meet Hildegard,
let's go back to the classroom and
reconnect with that strange
looking Benedictine Book.
One spiritual leader
within the community of
Benedictine convents was
Hildegard of Bingen.
Hildegard lived in the 12th century.
She came from the area of Bingen on the
west bank of the Rhine river in Germany.
She grew up in a Benedictine convent.
Here is the ruins of that
Benedictine convent and
then she went on ultimately to found her
own convent and these are the ruins,
or a 17th century drawing of that
convent which is now also in ruins.
Hildegard was a polymath.
She could do many things.
She wrote on church administration,
on botany,
on pharmacology, on medicine and on music.
Indeed, because of this diversity, we can,
I think, fairly say that the first
renaissance man,
in actuality was a medieval woman.
Hildegard of Bingen.
Popes and Bishops sought her advice,
in part because she was a visionary.
She had visions associated
with the Christian story.
Hildegard also wrote Gregorian chant.
So, let's look at some slides of
Hildegard, she was famous in her day.
Here we have a manuscript put together in
northern Italy about 20 years after her
death with the representation of
Hildegard up there on the top left.
Next slide takes us to
a blow up of this and
we see the representation of
Hildegard having a celestial vision.
That's why the wavy lines
going up from her head.
She's receiving the Holy Spirit.
She is copying down what she
perceives, not on a notebook computer,
but on a wax tablet with a large
stylus in her right hand.
Her assistant, the one male allowed
in this community for the sacraments,
her assistant, Volmar,
peeks in astonished at what he is seeing.