[MUSIC]
All right.
Let's have a listen now
to a chant of Hildegard.
Lillegard wrote about eighty of them.
Here is a page from a manuscript in
Belgium that preserves just one them.
A sample page, and
here is a blow up of that same page so
that can see it a little more clearly.
Just enlarged.
[MUSIC]
Now, a modern edition of
the chant by Hildegard,
made off of that manuscript, by myself.
Hildegard's music is very tonal.
It ends each phrase on
either the dominant pitch or
the tonic pitch,
as you can see in the red notes.
And I'll highlight them, here.
Here's one dominant note, here's another
dominant note, here's a tonic note,
a dominant note, dominant note,
and a final tonic note.
Most important,
Hildegard's text is wildly vivid.
She wrote not only the music,
but the text as well.
And this is just typical of hers.
Let me translate it for you.
A redness of blood that
flowed down from the heaven.
You are the flower that the wintry
breath of the serpent never wounded.
Let's talk about the setting of this text.
Some of it is syllabic.
Each syllable of text has only one or
two pitches.
Sometimes it is melismatic.
One syllable is assigned many pitches.
Not for example, fluisti here.
Many many pitches for that one word.
And that's an interesting case because
it's, the word means and you flowed, and
indeed the music seems to flow
rapidly down from high to low.
That's actually very unusual with chant
and with almost with all medieval music.
Text and music operate independently.
Music is abstract with regard to the text.
It carries, but it does not reinforce it.
The recording that you will hear is
one that I created some years back
with three professional women singers.
I call them the Hildegard singers.
I'll follow along as they sing.
[MUSIC]
Very
beautiful.
To sum up,
Gregorian chant is monophonic, one line,
music of the Roman Catholic church.
Sung unaccompanied, in Latin,
in the Middle Ages, and
down to the present day
in some monasteries and
some specially designated churches
that honor the old Latin Mass.
It has no accompaniment,
no meter, and no rhythm.
It generally is music for contemplation.
It is spiritually entombed,
it is transcendental music,
music that takes your mind elsewhere,
as Hildegard says,
carries you away, as it did her,
like a feather on the breath of God.