[MUSIC]
The music you just heard is another
recording I created some years back.
It involves two singers,
melody plus accompaniment.
So it's an example of polyphony?
You'll remember from our session six,
that there are three kinds of textures,
three primary textures in music.
And they are, well yes, monophonic,
homophonic, and polyphonic.
Chant was monophonic in texture.
But to make the church services more
splendid on high feast days of the year,
enterprising churchmen, musicians,
began to add additional voices to
the chant to make a more splendid sound.
Thereby creating polyphony.
At first this polyphony
was just improvised.
Then they began to write it down.
Let's see what this early
polyphony looked like.
Here we see a manuscript form
the ninth century, top and bottom.
Well, on top we have a three voice chant.
And as you can see here, the voices are
operating at the interval of a fifth and
the interval of an octave
moving along all in lockstep.
Below, we have two voices,
two voices moving in counterpoint.
Usually when one goes up,
the other goes down.
And again, mostly at the same time.
In both cases, the funny signs over here,
actually to the left,
the funny signs indicate pitches and
pitch relationships.
Now, a slide from Southern France
in the 12th Century.
The chant is actually on
the bottom line here see,
[FOREIGN],
on the bottom line.
Working with the singers here,
we know what the pitches are.
We know what they're supposed to be.
But what we didn't know was how long
each of these pitches should be held.
We were just winging it
with regard to rhythm.
What we tried to do was make
good vertical consonances.
So let's listen to a bit of
this recording that resulted.
We don't have time for all of it, so we're
going to hear just a bit of the beginning,
and then we'll skip toward the end.
Okay?
[MUSIC]
Creating a recording like this is
possible, if you have only two parts,
two voices.
But if you want three or four or
five parts, then the absence of
rhythmic specificity becomes a problem.
Let's see how they solved it.
Well, they did so by adding stems
on to the notes and note heads.
And eventually by creating note
heads of different shapes.
Here we see in our next slide,
down at the bottom, some music that looks
disturbingly organized,
because it has rhythmic component to it.
And these patterns began to take more and
more of a definitive shape.
As you can see by this slide,
one that I've created here,
you can see that there are stems beginning
to develop into notational symbols,
stems and note heads of different shapes.
And then we see here,
in this mid 13th century motet,
a great deal of organization.
This development,
the capacity to specify and
control rhythm in a precise way,
was hugely important.
What are the two axes of music?
Well, pitch and duration.
Pitch notation had existed for
centuries, since the 9th century.
But rhythmic notation only came into being
in the late 12th century, 300 years later.
And it was a game changer.
Up to that point, music unfolded through
memory and through improvisation.
Musicians could remember a chant,
and someone could come along and
improvise another voice against it.
But now, if you wanted big pieces of
polyphony, let's say with three, four,
or five voices, it got complicated and
you had to be able to
determine things in advance.
And you had to do this through
prescriptive notation.
Thus, in the West,
we moved from performance and
improvisation, to a priori composition.
The creator, the artist,
began to loom large, and the importance
of the performer diminished.
The creator was now the great architect.
The performer, just the carpenter.
What the architect created,
what the composer wrote down,
was a finite composition.
So in this period in Western European
history, in the High and
Late Middle Ages, we have the advent of
the composer of polyphony as we know it,
and we had the work of art as we know it.
And because that work of art can be
written down in almost all of its
specifics, it can not only be
performed at a later time, but
it can be also be analyzed and studied.
Musical analysis is now possible.
This specifying rhythm as well as pitch
was part of the change to quantification
in the West, a shift to specific
measurement of a lot of things.
Organ pipes on a large scale,
mechanical clocks,
the shift from Roman to Arabic numerals,
this all happens in the West here
in the High and Late Middle Ages.
Actually, musical notation,
with its vertical axis for pitch and
its horizontal axis for duration,
was the West's first written graph.
Where did this happen?
In France, specifically in Paris and
other cathedral cities such as Reims.