[MUSIC]
In this segment we will see of the
creation of of the means to control not
only pitch but
also rhythm allowed composers to
create long and complex pieces.
And to do this, we'll take a virtual
trip to France, first to Paris and
then a hundred miles out to the east in
the Champagne region to the city of Reims.
Here you see, of course, the facade
of the famous Notre Dame of Paris.
Let's take a look now, inside.
Here we see two images.
On the left the Choir of Notre Dame
as it currently exists and
on the right as it existed in
the Middle Ages with the stalls for
the clergy on either side in
this large root screen which was
taken down during the revolution,
There present.
The singers would actually come
out in the middle of the choir.
Now here's a manuscript
of the type of music,
actually is the music they were singing.
A four part composition.
Let me see if I can grab
the tenor part here.
Here is that chant here,
there's the first note.
That's the second note.
You can see the tenor holding out there.
We'll talk a little bit
more about that later.
Okay, now let's go onto the city of Reims.
Here we see it as it looked
in the 18th century.
And going back to this 17th century image,
we'll see how Reims towered over the town.
Here is the cathedral here.
We're gonna focus on this street back
up here because one of the clergy men,
name, Gilliam Dimesho, lived here.
And we're now going to go to the interior
of Reims as it currently looks today.
The very beautiful and
very unusual west facade of Reims.
And now the interior of Reims as it
looked during the Middle Ages in
a drawing by the architectural
historian Patrick Denois.
And you can see here, the stalls for
the clergy on either side.
Actually this is a representation of
the coronation of the king of France,
which occurred here at
the Cathedral of Reims.
And note here in the center
the large lectern.
That’s where the musicians would go when
chant and polyphony was to be performed.
And here is our composer that
we will be discussing today,
churchman Guillaume de Machaut In
a 14th century likeness.
Actually, the earliest likeness
that we have of a western composer.
And we're gonna focus now on a Mass
by Machaut, Our Lady Mass of Machaut.
But let's see what's first
involved in a musical Mass.
The mass, in terms of its musical parts,
is divided into two types.
The proper of the mass,
which you see listed on the left, and
the ordinary of the mass which
you see listed on the right.
The proper is sung every day.
It's proper to that day.
On the Feast of St, John the Baptist for
example, the introit,
the opening chant, might begin,
Oh wonderful John who baptized Christ,
or whatever it might happen to be.
But, if we focus on the left side, we have
just those chants that are sung everyday,
and we can extract those and
put them here in a list that runs Kyrie,
Gloria, Credo, Sanctus and Agnus Dei.
So those are the chants of
the Ordinary of the Mass.
Now let's look at the tenor.
How did Machaut go about
constructing this?
Well, he took a tenor voice, and
he rhythmicized it as you can see here.
Originally, this went.
[MUSIC]
And so on.
But he rhythmicized it, as I said, into
[MUSIC]
And so on.
And then he wrote surrounding music for
it.
Let's take a look at this next slide
where he have the four parts of this,
the beginning and
ending of the first Kyrie.
As you can see he has written a bass line,
an alto line in the superius.
Actually originally they
were called the tenor,
which held out the long notes there.
Then we had the contra tenor bassos.
Then we had the contra tenor altus.
And from that we get bass and alto.
If you've ever wondered why
the alto is actually the high,
it's actually lower than the soprano.
It's because it was originally
reckoned against the tenor.
So we have tenor, bass,
alto, and then soprano.
And they were added roughly in that order.
And here we have a full
score of that Kyrie.
You can see as it plays out
through several measures.
And here now, we actually have
Machaut's original manuscript.
We can't be sure that this was in his
hand, that this is his musical hand, but
this is from the 14th century,
all four parts there.
So we're going to listen to this,
and if all goes well,
we'll follow along with the cursor on
the screen here, the superious part.
The top part up here.
So let's see if we can get it going and
we'll follow along.
[MUSIC]
Good, it worked.
So let's go back to that slide that we
saw of the interior of the cathedral.
In his will Machaut stipulated that
he wanted this mass that he composed,
in honor of the virgin to be sung in
his memory, right here at this alter,
in the entrance of the choir
on the south side.
This altar to the Virgin,
statute of the Virgin, and
here it was sung every Saturday in
perpetuity, or at least for centuries.
So, what's the point?
What's the take away here
with the Machaut Mass?
Well, several things.
First, we're very close to seeing the
labeling of voice parts that we know them.
This idea of soprano,
alto, tenor and bass.
Also, we have a large split in terms
of the range between soprano and bass.
Greater seniority, it means it sounds
goods and we have a long piece,
20 to 25 minutes.
Because what he has done is to bind
them all together by using a common
motive or theme.
One melody that sounds
throughout all five movements.
[MUSIC]
That's the binding.
The adhesive there.
Most important we have
the concept of a mass.
Other composers, later composers,
Palestrina, Bach, Mozart, Beethoven,
Brookners, Travinski.
They composed in Palifini, the five
sections of the ordinary of the mass.
As we've said, Kyrie, Gloria,
Credo Sanctus, and Agnus Dei.
With his mass Machaut
had set the standard.