[MUSIC]
>> So far, our investigation of music
during the Middle Ages has centered on
religious music.
Music of the Roman Catholic Church.
Then the only Christian
religion in the European west.
But, there was also secular music,
non-religious music, and for
that, there was popular secular music.
Well what was this pop music like?
We really have no idea.
Or at least little idea, why?
Because the people who created
the pop music were illiterate,
couldn't read or write.
In the middle ages,
almost everyone was illiterate,
the only people who were literate.
Who could write things down,
well they were the clergy, and
they tended to write down religious music.
So pop musicians made, but
had no capacity to record their music.
And thus,
almost all of it has disappeared.
But, some secular, non-religious music,
does survive from the aristocratic courts.
This music was created by the troubadours
and trouvères, and sometimes by the same
priests who were composing sacred music
for the church, but also appearing in
court from time to time, and
in that context, wrote down secular music.
Michaud, for example, worked at the court
of several kings around Europe.
The King of Bohemia,
the King of [INAUDIBLE] and
The King of France in
the course of his long career.
So let's look now at the secular song and
dance centered at the courts.
And to do this, we have to call on
a true expert, our guest for the day.
So welcome again to another segment
of Introduction to Classical Music.
I'm delighted to have with us today,
my good friend and
colleague here at Yale, Grant Herreid.
Grant not only teaches music at Yale,
he is a world-renowned professional
early music performance specialist.
And indeed, Grant just got off
an airplane a day or so ago.
Now, where were you, Austria,
something like that?
>> I was in Austria, in Melk, and in
another little town in a little mini tour.
>> So he works out of New Haven, he also
works as many professional musicians do
these days, out of New York City and
travels around the world,
playing in a professional group
called Pifero, and one or
two others that we don't
have time to go into today.
But what we're gonna do is take you
through some of these instruments
that were the primary media of
performance in the Middle Ages.
And we're going to look at some
slides here, and Grant and
I are going to comment on those slides,
and you will be seeing those slides too.
I showed this to Grant a couple of moments
ago, and this is entirely unscripted and
unrehearsed, and
he recognized it immediately.
So, what is this?
>> It's from the, a large work in Sienna,
called the effects of good government,
from the 14th century, right?
>> Yeah.
I remember I actually took this photo,
I remember being way up kind of high on a
wall, it occupied an entire wall of that.
And in terms of looking at this,
what do you see by way of
performance activity here?
>> It's one of two examples in iconography
of, at least, of ladies dancing.
And you can see here, the dancers
doing some sort of a circle dance,
which would have been called a Carole,
to the accompaniment of one
of the ladies playing a drum.
And since her mouth is open,
it is possible that she is also singing.
So a dance song.
>> Yeah, so the whole idea of singing,
and our English word Carol,
is probably related to this,
in one way or another.
Let's look at another one.
This particular image comes from France.
That much I know for sure, 14th
century in the bibliotheque le somail,
in the collection Franc Francais there.
And we have a group of figures to
the right, and then another dance there,
but once again,
most likely this was being sung.
The text [FOREIGN].
>> Oh, you can read that.
>> Yes.
>> You're a better man that I.
>> [FOREIGN] And in fact,
this is from his [FOREIGN],
at a moment where the poet,
Michaud himself, encounters his lady.
Much younger than himself,
dancing with her friends.
And it says clearly in the text,
that they're dancing without
musical instruments.
>> Oh, really?
>> And they're providing all the music
themselves with their voices.
And I think at one point,
she raises her little finger and
beckons him to join the group.
And it's his turn to sing, and so
he sings this song [CROSSTALK].
>> Fascinating.
Well, let's look at, now,
you mentioned that this one would
have been danced to simply song.
But people sing and
dance, obviously, today.
Let's look at another image here.
And on the right side of the screen,
we actually have one of
these dance manuscripts.
This again from the collection
at the Biblioteca Nacional.
And then on the left, more importantly,
if we've had the full image here,
we would have dancers and
the instrument that is accompanying here.
So tell us, Grant,
about this particular instrument please.
>> This is known as the vielle.
And it is the, sort of, the work horse
of the medieval minstrel we feel.
Probably one of the main instruments
to accompany both Troubadour singing,
to accompany the Trouvere poetry in parts.
And also probably to provide dance music.
>> Yeah, so it might be going a bit
too far, but in an odd sort of way,
almost etymologically, or
at least organographically,
it's related to the guitar,
in some odd kinds of ways.
Distantly, and we'll get into that as we
go through some of the Vielles in the 15th
and 16th century.
But it was almost a factotum.
You could a lot of things with
this particular instrument.
Let's look at some other slides.
I'm gonna ask Grant to comment
on this one in particular,
because here we have a different kind of
position for the instrument, the Vielle.
>> It's often hard to tell how large
an instrument is, from iconography.
Often the painters seem to take
liberties with the dimensions of things.
But we know from practical experience,
that a smaller Vielle,
you can play up on your arm,
like we play the violin.
The larger ones, you'd have to play
down more like a cello or something, so
that seems to be what this fellow
is doing, with his crossed leg.
>> Yeah.
So again,
this instrument is called the Vielle,
spelled V-I-E-L-L-E, vielle, and
here is another representation
from Italy around 1400.
Maybe not too much we can say about that.
Any comments that you wanna add there,
Grant?
>> This one is one that seems
to have a [INAUDIBLE] string,
a string that's off the fingerboard.
So just a plain drone that gives us
a clue as to the sort of droney types
of accompaniment that these early
fiddle players may have used.
>> And I think this may be the last one of
these that we're going to take a look at.
It's a lot later,
it comes from the times of Raphael
in Rome in the early 16th century.
But it's a particularly
beautiful example of a Vielle.
And what do you see here?
What strikes you about this?
>> And this is a depiction of
Apollo playing the lyre, and
in the early Renaissance, the lira
da braccio, the lyre that you played
on your arm like that, was the main
representation of Apollo's lyre.
And you can see that it has seven pegs,
and therefore seven strings,
and that's also an imitation
of the ancient lyre of Apollo,
which was supposed to have
seven strings as well.
>> Yeah.
Okay well those are some
images of the principle
string instrument of the Middles Ages,
the Vielle.
We're now going to back and take a look
at some other dance representations.
But before we do that, we want to actually
hear the sound of the Vielle, and
I think Grant's going to be able to
demonstrate this, on his own instrument.
>> This is a copy
that looks very much like one of
the depictions that we just showed.
And the main way that they played it seems
to have been up on the arm like this.
[MUSIC]
So, but as the other fella had it on his
leg, you could also play it in this style.
[MUSIC]
>> Cool.
So that's the way it sounded in the Middle
Ages, although this is a reproduction.
Right?
This does not come from the 14th Century.
>> No, there are no Vielles from that.
I think the earliest one that anyone plays
is actually played by Jordi Savall, and
it comes from the early 16th Century.
>> I see, yeah,
the Spanish early music specialist.
Well, let's go on.
We're gonna look at some more slides now,
and you're going to join us.
Here is one from England, as you can see,
and we want to focus now on
what we do see here accompanying
instruments, clearly, a bagpipe, and
some [INSUDIBE] here,
and then our next slide.
Thoughts about this, Grant?
>> The common, sort of dance band of
the late 14th or early 15th century or
throughout the 15th century, in fact,
was the alte capello, or the loud band.
Comprised of shams,
the early sort of oboe type instruments,
oboe and english horn, and often a brass
instrument, either a slides trumpet or
an early trombone, which was called
Sackbut, in England and France.
>> So we're gonna get to a representation
of that little bit later on.
Let's look at a manuscript.
It's not too much that
we have to say about,
we're going back to that same manuscript
of some of this medieval dance music.
This dates from the 14th century.
And, one can transcribe this material,
if we look carefully, we could actually
point at the little stems going up and
down, and
they're the precursors of the stems and
flags that we have on notational symbols
today, what we call notes today.
And then we can take this early manuscript
here, and as my friend, Tim McGee,
who teaches at the University of Toronto,
has done and edited in modern notation.
So over to the left, you see a facsimile
of the original notation, and I could take
you through that with regard to semibreves
and breves and that kind of thing, but
we end up with quarter notes and
eighth notes and half notes.
So, now, we're going to hear the
instrument that was foregrounded there,
this double reed instrument called
the Shewm, S-H-E-W-M, Shewm.
So, Grant, what do we have here?
What's this thing?
>> This is what we call the Alto size.
This again is a modern reproduction.
We don't really know what
kind of reeds they played on,
since none of the reeds survived.
But whole collections of different sizes
of Shawms do survive from the early
renaissance.
And this is modeled on one of those.
It's also called the Bombard, because
it resembled a type of early cannon.
[SOUND]
>> [LAUGH] It sounds like one, too.
So are you gonna play it?
>> This is a bit of that.
[CROSSTALK]
>> So if all goes well,
we're gonna have a phrase or so
of the dance, the Es Stampede, the stomp,
if you will, from the Middle Ages,
played on the Shawm.
[MUSIC]
Great, so that's a little taste
of music from the middle ages,
specifically instrumental music,
specifically dance music,
played on and demonstrated by Grant
here on the Vielle and on the Shawm.
And we're gonna pick this up next time,
when we come to a session on music and
the renaissance.
Thanks very much.