[MUSIC]
Middle Ages, Renaissance.
What do these terms mean and
where do we get them?
Middle Ages,
well if they were in the middle of
something what was on either side?
Indeed two periods,
that are perhaps more stable and
perhaps more classical
in modes of thinking.
The Middle Ages then, were between
Classical Antiquity of Ancient Greece and
Rome and
the rebirth of classical ideas and
classical ideals in what
we call the renaissance.
Where do we get this term,
renaissance, rebirth?
Well that was first coined not until
the 19th century around 1860 by
a German historian Yaka Burkhart.
And it was intended to signal a renewed
interest in classical antiquity,
particularly of Ancient Rome.
Well, they say a picture is
worth a thousand words, so
let's have a look at one,
indeed more than one.
Here we see the Roman forum,
as it presently looks with the remains of
temples with columns and capitals,
both Corinthian and Ionic.
Now the famous Pantheon in the center
of Rome, again with columns,
capitols, a triangular penta metume,
and a rotunda.
Now we see architecture from 1500
years later, from the Renaissance,
from Palladio's Villa Rotonda near
Vincenza, Italy, but yet again,
the columns with Ionic capitals,
a triangular pedimentum, and a rotunda.
And now another view, straight on.
The Middle Ages were not so kind to Rome.
There was crime, organized and
disorganized, and decay.
The city of Rome went,
you'll never believe this, but it's true,
went from a population of more than
a million at the time of Caesar Augustus,
to somewhere around 25,000
in the 14th century.
Wolves ran through the sections
of the city, looking for corpses.
And the pope,
during most of the late middle ages,
didn't even reside in Rome for
nearly a century,
he lived in what was to become France
in what is today Avignon, France.
By the mid-fifteenth century,
however, Rome was on the mend,
a period of economic ascend, ensued.
The Pope had returned, and
the citizens were starting to rebuild.
And they, and their fellow citizens
in city-states such as Florence and
Sienna, rebuilt and
refashioned society and in so
doing, they asked,
How should city government work?
What should a building look like?
What should a sculpture look like?
Where should it go?
How should politicians behave?
How should a politician's
speech be organized and so on?
For answers they turned to models in
classical antiquity and made it reborn.
How did this renaissance apply to music?
Well less well, because almost everything
usable from classical antiquity,
the music itself and the musical
instruments have been lost or destroyed.
There was as far as they knew,
no surviving music.
But they did have a lot of books on music
theory and many literary references that
talked about how music was constructed and
how it worked in society.
One important point that Renaissance
musicians took away from these
reports about ancient music in classical
times was that it was powerful.
Music could move the listener, could have
a powerful emotional effect on the hearer.
So musicians of the renaissance devoted
a lot of time to creating a kind of
music that would move the listener and
they did so, as we will see,
by tying music to the text.
By having the music underscore,
reinforce, amplify,
the meaning of the text in ways that
it hadn't during the Middle Ages.