[MUSIC]
Humanism, let's begin our
discussion of musical humanism by
taking a trip to the Renaissance
city par excellence, to Florence.
We'll start with how it
looked in the Renaissance.
Here you see in the center the great Duomo
of Florence, to the left, over here,
the church of Santa Maria Novella,
the train station is right over there.
At the moment here we see
City Hall Palazzo Vecchio,
the Signoria where
the city fathers worked.
Now we're going to start up at the top of
this building with a slide that shows us
the city hall as it presently looks.
And now we're going to go
down to street level, and
we are going to focus on this sculpture,
this statue right here.
And now we're going to
see that same sculpture.
On the right, a copy of the statue of
David by Michelangelo on the street.
On the left, the original where
it now rest inside the Accademia.
The original was brought
indoors In the 19th century.
But before then the city had a tradition.
Florence had a tradition of displaying
the great works of art of its citizens for
all to see.
But indoor or outdoor,
either way, this David
is very different from the sort of
sculpture that we saw in the Middle Ages.
Medieval sculpture, taking again,
an example from the beautiful Cathedral
of Chartres, tends to be fully clothed,
somewhat impersonal and
representing archetypes.
Michelangelo's David,
obviously, is very different.
His seems to glorify, indeed revel in
the beauty of a perfect human form.
And we have a name here,
a human being associated with this
sculpture of David, Michelangelo.
By contrast, the most prolific artist in
the Middle Ages was Master Anonymous.
Here we see the Cathedral of Chartres,
massive.
But we don't know who designed it or
who built it.
Now you see a tryptic of sorts.
And we've come to realize
that in the Middle Ages,
all inspiration came from, comes from God.
Hildegard on the right looks heavenward
for revelation and receives it.
The Holy Spirit, as see in the center
with St. Thomas, and on the left with St.
Gregory, the Holy Spirit
sits on their shoulder,
in the form of a dove
communicating the divine word.
Artists, as we see here in the next slide,
they didn't bother to sign their works.
Here we have three magnificent specimens,
but all three are anonymous.
But when we come into the Renaissance,
there's a real person.
The inspiration comes from God yes, but
a human can now shape it,
fashion it according to his vision.
And again, he has a name,
that of Leonardo or Michelangelo or
of Shakespeare.
And what these artists
created were oftentimes
works that gave pleasure
to other human beings.
Yes, they dealt with religion often, but
they also dealt with other themes as well
such as nature and
the delights of this world.
Here we see Botticelli's,
Springtime in the Uffizi in Florence.
And compare here the essence of youthful
beauty on the right from the Botticelli,
from the Renaissance, with the abstract
medieval notion of a beautiful woman
on the left from the Middle Ages.
And there is a love of
the good things of this world.
Here's Leonardo's portrait of the young
mistress of the Duke of Milan.
Well she's certainly well
coiffed in fine jewelry and
holding in her hand her pet ermine or
pet mink.
Life is good.
These human creators such as Leonardo
da Vinci were valuable as creators,
as artists.
And patrons fought over them.
Artists had rivalries with one another.
Leonardo with Michelangelo,
they were not good friends.
The musician,
Josquin des Prez in one case,
played one patron off against
another to double his salary.
And the artist could get rich.
Michelangelo died with an estate of
about $10 million in today's money.
And what these artists created could
be evaluated on a scale of good and
bad by other human beings.
The concept of artistic value,
of artistic criticism,
of worth to society comes into
being during the Renaissance.
And even today we speak of humanism,
but more often of the the humanities.
He's majoring in the humanities for
example.
Well, what exactly do we mean
by the study of the humanities?
Well, evaluation, deep critical thinking,
comparison of literature, of the acts
of history, of art and of the history of
art, of music and of the history of music.
Comparison of styles and
of composers, that's what we're
doing here in this course.
And it all goes back to the Renaissance.