[MUSIC]
Let's talk now about the musical
instruments of the renaissance.
And to do that we're going back
just a little bit in time.
Back into the late middle
ages into the mid-evil church
which takes us to this instrument.
The organ.
Organs really came into being in
churches not until the 14th century.
They first appeared in the big cathedrals.
And they were always placed high
on the walls of the church for
all to see and hear.
These powerful organs were
the marvel of the age.
The represented cutting edge technology,
a measurement of pipes, the density
of materials, the distribution of
a consistent and constant wind pressure.
They were the space shot
of the middle ages.
And so they were placed high so
that all could see.
Here we have the earliest surviving organ,
coming from the late 14th
century from Sion, Switzerland.
It's in playable condition, so
let's hear a bit of its sound.
[MUSIC]
Here we see two more organs, two slightly
later organs from the 15th century.
On the left is a stationary one.
And then on the right, a movable one.
The stationary one on the left comes
from England or the low countries.
The one on the right comes from Germany.
The one on the left, because it is
stationary, is called a positive organ.
The one on the right, because it can
be moved around, a portative one.
So, positive, portative.
Here's a slide from Innsbruck,
Austria, 16th century.
We're moving a little later now into the
Renaissance, 16th century, as it sits in
what was then the Chapel of the Holy
Roman Emperor in Innsbruck, Austria.
It's now, of course, larger, and
it sits high on a wall as we have said.
And let's listen again to
that same organ music.
That organ music was in fact written for
this particular organ by the German
composer Paul Hofheimer.
[MUSIC]
The Gregorian Chant, is actually
in the middle part, in the tenor.
And up above, we have a great deal
of musical ornamentation.
Embellishment in this
top part as you hear.
All right, that was a quick introduction
to the organ of the late middle ages and
renaissance, but
what about string keyboard instruments?
Well, they existed too from
the 14th century onward.
Let's look at a manuscript of
the 14th century, 14th century
dance music written for
a medieval string keyboard instrument.
It actually comes from
the British library in London.
Notice that the musical notation of blood
is a little bit similar to
our contemporary notation.
But underneath we have letter names A,
Bs, Cs.
I see a couple of Ds here,
C B flat, A and so on.
So we had a dual system.
But it was eventually abandoned.
The letters were dropped, leaving musical
notation to develop as we know it today.
Let's hear just a little bit of this
dance music played by an early keyboard.
[MUSIC]
Pretty cool, very attractive music.
But for more discussion of these
renaissance instruments let's bring back
our expert, Bret Herod.
>> Okay.
Welcome back to another segment of
Introduction to classical music.
Today we're gonna be dealing specifically
with music of the Renaissance, and
even more specifically with musical
instruments and more, more,
more specifically with
keyboard instruments.
We're gonna start with
So on the screen you see a representation,
a painting, 16th century
Flemish painting in which a young
woman is playing the harpsichord.
And I have with me again today,
delighted to have my friend and colleague
Grant Herrod here who's an expert in this,
knows far more about it than I do.
To explain these sorts of things to us.
So what's of interest here with
this particular instrument,
which I think is called a Clavichord.
>> Yes, and this often played
by young ladies apparently.
But what strikes us most is the hand
position showing very clearly.
>> [LAUGH]
>> That they did not use their thumbs.
>> Yeah.
Did you ever take piano lessons?
>> Oh yeah.
[LAUGH]
>> So
what would happen if your teacher
ever saw you playing like that?
>> I would have been slapped.
>> Kaboom.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah you can't do that.
Really.
Through the time of Bach.
Often at E.
Well Bach was the first to use the film,
but he was still using his 3
over 3 over 3 type of approach.
But it's interesting
because as we look at these
keyboard instruments of the Renaissance,
we see that rather early on,
they had somewhat advanced
instruments here.
So here is a representation, a detailed
diagram, of a keyboard instrument.
In this case a harpsichord
coming from the mid
15th century from the Court of Burgundy
from someone named Arnault de Zolle.
It's preserved in
the Bibliotheque Nationale again.
Here is, as you can see,
the shape of the instrument.
Here are the keys down there.
And if you had time,
you could even watch this run up
from low C up to the A at the top and
the chromatic notes.
It's a fully chromatic keyboard
here by the mid-15th century.
So Grant,
one thing that always puzzled me,
but probably the same thing on the loop,
what are these designs here?
Yes the decorated sound holes or
rosettes they would be called,
just like the F and
C holes on string instruments,
they just allow the sound to
escape from the sound box.
>> Okay so
the sound is vibrating inside of
these instruments
>> And
you've got to let it out in some way.
>> Just like the sound hole in
a guitar but, a modern guitar, but
in the Renaissance
everything was decorated and
they would not just have a big round
empty hole in their sound board?
>> And the interesting thing here is,
in the upper right, where the inventor,
Arnault de Zolle, gives us a very clear
diagram of the jack mechanism that would
be the basis for sound production In the
harpsichord, which exists at this time but
we are going to explore it a little bit
later on when we get to baroque music.
This time we are going to London,
to the National Gallery in London
near Trafalgar Square there.
And we see a painting,
16th century painting by Hans Holbein.
And you can see on the screen
the arrow that directs our
attention to some musical materials,
specifically the Lute,
and Grant's going to tell us a little
about the structure of the lute,
how it works, and
then he's going to demonstrate for us.
>> You can see very clearly in
the foreground the peg box,
bent at an angle holding the twelve
pegs of this six-course instrument.
And-
>> What's that mean, a course?
>> The lute has pairs of strings
[MUSIC]
Although the top string,
the treble string, is usually a single.
And so they're arranged in six pairs or
courses.
And you see in the depiction,
a lute very much like this one with frets,
pieces of gut, tied around the neck.
Just to show you where
to put your fingers.
And a round back,
always made of ribs of wood,
glued together over a mold.
A decorated sound hole, as usual.
>> Again, as we said last time,
for the sound, so it can escape.
Let's look at another picture here,
because we see something called lute
tablature, you have to be able to read
this special sort of notation, right?
>> That's right, it's some of the earliest
music that we know was written for
a specific instrument is for
the lute, because of the tablature,
or the system of notation,
that is peculiar to the lute.
And here the young lady is playing, again,
this early kind of 16th century lute,
but you see that she's
resting it on the table.
[MUSIC]
And by doing so,
it actually makes the lute slightly
more round and sound it a little louder.
>> The table becomes a resonator.
>> Even a modern synthetic table, but
an old wooden table really
enhances the sound of the lute.
>> That's remarkable.
Well you want to play just
a little bit of something for us?
Anything that strikes your fancy.
[MUSIC]
Lovely, and what was that by the way?
Anything you made,
something you just made up?
[LAUGH]
>> Something when I was feeling blue
one day.
>> I see.
You made that up, okay.
But it sounded very much
in the Renaissance style,
because it was modal, I guess.
Let's see some more slides here.
We're going to take a look at one that
represents a typical early Renaissance
dance scene.
Grant, once again,
here your is there up in the balcony.
>> Yes, the alta capella, or loud man,
again playing their schawms and
slide trumpet for
the accompaniment of probably.
>> Mm-hm yeah.
Probably a wedding scene and
then here they are in the upper right in
the boudoir,
after the dancing in the banquet hall.
Now this is an interesting slide because
it's actually a cover of a record jacket,
involving the ensemble Piffaro.
And you are a member of that.
>> I have played with Piffaro.
>> How many years have
you played with him?
>> Probably about 20 years.
>> Oh yeah.
I didn't realize it was 20 years old.
You must have started when you were five.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But what this is,
is actually it was something on the wall
of the town hall in Nuremberg Germany,
painted by Albrecht Durer, and
then later on somebody came along and
did a specific painting
of this larger mural.
So we see a lot of
musical instruments here.
And again, it's this standard Renaissance
band that Grant has been telling us about.
So what instrument's do
we see here once more?
>> Right, we see the two shawms in
the foreground, leaning over the balcony.
Next to them is sackbut,,
or the early trombone,
which was a technological advancement
over the earlier slide trumpet,
which was slightly more cumbersome.
>> So let's take a look at another slide
here quickly, and as you can see, this one
comes from the low countries around 1600s
probably even a little bit after that.
But it's a particularly good
representation of some of
those instruments.
So what do we see here,
Grant, moving right to left?
>> Right, well,
because it is a little later,
they're probably playing five-part music.
And we have a large sackbut but
playing the bass, two sort of alto sized
shawms on the middle lines, and
on the top, a pair of cornetti.
The corneto usually slightly curved
with a kind of a mouthpiece on the top,
and it has finger holes like a recorder or
a clarinet.
But the mouthpiece resembles
a brass instrument.
And so it has very much a sound in
between a trumpet and sort of a recorder.
>> We may get to hear this
a little bit later on.
So this is a dinosaur, in a sense,
this instrument doesn't really.
The Lute we still see around,
the Trombone we still see around
in effect for the sackbut tombone,
but we don't see many-
>> Yeah, the cornetto sort of died out.
Right throughout the 17th century, and
by the end of the 17th century hardly
anyone was playing it anymore it seems.
>> Well, let's have a demonstration
of these various instruments now.
Which should we start with?
Maybe I guess historically,
you want to do the-
>> I'll start with the cornetto, yeah.
With the finger holes and
the trumpet-like mouth piece.
[MUSIC]
>> How many different, if you picked
up the lute, the sackbut, the viola.
How many different instruments-
>> Let me try it one more time.
>> No, no, how many different
instruments do you play?
>> I play a lot of them to a point.
You know, but
it's hard to specialize in all [CROSSTALK]
>> So we're not expecting a performance.
>> I'll just play it just a few notes.
>> Okay.
>> I'm sorry.
>> No, [INAUDIBLE] it's great.
Let's move on now to the brass instrument.
We've got the slide trumpet,
which is the precursor to the trombone,
right, I mean had this.
>> Right.
The trumpet can't play very many notes.
[SOUND] Just the sort of fanfare
notes of the harmonic series, and so
in the 14th century seems they developed
this technology of making
the trumpet longer and shorter.
[SOUND]
>> Really cool.
So, that's how the trombone got started.
>> Well, it brought the trumpet players
into the sort of world of dance music,
I imagine.
But later part in the middle ages and
the early renaissance,
they discovered that a double
slide made the work of
changing the length of
the tubing much more efficient.
[MUSIC]
And the trombone, or
large trumpet, was invented.
Again, in England and France and
other countries, called the sackbut.
>> Okay, well those are some of the dance
instruments of the renaissance.
Let's take a look at,
by going to our screen now, and
take a look at a manuscript.
A rather fancy manuscript because it
was put together for a princess of
the royal house in the low countries
in the late 15th, early 16th centuries.
It's a so-called basch dance manual,
but it's rather kind of fancy.
You ever worked with this at all or maybe?
>> I have.
And what's curious is that, it's just,
every note is the same
length in a tenor range, and
it seems that the early dance musicians
would use this to improvise over.
>> Yeah, almost like a maybe a standard
blues pattern today, a certain length for
one low bass note and then the next bass
notes got to go through so many bars and
the next bass notes gotta go-
>> Very much.
And, we've noticed in each of these
depictions of Renaissance Minstrels
playing these instruments,
they are never reading music.
And it seems that their specialty,
like a modern Dixieland band or
something was to learn
a bunch of repertory, and
be able to play by ear, from memory,
and of course improvising dance music.
>> Yeah, and of course all popular
musicians operate that way today.
Why would they ever need music?
They're really good musicians.
>> Right.
>> Okay, so that's an actual dancing
manual because underneath here,
if you can see these other letters,
you can see the r for [FOREIGN],
a big sweeping bow, and then the little
shake, or equivalent of the [FOREIGN].
And then two [FOREIGN] and
a couple of [FOREIGN] in a row, and on.
So this manuscript is giving us
the steps for the dance, as well.
And if you're really good,
we will demonstrate the dance for
you a little bit later on.
And a final slide.
Let's look at this one.
We can't be sure this is
really Queen Elizabeth or not.
In some corners it's thought to be Queen
Elizabeth, some not thought to be her.
And it clearly a representation
of a couple here dancing
a galliard,
which was a fast leaping dance.
Galliard was preceded by a pavane.
Here we can see some of the stringed
instruments accompanying.
But this pair of pavane and
galliard became the standard
dances of the Renaissance.
You'll remember that we saw a dancing
manual from the Renaissance.
That manuscript written in silver and
gold on black vellum, with the music and
dance steps written in.
The two principal dances of the
Renaissance were, again, the Pavane and
the Galliard.
The pavane was a slow, stately dance
recommended for processions and
dances involving old people.
The galliard, as we saw with our leaping
queen, probably Queen Elizabeth I,
was much faster and more athletic.
To give you a sense of the slow,
stately pavane, I conned my friend
Grant Harrod to dance with me.
Remember what Grant pointed out.
Not only did men and women dance together,
but women danced with women in
the Renaissance and the Middle Ages,
and men danced with men.
Gender didn't matter all that much.
Getting the steps right did.
Again, we'll now see a Renaissance pavane,
danced with music supplied
by the ensemble Pifaro.
[MUSIC]