[FOREIGN]
>> Despite
the popularity of instrumental
dance music in the Renaissance,
sacred religious music from
the Renaissance continued to thrive.
Sacred music for
the Roman Catholic Church.
Some of it later for
the Protestant Church as we'll soon see.
But for the religious music of
the Catholic church in the Renaissance,
we need to go back to Rome.
Here we see obviously, the front of St.
Peter's, with the Pope's quarters and
the Sistine Chapel on the right.
Now looking in the opposite direction
we see Saint Peter's on the right and
the papal quarters on the left.
Now we're gonna go up on
the top of Saint Peter's and
look down at the Sistine Chapel and
the papal apartments.
The papal stanzas, rooms,
as they are called.
Some of which are beautifully
decorated by Frescoes by Raphael.
Here is his School of Athens from
around 1500 in which he painted, and
I think I can point this out to you,
he painted Leonardo here,
he painted Michelangelo here and
he painted himself, Raphael, right here.
But back to the rooftop.
So here's the roof of the Sistine Chapel,
now we're gonna go on the other side of
that roof to see Michelangelo's
famous creation, the ceiling
of the Sistine Chapel with Creation and
the Expulsion of Adam and Eve.
And now we're gonna switch to the high
alter end of the Sistine Chapel.
And the Last Judgement by Michelangelo,
notice here
on the lower right, the gallery,
see if I can point to it right here.
The gallery, this was the or the balcony,
this is where the singers came out and
stood during the services, and
they still do today at this spot.
They were grouped around a lectern,
as we see, not from Italy, but
from France in this period.
But it's a particularly good view of
the lectern, all grouped around the music,
up in front of them there,
all singing together.
Now I wanna go over to Saint Peter's
just for a moment and make a point.
This is a very big church,
the largest church in the world.
As you look around here,
there's one thing that's missing
that's found in most churches.
It's missing too in the Sistine Chapel and
that's the organ.
The only organ that I
could recently find at St.
Peters was this one, a small one tucked
away in the Nave of the Basilica.
Organs and instruments generally did not
play a role in the religious music here,
and certainly not in the Sistine Chapel.
In the Sistine Chapel there was always,
and
is still today, a tradition of
singing without instruments.
So we have this term,
A Capella Sistina in the Sistine Chapel.
And from it, we derive this term
A Capella, A Capella singing.
The music performed here
in the Sistine Chapel,
in the Renaissance and
ever since is in A Capella style.
But let's hear some of that music and
to do so we turn to the music [FOREIGN].
Here is a wood cut of this composure made
in the 17th century from a lost painting.
And here is an original manuscript,
still in the Vatican collection,
showing a mass by Josquin for four voices.
Here at the top with the red arrow,
you can see Jousquinous Desprez.
Four voice mass, soprano and
tenor on the left side of the page
alto and bass on the right.
Music in the Renaissance
was rarely arranged
vertically in score as we have it today.
But here is a modern vertical
score of a Monnet by Jacque.
A motet is a genre of sacred music.
Usually setting a Latin text
intended to be sung in church or
possibly in a devotional context at home.
In the Renaissance the motet was almost
always written in polyphonic texture and
involved imitation.
Here you can see the numbers on the score,
I've labeled them obviously one,
two, three, and four and
these represent little themes or
motifs that are sung in imitation.
So we've mentioned a number of terms here.
Let's review these terms
by means of the next slide.
A Capella means of course singing
without instrumental accompaniment.
Motet, a genre of religious music.
Usually setting a Latin text,
virtually anything other than
devotional music besides a mass.
Polyphony, obviously more
than one voice at a time.
Imitation, voices repeating for
a short period of time what
a preceding voice had done.
And voice pairing, well,
two voices could play off against
another set of two voices.
We'll see that in just a minute.
All right, now let's see how this
works in a motet by Josquin.
Here is his Ave Maria.
We'll start with just the Latin
text that Josquin is setting here.
It tells the story of the virgin
as recorded in the Bible and
expanded on during the Middle Ages.
Josquin structured his music
around the existing structure
of this particular chant, Ave Maria.
He doesn't borrow the chant,
just the text.
But he emphasizes the structure of
the text through the music he creates.
In a particular way.
Each starts with a tune line
salutation as you can see here.
Ave Maria grazia playing hail Mary we
will be with you serene virgin and so on.
Then follow a succession of five stanzas.
You won't see them all here, but
five stanzas each with four lines
that run the various events
in the life of the virgin,
conception, her birth,
enunciation, and so on.
And finally it ends with
another two line petition,
petition peroration if you will.
Petition to the virgin to intercede on
behalf of the petitioner, the listener.
At the hour of our death.
Josquin sets this text as we
have seen in a particular way.
It has a particular structure
that gives it humanistic clarity.
Okay, so let's listen to this piece now.
[MUSIC]
>> [FOREIGN]
>> Opening salutation.
Soprano and alto, tenor and bass.
Soprano, alto,
tenor and bass.
The lord be with you, again,
soprano, alto, tenor.
Bass.
>> [FOREIGN]
>> Soprano with virgo.
>> First stanza.
[MUSIC]
Soprano and alto together.
Entered by tenor and bass together.
[MUSIC]
Now we're talking about fully singing,
everybody rejoicing together.
[INAUDIBLE]
[MUSIC]
Building up to a climax,
watch what the tenor does.
[MUSIC]
Leaping up.
Second stanza.
[MUSIC]
Let's sing, gambit, soprano,
alto, tenor and bass is pursued.
[MUSIC]
It's coming down soprano,
alto, tenor, bass
[MUSIC]
Third stanza, altos and sopranos.
And there's some bass respond.
[MUSIC]
Annunciation was our salvation.
Now completely different meter.
[MUSIC]
Triple.
In homo-phony, not polyphony.
[MUSIC]
Triple meter.
[FOREIGN]
[MUSIC]
Now onto the final full stanza and
back to imitation.
[MUSIC]
In duple
meter and the
arrangement
soprano,
alto,
tenor and
bass.
[MUSIC]
And added pairation or
mother of God have mercy for me.
[MUSIC]
Remembering.
Well, no matter what your religion is,
that's gorgeous.
It's also a fine example
of form in a Renaissance.
Two lines, plus five times four lines,
plus two lines.
24 lines in all.
It's balanced and it's symmetrical.
More humanistic rhetoric
designed to persuade.
Balanced and symmetrical.
And let's remember, balance and
symmetry were very important in
the architecture of the renaissance.
Here we see the symmetrical structure
in Palladio's Villa Rotunda.
And it was important in painting.
In paintings by Rafael and Leonardo.
The renaissance was very much
a balanced classical age.