[MUSIC]
In the early 16th century another
religion, initially a splinter group, or
breakaway group, began to protest the
practices of the Roman Catholic Church,
protests with regards to
religious doctrine and economics.
The flow of money heading south
from Germany into Italy and
specifically to Rome.
They ultimately were call
the Protest Tents, or the Protestants.
Here's a painting of the man who initiated
the Protestant Reformation, Martin Luther.
Luther was not only a theologian but
a skilled musician.
Indeed, his favorite composer was
the fore-heard Josquin Des Prez.
"The notes regulate (control) other
composers with Josquin, however,
he governs the notes." And indeed,
Martin Luther himself was a composer.
Here you see a slide of a a tenor.
Let's take a look at the specifics
with the pointer here.
Up at the top, we see the 46 there.
What would that be [FOREIGN].
So, this is in Latin,
written by Martinus Luther.
But the text here of this song
that Luther created is in German.
German was supposed to be part of
the service of the Lutheran religion.
This is a composition again
that Luther himself created.
We call it a chorale,
what other denominations would call
simply a hymn tune, so Martin Luther
has created a choral tune here.
We're going to listen to it.
And as we listen to it,
notice that it is actually in octaves.
But each of the octaves is
separated according to voice.
We have a bass voice, a tenor voice,
and a female voice in the soprano.
So, let's hear it now.
Monophonic texture.
>> [MUSIC]
>> So, that's the first strophy
from this tenor part book.
Talk about that in a moment.
Just has the music for
the tenor not the other parts in it.
All right, let's take a look here
by of what about what we just said.
Let's take a look at a slide
that gives us some terms.
Protestant Reformation,
Martin Luther, Chorale Tune,
again same thing as a Hymn Tune,
Part Book.
By that we mean a book
containing just one vocal part.
Monophonic texture that we heard there.
Polyphonic texture,
well let's go back and listen to that and
we could even throw in here the term
homophonic texture because in a way
that's what we have with the next slide.
Let's take a look at the next slide and
before we get to it.
Let's observe the following that we're
not going to have the music here
be exactly what the music we see on
the screen be exactly what we are hearing.
We are going to hear
Luther's original music
helped along here by
an arrangement by Yohan Valter.
Luther's original music With a score,
certainly a different score,
from the 19th century.
The melody that you will hear,
you'll see in the soprano part is
actually being sung in the tenor line.
Let's have a listen.
>> [MUSIC]
[MUSIC]
>> Maybe we'll fade that out now.
Let's take a look at a map,
see where we are.
By the mid 15th century
most of northern Europe
had blown over to the Protestant cause.
Cities such as Augsburg and Munich,
well they were sort of half and half.
Swing cities.
Vienna was still fully Catholic,
Innsbruck, and so on down to Italy.
The Catholic church who has since
fought back in the form of the counter
reparation and for the counter reparation
we're going to go back to Rome and
take a look at an image of St.
Peters as it is being built.
So, here we are.
In the Vatican,
this is the Sistine Chapel here.
This is the roof of the Sistine Chapel.
This is the great dome of St.
Peter's designed in part by Michelangelo.
You can even see the workmen up there
Let's go into the Sistine Chapel.
This was, again,
the time of the counter-reformation and
the Council of Trent.
What was the Council of Trent?
Well, it was a gathering
of all the leaders,
all the male leaders of the church.
To determine how to respond to
the protestant reformation.
On this slide you see that victory, here,
will be that of the faithful Catholics.
You see the allegorical figure of
victory wearing a papal tiara.
Now, the foremost composer of
counter reformation music was.
He wrote in a pure clear style,
not too much imitation so
that the faithful could focus ont he text,
so that they could understand the text and
not just enjoy the music.
Because of this pure style of church music
He was said to be
the savior of church music.
The savior of needless to say,
Roman Catholic church music.
Here we have an image of Palestrina
on the right, presenting a volume
of his Salvific masses to Pope Marcellis.
In the 1560s.
But let's think about.
You can see the soprano
part on this piece here.
Let's think about how the sopranos were
actually performed in this period.
Who sang the soprano line?
Well, there were three possibilities And
one of them was not having women singing
the soprano or alto part because,
ever since the Bible,
there had been this proscription
against women singing in the church.
Mulier taceat in ecclesia,
the woman should be Silent in the church.
Well if that's the case,
who is going to sing the voice parts then?
Well, three possibilities,
as you can see here.
First, males singing in falsetto,
we've heard that already today,
we'll hear more of it.
Secondly, choir boys,
here's a good image of that, fresco...
Showing choir boy down below, and
older toncert clerics behind him.
And a third possibility was the castrato.
Castratis entered the Sistine Chapel
during the 1560s, and then,
during the 17th and 18th century,
because they became important in opera.
They become something similar to
the rockstar of the stage
because of their high voices,
their powerful voices, and the capacity,
as you can see by this account here.
Their capacity to hold a note for
an unbelievable amount of time.
Let's take a look at this slide from
a recent film called Farinelli.
As they say, they were something
of the rock stars of the 17th and
18th century, and we will come back to
this when we come back to Hendle and
the opera in the 18th century.
And and
although this tradition of the castrato
died out in opera, in the early
nineteenth century, around 1830,
it held on in the papal chapel
into the early twentieth century.
Here you see an image of
the last living castrato,
Alessandro Moreschi He happened
to be recorded by accident.
They wanted to record
the Pope at that time.
The Pope is busy, so they took their
recording equipment here in 1904,
next door over into the Sistine Chapel,
and asked Moreschi to sing for him.
Now, Moreschi was very old at this time.
He was about 70, and needless to say,
this recording of 19 1904 was
very early so the sound,
the audio is terrible but
at least it gives you a taste
of this extraordinary voice.
The sound of the last, in this case,
the last living castrato.
>> [MUSIC]
[MUSIC]
>> Well, as I say,
it was all the acoustics here and
the audio equipment here is not good.
But at least it gives us a hint of this
eerie sound of the Castrato voice.
Let's turn now to a modern video.
Here we have The Tallis singers,
Tallis scholars, with peter Phillips.
For my money, the finest acapella singing
group in the world, year after year.
No matter what group he has put together,
the intonation and the balance and
interpretations are always extraordinary.
Here we have two choirs.
One that you see in front
of us with five singers.
Over top of the lady in blue,
we have two gentleman there that
will singing a Gregorian Chant, and
then faintly Here in the distance
in another chapel, another choir.
And they will be singing in a way,
that once again,
tends to recreate the sound
of the castrati voice.
So, we will begin this with
Peter Phillips conducting.
And I'll comment as we go.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Homophony.
>> Soprano.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Falsetto,
tenor, bass.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Now over to the Chanting.
Slavic chant.
Rapid delivery of a psalm text, psalm 50.
>> [MUSIC]
[MUSIC]
>> Again, the part that you heard there
would have been sung by a castrato.
>> [MUSIC]
>> This motet by Allegri was sung done
during Holy Week in the Sistine Chapel in
full darkness with the castrati placed
up the niches near the famous ceiling.
Visitors for centuries came to hear it,
including the 14 year old Mozart
who heard the piece once,
walked back to his hotel room with his
father and copied it down note for note.
Remarkable, but so too is this
sound of the lost castrato voice.
But whether by Josquin des Prez or
Palestrina or
his later contemporary Allegri,
this is wonderful a cappella choral music.
Indeed, the renaissance is known
as The age of a capella singing.