[MUSIC]
We said that in the Renaissance,
written composed music became
available in written form,
to a broader segment of society.
This was part of the humanizing
of the Renaissance, and
it was driven in large
measure by technology.
Technology changed what art was and
how people experienced the world,
just as technology determines
what art is today, and
how we experience the world,
how we hear music.
The technological revolution of the
Renaissance was, of course, the printing
press, invented in Germany on the banks
of the Rhine River about 1450 or so.
And from there it spread to Italy,
first to Venice and then Rome and
then to France in Lyon and Paris.
These became the music publishing
centers of Western Europe.
On the screen you see
the finished product.
This is just one part, here again,
a tenor part book for a mass.
A singer would buy the book for just his
part book, or possibly for secular music,
her part book, the soprano voice,
the alto voice, the tenor voice, whatever.
Why would you need the other parts?
You just needed your own music,
except if you got lost,
you needed to peg off of or
reference off of the other parts.
Here on the screen now we see an image
of a printing press in action,
we see men working with movable type.
Pressmen creating multiple
sheets that had to be cut and
these sheets had to be bound.
And the proofreader had
to vet all of this,
had to vet guarantee the finished product.
This is from a French image from Paris.
And we know that there was an important
music printing working in Paris at
this time in the 1530s,
one Pierre Attaingnant.
Let's look at the title page
from one of his prints.
Here you can see one that reads,
30 Musical [FOREIGN] In Four Voices,
etc., etc.
New pieces printed by Pierre Attaingnant,
A-T-T-A-I-N-G-N-A-N-T, living at,
[FOREIGN] and so
on near the church of such and such.
And here are the 30 or so
pieces in this collection and
it is simply a part broke,
the Superius part broke.
But he tells us who he is and
where he's living.
And based on this and the location of
that church, we can actually see where
he was working here on the left bank,
within a block or so of the Sorbonne.
And interestingly enough, there's still
a bookstore, [FOREIGN], on that very spot.
Now let's see some of these part
books as they were actually viewed.
Here we see a trio, the young lady playing
on a flute from a soprano part book,
while another singer sings, presumably
from another part book in the back and
a lute fills out the harmony.
Of course, this was communal music.
It was fun, but
everybody was to be a participant.
It wasn't any such thing as
an audience as we think of it,
a large gathering of
people who just listened.
Now let's see a slide from Paris,
actually downtown Paris.
If you look in the background here,
you can see the spires of Notre Dame.
We saw that from the other
side in our session 7.
Again, here is the park book
with someone singing out of it,
conducting and
a flute is playing the soprano part.
Generally speaking, much of this secular
music was sung just one to a part.
Sometimes with instruments but
often times, a capella.
So here we have a group all singing out of
a part book, three ladies and a gentleman.
He seems to be conducting given the hand
position that he's gesturing with.
Let's listen to this.
It's a chanson by Attaingnant Tant que
vivrai performed here by Voices and Lute.
[MUSIC]
Now Pierre Atoniogne was
an enterprising fellow, and
arranged for these songs in
every sort of different way.
He wanted to make, to be bumped as much
money as he could on this enterprise.
So he raised them for voices, for
voices and instruments, for lute, for
lute and voice, recorders,
keyboard, alone, and so on.
Here's a harpsichord,
from slightly later after 1600.
It's in the Yale Collection.
Let's listen to the same chanson,
Tant que vivrai, but
now arranged for harpsichord alone.
[MUSIC]
And this brings us to the most popular
kind of vocal music of the Renaissance,
the madrigal.
The madrigal is a genre, again a type of
music, involving several solo voices,
usually four or five,
that sets to music a poem.
Most often a poem about love or
of love frustrated.
Usually only one singer sings each part.
And most often the madrigal was performed
acapella, no accompanying instruments.
More than 2,000 separate books
of madrigals published during
the Renaissance, first in Italy and
then in the low countries, and
in Germany and in England.
Usually there were 20 madrigals or
so in each volume.
So you can see that they're
somewhere between 30,000 and
40,000 of these madrigals created.
I suppose singing the madrigal
was something of a rage,
perhaps the way doo-wop was, or
maybe folk singing in the 1960s.
Let's review all this
by means of this slide.
Madrigal, what is it?
Well, it's a genre of vocal music sung,
not in Latin, but
in the vernacular language.
It could be English, it could be Italian.
Where was it generated?
Well, first in Italy, around 1530, and
then it spread to the rest of Europe.
How many?
Well, as we said, thousands.
Maybe as many as 40,000.
By the time it reached England,
we were in the Elizabethan Age,
the age of Queen Elizabeth I.
There were a number of important
musicians working at her court,
associated with her and
with London generally.
Thomas Morley, William Byrd, Orlando
Gibbons, John Wilbey, Thomas Weelkes and
collectively they formed what's
call the English Madrigal School.
So we're gonna take a listen to now,
just one Madrigal
out of an important collection
called the Triumphes of Oriana 1601,
a collection of, again,
roughly 20 or so of these Madrigals.
This collection is interesting
because each one of them,
in order to be included in this
collection, you had to end your Madrigal
with the salutation,
long live fair Oriana.
Oriana was the favored
nickname of Queen Elizabeth.
So each of these madrigals ends this way.
We're going to turn our
attention now to the madrigal
As Vesta was from Latmos Hill Descending,
by Thomas Weelkes.
Again, you can see on the screen here
six vocal parts to six part madrigal.
Each of the parts would be
sung only by one voice.
And only four of the voices,
the top four voices start out.
But let's move on now to three images.
One of the composer Wilkes who
wrote this madrigal in 1601.
Second, in the middle of course,
Queen Elizabeth the first,
the dedicatee of this madrigal.
And third, my friend and
former colleague here at Yale before,
his regretted retirement,
Simon Carrington who is the founder and
conductor for years and
years of the King Singers.
So we're gonna turn now to
a recording of the king singers.
And in it we're going
to hear the following.
We're going to listen to this madrigal
As Vesta was from hill descending.
It's full of what we call word painting or
madrigalisms.
Moments when the music
underscores the text in a direct
Onomatopoeic way,
music in the service of text.
So, I'll talk a bit as we proceed.
Let's see this music now
sung by the King's Singers.
[MUSIC]
Descending now.
That music of course is graded down,
so everybody's coming down.
Latvis hill, what do they see?
They see the Queen ascending,
so the music has to go up here.
[MUSIC]
Attended on by all.
Well we'll have a lot of voices
here cuz everybody's in.
[MUSIC]
All six voices singing in [INAUDIBLE]
So Diana's darlings,
those attending the goddess Diana,
they came running down a-mains.
So, it's going to go fast and downward.
[MUSIC]
Two by two?
Yes, two voice.
Three by three?
Yes, three voices.
[MUSIC]
You guessed it.
All alone.
[MUSIC]
And mingling with
the Shepard's,well, we'regonna
mingle here poly-phonically with
lots of imitation, busy music.
[MUSIC]
Then sang, well everybody together now,
announcement.
[MUSIC]
All the nymphs of Diana sang.
Long live Oriana.
[MUSIC]
And they sing this for
a very long time in imitation with
the bass singing in very long notes.
[MUSIC]
Sometimes the memetic nature of the music,
the memetic nature of the music,
underscoring each word or
phrase with an appropriate music
gesture gets down right silly.
But this development is hugely
important in the history of music.
It developed a vocabulary
of musical expression.
We can talk about the different periods
in the history of music, Medieval,
Renaissance, Baroque and so on.
But the two most important changes in
the history of Western music arguably,
were the switch from
oral to written music,
which occurred during the Middle Ages, and
the switch from abstract music, chant,
mass, motet, to memetic music
here again in the Renaissance.
Music became a memetic language that we
all speak, or at least can all understand.
Happy music,
well what are we gonna do with that?
We're happy, we're gonna put it in major
and probably in an upper register.
She falls down, struck down with grief.
Well that's going to be slow in tempo.
It's gonna be minor in key and
the music undoubtedly will go downward.
These are sorts of gestures
that make up this language.
In the next period in the history
of music, the Baroque period,
this language of music which originated
in vocal music, will become so
commonly understood that it can be
sounded by instruments alone, and
we all will understand it.