[MUSIC]
As we said,
opera originated in Italy around 1600.
Actually it's surprising
that it took that long.
China and Japan had had opera
ever since the 13th century.
In the West, again in Italy,
opera rose as a new genre.
Ironically by trying to re-create an old
one, ancient Greek drama, Greek tragedy.
In a very real sense, the creation of
this genre, opera, was not something new.
But a continuation of
an older humanist agendum,
the need to recapture,
recreate the power of ancient Greek music.
And indeed the very subjects,
the plots of these early operas were based
on those of ancient Greek drama or
mythology or Roman history.
But what is opera?
Well of course a drama,
a play that is sung.
That's an odd thing to do, to sing a play.
Normal human discourse
is usually not sung.
We don't go around saying you took my
parking place, I'm very angry at you.
But in opera, we do.
Why?
Because with opera,
the assumption is that the drama is
powerful and that the music is powerful.
And if you could put the two together,
you'd have something very powerful.
Opera, in fact,
is greater than the sum of its parts.
In some ways,
opera is like a traditional Broadway show.
You have a sung play that is divided
into acts, usually two or three.
You have a book, in other words the text,
which is opera we call
the libretto, and you have the lyrics,
the poetic part of the libretto.
And you have the musical score that
adds emotional intensity to the drama.
What happens first?
Well, an opera usually
begins with an overture,
an instrumental piece
that opens the opera.
It used to be that the overture was
played to call people to attention.
To tell them hey, pay attention.
Go take your seats.
Only later was it played after
the people were seated and
people listened to the overture.
Let's see how this works.
To do so we go to northern Italy,
the birth place of opera.
Even today about three quarters of the
operas that are performed in opera houses
around thee world have been written
to an Italian text, perhaps, in part,
because of the regularly spaced
vowels in the Italian language.
Anyway, here's a map of the city-states
of Northern Italy around 1600.
And you can see there in red Florence,
Mantua and Venice.
The first opera of lasting
importance was composed here
in Mantua by Claudio Monteverdi.
Now, Monteverdi's first
opera was entitled Orfeo.
And he wrote it, again, in Mantua in 1607.
Orfeo, or Orpheus,
was an appropriate subject because
the story is drawn from
classical Greek mythology.
What's the story about?
Well, it tells the tale of Orfeo,
a half-god,
half-man who has married a human,
Eurydice, but
she's been killed by a snake, and carried
off to Hades, the Greek vision of hell.
It's Orfeo's job to descent into Hades and
rescue her.
So, this, in a sense, is a rescue drama.
Here on the right, we see the scene.
Down below, we've got the River Styx,
Charon, the ferryman on the left and
or fail with his lyre to which
he sings on the right, and
moribund Eurydice.
Well, let's watch a video
now of the first fully
formed opera starting with the overture.
The production here is by the Spanish
early music conductor Horace
who has done his best to recreate the
opera as close to Monteverdi's original
intentions as possible.
Here's the overture.
[MUSIC]
Okay I'm gong to pause it here just for
a second.
And you can see on the screen there
some of these baroque instruments.
We see a harp in the orchestra.
Normally we don't see that.
We see some violins.
We see some strange looking woodwind
instruments that we'll talk about
a little later on.
And we see that giant
lute-like thing over there,
to the right center, a theorbo.
So this is Monteverdi's
early baroque orchestra.
All right.
Let's go on and
hear the rest of our overture to Orfeo.
[MUSIC]
As to the opera itself, well,
let's first have an explanation of
the style of singing calling monody.
Expressive one line monody solo singing
accompanied by a small ensemble.
Eventually, early monody would bifurcate
into two contrasting modes of delivery,
recitative and aria.
What the difference between
a recitative and an aria?
Well recitative generally told what
was going on, what's happening, and
aria reflected what the protagonist,
the singer, felt about what was happening.
You can find almost all of
Monteverdi's Orfeo on YouTube.
But let's cut to the high point.
Let's go to the climactic aria
in which Orfeo tries to convince
Charon to allow him to cross
the river Styx and into Hades.
But first, let's review the nature of
this particular aria by way of a slide.
As you can see here,
the notes of the music
pertain to the aria Posente Spirto,
powerful spirit.
And this is an aria in which we
have passionate, expansive, and
tuneful expressions of the feelings and
motions of Orfeo.
It's accompanied by the full orchestra and
by a basso continuo, which we'll
talk about a little bit later on.
It's a self-contained unit,
both textually and musically, so
we've got a poem here set to music
which has its own meter and rhyme.
And note the vocal embellishments
to convey emotion.
Orfeo wants to persuade us, and
he does so by means of ornamentation.
Odd sorts of ornamentation,
where he might sing,
[MUSIC].
Sounds strange,
sounds almost like a goat, but
that is where Orfeo is trying
to be his most persuasive.
All right.
Let's turn to the video now.
And I might talk a bit as we go.
>> [FOREIGN]
>> Powerful spirit.
[MUSIC]
It is referring to the God Charon,
the guardian of Hades, or Hell.
[MUSIC]
So the music here is actually
coming from the pit.
Those on stage are simply
holding symbols of the music.
Indeed, Orfeo is holding
a symbol of the music, the lyre.
[MUSIC]
And the ornaments, or
imitation that you just heard again,
are attempts on Orfeo's part to
persuade Charon to allow him
to cross into Hades and rescue Eurydice.
Music is the agent of the river.
This is just a taste of Monteverdi's
Orfeo, and you can watch all of these
scenes in more than one production
on YouTube, and compare them.
But now we're going to move on
from early 17th century opera to
late 17th century opera.
And we'll see how monody has
progressively split further
into these two distinctly different
styles, recitative and aria.
For this, we'll go to England,
specifically London, and
to an opera by Henry Purcell,
Dido and Aeneas.