[MUSIC]
Here we are in 17th Century London.
You can see there we've got the river
Thames, and then London Bridge,
the one bridge there in the 17th
century that went across the river.
To the right of the bridge
we see the Tower of London.
As we swing around to the left we can see
St. James park, over here to the left.
The king lived in this area, Whitehall
was down here and Westminster Abbey.
And then over here actually not
the map is where Buckingham Palace
will ultimately be built.
And then farther off to my left
from there we come to Chelsea which
was in a suburb but's now
very much downtown London.
And Chelsea is an important
part about what
we are going to discuss here
with the opera of Henry Purcell.
So here,
you see an image of Henry Purcell.
He's one of the three greatest
composers in English history.
Purcell, Handel, and Paul Mc Cartney.
Well, at least those are my choices for
the three greatest English composers.
Purcell worked as an organist
at Westminster Abbey.
And is a composer and organist for the
King in the Chapel Royal, as they call it.
And he had an interest in theater music,
London being,
ever since Shakespeare's day,
the world's greatest theater town.
Purcell's most enduring opera, Dido and
Aeneas, was one of the first
written in English.
It was actually composed not for
a commercial theatre but
for a girl's boarding school or
finishing school in Chelsea.
The opera functions something came to
a senior class play because all the parts,
except one, were written for girls.
These girls had surely studied Virgil's
and Nyid in their Latin classes.
It was standard Latin to be memorized.
And Purcell fashion and
opera libretto out of Virgil's poetry.
The story, as you may know,
is about Aeneas and the Trojan Wars and
his flight from Troy.
Stopping by Carthage,
capturing the heart of Queen Dido, and
then abandoning her to go on and
found the city of Rome.
Alone, broken-hearted, noble Queen Dido
sings her last, and then expires.
Stabs herself with a sword, or
burns herself on a funeral pyre,
or dies of a broken heart in the opera.
Whatever.
As my colleague Tim Rhode has
famously said her despair,
her despondency is poison enough.
The scene of Dido's death,
which we will study here,
is divided into Dido's recitative and
her aria.
Here's the music of her recitative.
So here with the recitative
the music slides down chromatically.
[MUSIC]
So as you heard,
the music is sliding down there.
Chromatic scale,
a descending chromatic scale is used.
Chromaticism in music signals tension and
pain.
Here, the music descends.
Which symbolizes or
expresses defeat and resignation,
Dido's defeat and resignation.
People die down, they don't die up.
Downwards equals resignation in life and
in music.
Then comes the aria.
It's written on an ostinato,
a repeating bass.
The English word for
this is a ground bass.
A repeating or foundational,
a grounding bass.
Let me play the,
just the bass on the keyboard here.
[MUSIC]
Okay, so that's the five measure bass.
It has a chromatic descent.
[MUSIC]
Again, more pang, and
then a sort of looping around.
[MUSIC]
To end the five bar phrase.
And then up above this,
Purcell writes a beautiful aria that we
will hear that proceeds with
consonance and dissonance.
[MUSIC]
Now looping back.
And there we are.
So, now we're going to
watch a video of this,
stopping along the way to discuss things
such as basso ostinato and basso continuo.
[MUSIC]
[INAUDIBLE] Okay, here we go.
With the recivity,
with Dido singing to her servant.
[MUSIC]
Still falling down here.
About half way down.
[MUSIC]
Okay, recitative, just been
accompanied by a string instrument.
Now another string
instrument starts out here.
[MUSIC]
Here's our basso ostinato, or ground bass.
Just with a low string instrument.
Accompaniment comes in with the voice.
Orchestra comes in.
[MUSIC]
Here the loops back and
starts all over again.
[MUSIC]
Base descending chromatically.
Looping back to the tonic.
Repeat of the text.
Repeat of the melody.
Aria repeat texts.
Recitative don't repeat text.
[MUSIC]
>> Now, heads up on the word create.
You can hear ornamentation
provided by the singer.
[MUSIC]
Hear how she filled in that interval?
Here she'll do it again.
[MUSIC]
And the ostinato as it loops back.
And on the [INAUDIBLE].
So we're going to pause it here.
Well that's just one
interpretation of this aria.
But we're going to go on now to
a comparison of two other, two very
different approaches to one and the same
aria taken by two different singers.
Music is communication from creator
to listener with the performer
as something of a middle man, or in this
case, a middle woman, an intermediary.
But the intermediary in
delivering the message can do so
in very different ways, as we'll here.
So let's compare singers here.
Let's compare intermediaries.
We'll start with the early
music specialist.
She's not a modern opera star, but
a specialist in early music, Emma Kirkby.
As you listen, think about three things.
What's the nature of
the singer's voice here?
How much vibrato does she use?
How much vibrato is there
in here mode of singing?
Second what's the tempo?
Conduct along with the music.
It's in three and you'll get a sense of
the, of the tempo if you, if you conduct.
And three, how powerful is the orchestra?
Does it seem like a small, early music
orchestra of the baroque period?
Or a large, modern symphony?
So here's your challenge.
Answer those three questions.
Here we go.
We're starting with Emma Kirkby.
[MUSIC]
One, two, three, one, two,
three, one, two, three.
[MUSIC]
All right, let's pause it here.
We're going to go on now to the reporting
of opera star Jesse Norman.
And again the same three questions.
What's the nature of the singer's voice?
How much vibrato does it have?
What's the tempo?
Conduct along with the music.
And three, how powerful is the orchestra?
Does it seem like a small, early musical
orchestra, or a large, modern one?
Let's listen to Jesse Norman now.
[MUSIC]
So let's pause it here.
Well, what'd you think
about these two recordings,
the difference between the two?
I'd like to know, so go online please and
take an interactive quiz
responding to the questions posed.
You can also answer specific
musical questions, and
you can tell me which
recording you preferred.
And why?
Again, two very different interpretations
of one in the same
beautiful aria
by Henry Purcell.