[MUSIC]
So far in our discussion of Baroque music
we've talked about opera and voices,
now its time for instruments.
Let's start with a melody and base, and
this brings us to the two instruments
that dominated Baroque instrumental sound,
the violin and the harpsichord.
The violin to the melody.
Harpsichord, for the bass and harmony.
And we'll throw in another bass
harmony type instrument, the theorbo.
Now let's start with the violin.
Actually the term violin is diminutive.
Little viol, violino, violino; but as the
violin is the little viol, what's a viol?
Well, it's an early six string instrument.
Or in some cases, here as you see on the
screen to the left, even a seven string
instrument that prevailed in Western
Europe during the 15th and 16th centuries.
It was also fretted like
the guitar of today.
In the mid 16th century,
there arose a small cousin of the viol.
Violin, or little viol.
You can see the difference,
comparing left and right.
Only four strings to the right,
and no frets.
And it has sounding holes in
the shape of an F rather than a C,
which makes a slight
difference acoustically.
The violin was originally a low class
tavern instrument, played by dancing
masters, dancing teachers,
to entertain with dances in taverns and
in public houses, bars and effect.
Looking at this map we see that
the center of violin construction
was then in Northern Italy,
specifically in Cremona.
And that's where the center of
violin making is still today,
in Cremona, to the left there,
to the west of Mantua.
And here we see a woman in
one of these many small shops
that you can visit in Cremona.
Now, there's one thing
that's always surprised me.
Yes, violins are made of maple and spruce.
That much I knew, but
all violins seem to look
remarkably similar in size and
shape and general design.
They're all pretty much alike,
pretty much identical.
Here we see violins from different
times and different places.
One from 17th century Italy,
18th century Germany,
20th century Germany, but
they're all identical.
How did they do that?
How do they do that?
Well, let's see, this way.
They do it with a mold or a a frame.
There was a standard mold that
every Luthier, in other words,
instrument maker, had and passed along
that led to this standard size and shape.
All right, so the violin is the primary
melody carrying instrument of the Boroque.
But what about the bass and the harmony?
Well at first,
that was provided by a large,
loot like instrument called the theorbo,
and then by the harpsichord.
For demonstration of both of these,
let's go back to my colleague and
professional early music performer
extraordinaire, Grant Herod.
>> So here we are back again with my
friend and colleague, Grant Herod, and
we're going to be talking today
about baroque instruments and
baroque orchestras.
But first, the baroque instruments.
We left off last time, we're gonna show
this slide now, we left off last time with
a slide coming from the National Gallery
in London of a lute.
And then we're going to turn to the next
slide which actually comes from
an American collection out in Columbus,
Ohio, an art museum there,
showing this instrument called,
oh what is this thing called?
>> This is the theorbo.
And it's a kind of a bass lute, from about
here to the end of the peg box here.
It's just a large loot,
bass loot, and the strings
[MUSIC]
are tuned like a loot
except it's too long.
So the top two strings
[MUSIC]
are tuned down an octave
from the loot tuning.
So the highest sounding string is
the third string from the edge there
which gives it a peculiar technique and
a very bassy or tenor-like range.
Then we have an extension neck
set on it that accommodates
these seven bass strings.
[MUSIC]
Tune to some sort of a scale usually.
>> Mm.
>> And this was an attempt
to give the lute a little
more volume, a bigger range obviously and
more of a base presence so that.
[MUSIC]
The lute was just more suited to
play the music of this early baroque
period that featured the baseline
more than renaissance music.
>> Yeah, that's a very important
observation, because we have been talking
about and will be talking more about
this whole idea of the basso continuo.
Well, this instrument could really by
itself provide all of the bass and
the harmony.
In an odd way,
it's like a piano in a jazz band today
except it's a lot more portable.
Or like a harpsichord would
have been in the early Baroque.
Except again, it's a lot more portable.
Strum a chord or two more just to
show them the sound of that bass.
[MUSIC]
Beautiful, beautiful sound, and
one of the things it would do,
of course,
is play something called the figured bass,
and you will see a slide a little bit
later on showing you how this works.
But maybe you could give us
a demonstration whereby you the performer,
Grant, have just a bassline and
some numbers and
you're supposed to know how to
flesh out a chord from that.
>> Right.
>> So can you play a bass line?
>> Yeah, so
a simple bass line might sound like this.
[MUSIC]
I harmonize that bass line according
to the numbers in the figured bass.
[MUSIC]
So it's almost like an entire orchestra.
Sound big booming and it could very
well support a baroque singer.
Now let me formally introduce two terms.
Basso continuo, continuous bass,
and figured bass.
A basso continuo is the Baroque term for
a strong bass and chordal accompaniment.
Created by, usually by a stringed
instrument, such as the cello, and
by a chording instrument,
such as the theorbo, that we'll see again.
We just saw, or perhaps the harpsichord,
or sometimes even the organ.
And this string instrument plus
the chording instrument play throughout
the piece.
That's why it's a continuate.
Plays continually,
a strong continual bass.
The string plays the bass line and
the chording instrument flushes
out a rock solid harmony above it.
Here's an all female quartet from the 18th
century in which the melody is played
by flute and violin and the basso
continuo by harpsichord and cello.
Let's review and go on to figured bass.
So, looking at the slide to review Basso
continuo a small ensemble of at least two
instruments which provide a foundation for
the melody heard above and
played continually throughout the piece.
Okay now figured bass,
well figured bass is a numerical
shorthand placed below the base line
that an experienced musician
who's studied music theory and
knows how to play the keyboard will be
able to look at these numbers associated
with the bass line and
fill out a chordal accompaniment with it.
So, let me see if I can generate this for
you on the keyboard.
Here's the bass line.
[MUSIC]
And an experienced musician
would flush it out this way.
[MUSIC]
Like that and here's an example of
an early keyboard piece by J.S.
Bach with a figured bass.
I'll play the bass and
then I'll realize it for you here again.
In our studio let me get
the music here is what wrote just
the bass line you have both
the above the realization below.
[MUSIC]
Okay now here's what Bach
wanted to have performed.
[MUSIC]
All right let's go on now to talk
about the workhorse of the baroque,
the harpsichord and we'll begin
with a few introductory slides.
Here's a typical harpsichord of the early
baroque with just one keyboard.
Much later, much bigger harps accord.
This one is about 1750 I believe,
with two manuals and three registers.
By registers I mean sets of strings.
Now here's a modern reproduction
of the Harps accord at Yale.
Two keyboards,
two long sets of strings called eight
foot strings and one set of short strings,
called four foot strings.
So, you can sound one pitch by plucking
one of the three strings or you
can sound two pitches by plucking, you can
sound two strings and get the same pitch.
Sort of double down or double up or
you can bring three strings into play and
sort of get a trifecta here
a wammie of three strings all
playing at once, but
no matter how many strings are playing,
they're all plucked by
the same thing called a jack.
Let's take a look at the jacks now.
So, here we see the jacks on
an actual harpsichord, to the right
and a diagram of how the jack works.
As you can see, you press the key,
a fulcrum goes up, and
drives the jack up and up.
As the jacks go up,
they pluck the strings.
Now, to make some sense out of this,
we'll go to another
explanation from Grant Harrid.
Well welcome back.
Now we're gonna talk
about the harpsichord.
Harpsichord was the workhorse
of the baroque era.
It was the literally the basis
of virtually all music that was
made from roughly 1650 up to 17 50,
17, 70, or
so, and we're going to turn
once again to Grant Herod.
Just when you thought that Grant had
demonstrated everything possible to
demonstrate by way of musical instruments,
yet, here is Grant again
demonstrating another instrument.
This time, the harpsichord.
>> Just to explain a few things about
this 18th century style harpsichord and
some of the bells and whistles it has.
First of all, of course the sound of
a harpsichord with its metal strings
is created by a bit of
a feather plucking the string.
The feather is attached to a jack and
under this jack rail
are the rows of jacks.
Three rows for the three different
registers of this harpsichord.
As I pluck the string or press the key,
it sends the jack up and the little
tangent plucks the string on its way up.
[SOUND] The jack rail is
in place to make sure
that they don't jump out of their sockets.
>> [INAUDIBLE] on the way back down?
>> There's a system of,
if it's slightly weighted so
that on its way back down
it rocks slightly away and
the tension actually doesn't
come in contact with the string.
Very sophisticated but
sort of simple mechanism and
I can [SOUND].
Play the upper keyboard as well.
You notice the different
jack is activated.
[MUSIC]
>> So, there are three jacks then for
each pitch?
Or is that-
>> Each key, yes and each pitch because I
can also add a little, the shorter
set of strings that are sounding at
four foot pitch rather than eight
foot pitch, so an octave higher.
[MUSIC]
I can get a contrast
between the upper keyboard
[MUSIC]
Which because it's plucking
the string a little closer to
the bridge is slightly more brittle.
[MUSIC]
And of course,
the two keyboards can be coupled together.
[MUSIC]
And adding the back in,
we have the whole sound.
[MUSIC]
A sort of orchestral
sound of the harpsichord.
>> So, just to review, we actually have
three sets of strings on this instrument?.
>> Yes,
two at what we call eight foot pitch and
then one set of strings at four
foot pitch, an octave higher.
>> Obviously as Grant just said,
an octave higher,
and we have two keyboards so
how does that work?
One keyboard plays two sets of strings
has the capacity to play two at one time?
>> The lower keyboard can play the
[MUSIC]
one of the eight foot sets of strings or
registers and, again,
we can engage the forefoot.
[MUSIC]
So, we have octave sounding there.
That's on the lower keyboard and then
the upper keyboard can play by itself.
[MUSIC]
With a slightly more brittle sound or
if they're joined together,
just by playing the lower keyboard I can
engage both of the eight foot registers.
[MUSIC]
So quite a variety in a single instrument.
>> So, one hears that the reason that
the harpsichord fell by the wayside
around 1750 to 1770, is that it had no
capacity for the gradation of sound.
And in some ways, that's true.
If you punch hard, [SOUND] okay.
And now play very softly,
push very softly.
[SOUND] The same volume sound,
basically the same volume sound.
>> Basically yes.
>> Because it doesn't,
the impact of the plucking,
the force of it in no way
impacts the volume that's generated
from that particular string.
So what you can't do, what's difficult
to do is to shape a phrase in a way on
a harpsichord quite the way you can on
a piano with little gradations of loud and
soft going up and back.
Could I take it for a test drive here?
So start me out here, you be my
instructor, let's say I want to play
something baroque that's very soft and
light, this thing [SOUND] of Bach.
Now that sounds awfully loud, so how could
I back that down to maybe just the four?
I've played on this keyboard here and
you disengage some of the eights, or.
>> We can take the eight off here and
that will leave you with
just the four foot here.
[MUSIC]
let me disengage this keyboard as well,
by pulling that out, and
that should just be the four foot.
[MUSIC]
>> Wow.
That is very quiet, all right so
let's build up our sound now.
So that's just the four.
>> If we add an eight foot to that,
we'd get this sound.
>> Let's see.
[MUSIC]
And then by the big band sound.
>> Right, engaging the other set of eight.
[MUSIC]
>> So it is a little bit bigger.
I bet it sounds good with some.
[MUSIC]
The Pachelbel bass that we're going
to explore in another segment.
So as we saw, the harpsichord
has some capacity to increase or
diminish the sound according to
how many registers of strings,
one, two, or three, are brought into play.
But no matter how hard
you strike any one key,
you're always gonna get the same
volume with the harpsichord.
And that limitation of volume and
inability to shape a phrase by
means of volume was the liability of the
harpsichord and gradually the harpsichord
gave way to the pianoforte or as we
call it today, gave way to the piano.
Around 1770 the piano
replaced the harpsichord
because of the sound
limitations of the harpsichord.
So, to sum up this segment.
In the Baroque era, the violin became
the principal carrier of the melody,
and the harpsichord the principle
setter of the harmony.
But how did the full orchestra,
the orchestra of today, come into be?
Well, we can demonstrate this quickly
by looking first at this slide.
In the early Baroque period or
up to around the mid 17th century
the core of the orchestra
was in effect all-strings,
soprano, alto, and bass or
violin, second violin,
viola, and cello,
with the double bass doubling the cello.
That's why it's called a double bass.
And of course we could have also with this
group the or a harpsichord or an organ.
We would need those instruments as well.
Now, let's take a look at a larger group.
To this initial core that we just saw,
were gradually added woodwinds,
oboe and bassoons.
First doubling the strings.
In other words, the oboes and
the bassoons just doubled what the violins
were doing, violins and lower strings.
And then they were given, the oboes and
violins, their own independent parts.
And the horns were gradually
added to sustain the sound.
We began to call them French
horns in the 19th century.
So, the late 17th as the horns were
added to sustain the sound, and
then also late 17th century trumpets and
drums added for brilliance when needed.
So, by around 1700, the late Baroque
orchestra was in play, in place.
And it gave us the symphony
orchestra of today.