[MUSIC]
Welcome back.
We've talked about the instruments
that led the charge and
in fact led the change in baroque music.
Let's now focus on some pieces.
I've chosen two that you'll
likely know very well.
The Cannon by Johann Pachelbel and
The Spring Concerto of Antonio Vivaldi.
Let's start with the Pachelbel.
Second only to the bass line
of the blues the most famous bass line
of all is that of the Pachelbel canon.
Like the blues bass, it's another ostinato
bass, a bass that repeats over and over.
Well who was Johann Pachelbel?
He was an organist and
composer in south central Germany
at the end of the 17th century.
Johann Christoph Bach was
a pupil of Pachelbel.
And when young Johann Sebastian Bach's
parents died and left him an orphan at
about the age of ten, eldest brother
Johann Christoph became his guardian.
So there is a Pachelbel-Bach connection.
Anyway, Pachelbel composed
an instrumental Canon in D Major.
And here you see the music of
it we have the famous bass
line it's a underneath
of eight pitches and
above those eight pitches
a harmony is constructed fleshing
out the figured bass producing
the basso continuo here's the bass.
[MUSIC]
And then here's how the keyboard
player would realize that.
[MUSIC]
So that's the basso continuo
playing throughout the piece and
basso, basso ostinato starting over and
over again, going 28 times.
The odd thing is with the Pachelbel Canon,
the odd thing is we don't hear the canon.
Let me play just a little
bit of the canonic line.
[MUSIC]
And then another part comes in.
So we have a three part canon or
a three part round.
But we don't hear it.
Why don't hear it?
At least we don't hear it literally.
We don't hear it because
Pachelbel has orchestrated this
with all instruments
being played by a violin.
So there's no separation by color here,
there's no separation by timbre.
And they're all in the same range, so
there's no separation by range or
frequency.
But here is a video of
the Pachelbel Canon, created by,
actually by my friend Stephen Malinowski
out in Richmond California.
And we're going to play this.
Let's start it up here now.
[MUSIC]
Good.
So we have the basso continuo,
basso starting out.
And here comes the first violin,
it's right down the scale.
[MUSIC]
Second violin just duplicating
what the first had done.
[MUSIC]
Third violin come in.
And the first violins now playing quarter
notes, dividing the half note into two.
Second violin picks up
those quarter notes.
It's a little bit complicated.
What we hear is that ostinato
bass chugging underneath.
[MUSIC]
It's hard to know that we've got around
in here, it sounds like the music.
Now the first violin is
leading out with eighth notes.
Second violin picks that up, gives
the sense that the piece is going faster.
There's more activity.
It's actually not going faster.
The tempo is exactly the same,
the tempo is rigid.
But psychologically,
we perceive this as motion.
[MUSIC]
Increased motion.
Now the leader will jump a bit in
counterpoint against those eighth notes.
And in a moment that leader will seem to
be going even faster with the advent of
16th notes.
[MUSIC]
Second chorus picks up the 16th notes.
All right, let's phase it out here.
So again, although the tempo was
the same with this particular piece,
the psychological effect
of the piece is that it's
moving faster to build to a grand climax.
And I encourage you,
encourage you now to go on and
pick this up with the full presentation
by Steve Malinowski on YouTube.
So that's Mister Pachelbel,
that's Mister Pachelbel.
Let's move on now,
south across the Alps to Venice and
learn about
Antonio Vivaldi's Spring Concerto.