Hello.
Well, we're now finished filming
all 24 hours of our course,
introduction to classical music.
And you might be wondering,
what you might be getting into,
what kind of experience
you might have here?
Well let's take a preview.
The first six sessions tell us why
music matters, why it moves us so
much, why so
many people listen to it every day.
And they provide the technical
information that you'll need to
fully enjoy classical music.
By technical information,
I mean what we'll need to know about.
How music works, at it's most basic level.
About rhythm, melody, harmony, and so on.
How technical is this going to get?
Well, here's a sample moment from
our discussion of rhythm in music.
Rhythm is a bit more complicated.
Rhythm is the organization of time
into compelling patterns of long and
short sounds.
Here's a famous melody, one created
by the French composer Maurice Ravel
from his ballet Bolero of 1928.
There is a tune, a succession of higher
and lower pitches shown vertically,
and there is a rhythm
moving left to right.
Now lets strip away pitch and
leave the rhythm alone and
it will look like this as
we see on our next slide.
But what we hear first at the beginning
of Bolero, is not the melody but
another rhythm.
This one.
And it's played by a snare drum.
Now, a snare drum, as you may know,
has no particular pitch.
It just plays a rhythm, pure rhythm.
I'll tap it.
[MUSIC]
And that's all the snare drum player does.
So he better write that pattern.
He's going to be doing it for
the next 14 and a half minutes.
Now, beneath the snare drum pattern,
low strange play, another rhythm that
provides something of a harmony.
Let's take a look at that now.
[NOISE]
And
so on.
Eventually the flute enters,
adding the enchanting melody.
So now we have three
rhythms operating here.
One in the flute,
which also carries the melody.
One in the snare drum,
which is a simple or pure rhythm.
And the third in the bass,
which is providing something of
a harmony below the melody up above.
So we have three rhythms
that are staying within and
emphasizing the structure of the measure.
Three different rhythms
sounding simultaneously,
three different patterns of longs and
shorts.
Having learned about the elements
of music, what makes music work?
We'll move on now to listening to
great pieces of classical music.
Starting with Gregorian Chant and
working up to the Renaissance, and
then the Baroque Era.
Here's a sample from the Baroque Era,
featuring music by Handel,
the composer of course of
the oratorical Messiah.
But here, we're discussing the music for
the royal fireworks, again by Handel.
Combined with them is the English group,
The Orchestra of the Age of Enlightenment.
I'll comment as we go.
[MUSIC]
Starting with replica of natural trumpets,
no vowels
[MUSIC]
So here's the minuette.
Notice that the tempo of
course is much slower.
I would say that the playing
is a lot cleaner.
[MUSIC]
This was a difficult technique,
this clarino playing from the Baroque era.
Only specialists could do it.
[MUSIC]
Obviously overdo the oboes.
See the old oboe, in the middle of the
orchestra, authentic performance practice.
What we don't see here is a conductor.
The first violinist is conducting,
and that's correct.
There were no conductors standing and
waving batons in those days.
So the first violinist is conducting here.
And he's very, very,
[MUSIC]
The natural horns.
Pretty impressive.
Next we go on to a discussion
of classical music,
with Haydn and specially with Mozart.
But here, let's look at a clip
demonstrating how classical Beethoven
constructs a symphony, specifically
his Eroica, or heroic, symphony.
During most of these years, Beethoven was
living here, at the Pascualati House,
which happened to be on
the ramparts of the old fortress.
So, when Napoleon unleashed his hundreds
of cannons at the old city fortresses,
well, Beethoven had a ringside seat.
And although he was nearly deaf,
he was terrified by the sound and
the destruction of the cannons.
Well anyway,
enough about Beethoven and the poem.
Let's get to the music.
To do so, we'll start with the opening
sounds of the Eroica Symphony.
Let's see what's revolutionary about it.
As we listen, you identify three things,
three ways in which this music
differs from Mozart of Haydn.
What is Beethoven doing here that Mozart,
for example, would not have done?
And here again we're going to employ
a video made by Steve Melanosky.
Two hammer strokes right at the beginning.
Then the theme appears, not in the first
violins like we would expect but
in the cellos.
[MUSIC]
Now the woodwinds take over the theme.
Takes it up a step.
Up another step.
[MUSIC]
And now we get ready for
some heavy-handed syncopation.
[MUSIC]
More syncopation.
Now, everybody in!
Full orchestra.
[MUSIC]
From a live classroom,
to an online mode of delivery,
such as we have in our online course here,
we knew we had to take music and
make it less audio and more video.
We knew that the Internet is not
good at delivering quality sound.
But it is good at letting us see how
things work, even see how music works,
hear animations, and diagrams,
and video clips of all sorts.
They all allow us to understand,
to demystify,
classical music as we see here in famous
passage from a song of Gustave Mahler.
As the text at the end says,
I have escaped into a solitary
world of love and music.
A love for music.
[FOREIGN] In my love and
in my song, my music song.
You're being a metaphor for all music.
Let's
listen
to this
beautiful
piece as
conducted
by
Claudio
Abbado
and
sung by
Magalina
Piscina
[MUSIC]
Finally we've tried to be creative.
And in so doing, sometimes we came close
to creating out own new art forms.
As you see in this last
clip from a discussion
of the post-modernist
music of Phillip Glass.
So we have just this repeated note and
then this,
[MUSIC]
And then, slowly,
seventh chord will be introduced.
[MUSIC]
And then another one, but
another one going against it.
[MUSIC]
Opposite direction,
one coming down as one goes up.
[MUSIC]
And then he would double the tempo and
run them both up and down simultaneously.
[MUSIC]
In that fashion.
So let's hear a bit of the original
composition flow by Phillip Glass, and
as we do so, as these arpeggios are going
up and down against themselves,
we'll look at this visual image.
Each of these squares is
a rectangle against itself.
You can study these rectangles or
these mirror images as the music plays.
[MUSIC]
Okay maybe we'll
pause it.
>> I hope you can see that we've tried
to be creative with our introduction to
classical music,
we've tried to have some fun.
For as we know in music, or
anything else in life, we all are more
engaged when we're having fun.