[MUSIC]
Hi, welcome to Office Hours.
You might recognize the,
that part of the theme that I just played
which is from the second movement,
the opening of the second movement
of Dvorak's very well-known
New World Symphony.
It's his Symphony Number Nine.
It was composed in 1893 while he was
serving as a director of
a conservatory here in the US.
This is a very, very well-known and,
and beloved piece.
And I actually wanted to talk with all of
you actually about the first movement,
not the second movement today,
which is still lovely.
But we're going to talk about the first
movement because I thought it might be fun
to go through a, a piece, a movement
of a piece that is very well-known and
hopefully recognizable for
many of you out there.
And, and talk through it both from
a musical, descriptive level,
but also to travel through it and look
at sonata form which is one of the major
forms that we deal with in western
art music in, in classical music.
And I think that in using this piece as
an example, we can kind of see how some of
the familiar scenes that you might know
just from being an active listener,
can map on to the sonata form structure
that Dvorak has employed here.
And, and countless of composers in
the Western art music tradition,
have employed for
over two centuries at this point.
So let's start out by
just talking a little bit
about the framework of this symphony.
I'm going to go to
the white board over here.
And what we're going to do
is just very quickly map out
the kind of general sonata form structure
that you've learned it, which would be,
here we have the exposition, and
I'm just going to abbreviate that.
And then we know that there is a middle
section that is the development,
and then at the end we have a third
part which is the recapitulation.
We'll call it here, the recap.
Broadly speaking, those are the three
main sections of a sonata form movement.
The exposition, of course, is in
charge of laying out all of the major
musical ideas of the form.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to refer to these
areas as kind of zones or groups.
So we'll have a first theme,
zone or group.
Another way to think of it is as
a primary, primary theme, group.
Then usually there's
some sort of transition.
Just transition.
Then we get to the second theme.
Or we can call it our,
our secondary theme group, or zone.
Of course, that'll go for a little bit,
and then we'll come to our
third thematic area or group, and
sometimes it's thought of as being
like the closing melodic area.
So once again now we have kind
of the layout of our exposition.
This is going to give us the,
the primary not necessarily primary,
but the important musical ideas for
this sonata form, and
then for the rest of the movement we're
going to see how these things play out.
There are many different things that
are implicated in a sonata form that we
are going to probably skip over for
now, because they
not only go into greater music
theoretical terms, but also they don't
always necessarily play out exactly the
same way from one sonata form to the next.
We have to think of this as kind of
an ongoing tradition and an ongoing,
maybe dialogue between a composer and
the music, a composer and
other composers who are using sonata form.
And of course the kind of
the history of sonata form as it
as it spreads across different countries
and different composers and styles.
So not every composer is
going to do the same thing.
However, I'll just quickly kind of
highlight that often times when we move
from our first theme group to the second
theme group, there's usually a modulation
and that often happens over
the course of the transition.
And then usually the second and
third theme groups are going
to be in the same key.
But once again that's not a hard and
fast rule.
So in traditional sonata forms,
you're actually going to have a repeat.
This is our,
this is the music sign for repeat.
If you ever look at a music score and
you see this right here like that,
that usually means to repeat
back either to the beginning or
repeat back to the first
opening repeat sign.
So if you see one of these
somewhere before it,
this repeat sign's going to
tell you to go there.
If you don't see that, it's going to
tell you go to the beginning.
Now we get to our development.
A development usually entails
taking some of this material that
we've heard in the exposition and
actually developing it.
Kind of playing with it,
giving some new twists or
spins to it, kind of a metamorphosis.
You might hear lots of modulations or
traveling to different key areas,
even though we don't necessarily stay
in those key areas for very long.
And then this is kind of
the section that has the most
free-flowing creativity,
well I shouldn't say creativity.
It has the most kind of
variability in the sonata form,
so for now I'm just going to do,
I'm going to represent that like this.
I'm just going to say, it's a lot of this
and then eventually there's going to be
a moment where you can kind of tell
that the tension is building and
then all of a sudden we now get
the onset of the recapitulation,
which essentially is a conceptual
restatement of the exposition.
So you know, we can think of this
kind of loose turn or A, B, A, right.
A, B, A.
In the recap then we're going to
get the first theme group,
second theme group,
third theme group again.
We can call it again PSC.
And oftentimes there are going to
be some slight, modifications.
It's not necessarily always going to be
an exact restatement of the exposition.
For instance, if you recall, I just
said that oftentimes in sonata forms,
you will have a modulation between
the first and the second theme groups.
In the recap, usually, that mod,
that modulation is going to be modified so
that you stay in the same key.
That's kind of a typical move,
but again, once again,
it's not always the hard and fast rule.
So in this case,
let's just leave this as our broad layout.
Now, in the Dvorak symphony, the New
World Symphony, in the first movement,
we have an extra little component, which
I think we've also encountered in our
course before, which is that before
the exposition even begins,.
And I'm going to now erase a little
bit of this to create some room.
Before the exposition begins,
we actually have a slow introduction.
And so this is also some material.
Slow introduction, then there's going
to be a transition out of that,
into the onset of the exposition.
Now, in the Dvorak,
you're going to hear a repeat.
That repeat, is actually not going
to take us all the way back to
the beginning of the slow introduction.
It's in fact going to take us back to
the beginning of the exposition proper.
So, you can think then,
of this as having a slow introduction,
and then, repeat signs there, so that
you going to hear the entire exposition,
then it's going to repeat
back to the exposition again.
On the second pass through,
you're going to hear the same thing.
When we get here there's going to
be a slight modification so
[LAUGH] that we don't repeat over and
over again.
A slight modification that's going to
then lead us in to the development, and
then we're going to go all the way through
to, to the recap, to the end of the piece.
So that's our crash course
again in sonata form.
And now, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to walk you through some of
the themes that we're going to
hear in this movement.
And then we're going to
actually walk through
a listening of the entire movement.
It takes about 11 minutes or so and
I'll try my best to not talk
too much over the audio.
But I think I will talk over the audio so
that I can guide you as we're going and
we can, we can talk about what
we're hearing in real time.
So, at the very beginning,
our first theme.
And I'm not going to play all of
these themes in their entirety.
One of the interesting things about music,
and music as it takes
place in larger forms like this,
is that there is some flexibility
with how we define various concepts.
When we say a theme,
we usually do mean though kind of a,
a relatively self-encloser at least.
And a noticeable or parsable melody that
you can kind of say has a beginning and
possibly an end.
In, in, in this case the theme is somewhat
longer and made up of smaller gestures.
So I'll play you kind of the main
idea here which just goes
[MUSIC]
And then keeps going.
So this theme has like a very
noticeable idea, which is.
[MUSIC]
And then keeps going.
Now it's that, will take place.
And then we're going to hear more music,
which obviously ensues.
And, and there's not necessarily
a clear distinction between like,
Oh, the theme has stopped right here and
this is clearly non-thematic material.
However, there are, there will be points
in the music where you can tell that it's,
that the music is not necessarily supposed
to be acting, you know, like a theme,
but rather it's supposed to
be transitional material or
kind of developmental material.
As we go through the piece,
I'll kind of explain this further, and
I hope that we'll be able
to here that more clearly.
So that's our first theme.
Then, the next theme is
going to take us to.
It's going to take us to
the second theme group.
And that one goes.
[MUSIC]
Like that.
That's our second theme group.
And, once again, you're going to hear that
develop and it's going to keep going.
And then we're going to experience
transition to our third theme group,
which sounds much more relaxed
then the first two themes.
This one goes like this.
[MUSIC]
And then keeps going.
Now one thing you might notice about
that theme, maybe not right away, but
the very first rhythmic idea in
this theme right here, which is
[MUSIC]
like that.
Actually it has the exact same
rhythm as our first theme which was
[MUSIC]
So now let me pull the melody out of it,
let's pull the notes out of it and
just think of it as pure rhythm.
So the very first theme goes
[MUSIC]
like that.
And then our third theme goes.
[MUSIC]
So you can see how these two ideas
are somewhat related, even at a kind of
rhythmic level, even though they
have very different characters.
The very first theme, as you're going to
hear has a, a more emphatic quality to it.
While, while this theme,
the third theme, sounds more pastoral.
But yet
they share the same opening rhythmic idea.
So there's a, a link there that is not
necessarily immediately audible, or
maybe it was.
Maybe it was to you when,
when you just heard them now.
Either way, whether you recognized it
off the bat or not, it's there and that,
that kind of adds some additional
kind of quality of rela,
an additional relationship
to the different themes.
So, that's part of the way that
sonata-formed themes work is that each
theme often has a different
sort of character to it.
And that's also how we can keep
track of them throughout the piece,
is that they can be they can have a kind
of a certain identity of their own.
All right, so now that we've heard those
three themes, let's just start here at
the beginning of this movement, and
travel through and, and see how we fair.
So, I'm going to go to the very beginning.
And here we go.
Here are, we are at our slow introduction.
We're using a recording by
the New York Philharmonic conducted by
Leonard Bernstein.
The reason why I chose this is ultimately
because I like the recording [LAUGH] and
I think Leonard Bernstein is a,
is a very nice interpreter of this music.
But also for, equally important is
that it is one of the recording, or
one of the few recordings out there
that I've found that actually does play
the expositional repeat.
And I think that's really important for
us to be able to hear.
Sometimes conductors will
make the decision and
there are many reasons for it.
It could be recording you know, depending
on when it was recorded it could've been
the limit in, in the time that they wanted
to give to the overall recording, and
sometimes to save the time,
they will skip the repeat.
It could've just have been
an artistic decision.
But in this case,
what we are getting is the full version
of the movement that includes the repeat.
So here we go, from the, from the top.
[MUSIC]
As you can see, it's a very somber mood.
Low register, very quiet.
[MUSIC]
Mounting
tension right
here.
Right here, rumbling of what will become
our first theme, here it is again.
Violent outburst.
And building.
And right here is the start
of our exposition.
[INAUDIBLE]
So
you can here how
this theme has been
generating momentum,
now we're moving onward.
You hear the theme again.
Now I'm traveling.
Your
sequence
here.
All right.
Now.
We've reached our second theme.
And you hear the oboe.
Transfers
to the
strings.
So as you can see,
we're traveling again now.
It's kind of in transition here.
Some turbulent music and
then it seems to relax again.
More relax.
Now you can kind of feel the slower role.
Here's our third theme.
The flute.
Once again, transferred to that strings.
Momentum's
building.
Final presentation, of this third theme.
Where are we going back?
Back to the beginning, or
to the beginning of our exposition.
So here we are, we've now
experienced the expositional repeat,
we're back in our first theme area.
So on the second pass visualized and
also hear your way through the form.
First theme again.
Now, traveling.
Here's our
sequence.
Okay, here we are, traveling again.
We have a change, slow change in mood.
Feel kind of
a deflation
a little bit.
Now second theme.
Transfers to the, the middle strings.
Another outburst.
And they're building again and
getting a head of steam.
It kind of breaks through and
now again kind of turbulent.
Relax.
And again, building
again, relax.
Here we go again.
Third theme, you can hear
how pastoral it feels.
Another iteration
of the third
theme.
Now we're going to travel through.
You can hear now, we're traveling.
And here's our onset of the development.
That sounds a little bit
like the third theme.
But now, the development is happening here
as we see that kind of breaking it down.
Ba ba ba ba, all right,
so you can hear,
there's a little snippet
of our first theme.
Some snippets of
the first theme.
Here you go,
another hark back to our first theme.
You can hear now, we've moved again.
Da, da, da, da, da, same thing.
So now we're using a rhythmic
jester from earlier.
Now the oboe has it.
Puh, puh, puh, puh, puh, puh, puh.
See, you can here how Dvorak is playing
with some of snippets of ideas from
the exposition, piecing them together.
And now we're back at the recap.
And this should sound familiar because
this is pretty much what we get at
the very beginning of the exposition.
Here, you might notice there's
a modification happening.
It's not exactly like it
was in the exposition.
We're on our way to
the second theme group.
And here.
[MUSIC]
It's still in the flutes though.
Then it gets past.
This time stays in the woodwind family.
[MUSIC]
Here now again, tension.
And a little relaxation.
The same thing again.
The swirling.
And relax again.
More relaxed.
Lowering down.
And here we are at our third theme.
[MUSIC]
All right, now we reach the end.
Or, the point where we would be
at the end in our exposition.
[MUSIC].
Now we're recycling some key material.
All this is new, of course.
[MUSIC].
Coming off of again,
our first new material.
[MUSIC]
Feel the energy.
Momentum.
Feel the boom, boom, boom.
[MUSIC]
Feel the rhythm.
First theme again.
[MUSIC]
So I'm going to go back to the whiteboard
here, to illustrate one thing.
Which is that in the recap,
when we got to our third theme area,
we heard the full iteration.
[MUSIC]
And then played all the way through and
then we got to that big conjubilant point.
And of course at that
point in the exposition,
we got to that jubilant point and
then we repeat it.
And then, the second time we
went onto the development.
This time we get to that
jubilant moment and
then Dvorak basically ex,
extends the activity.
He first of all, modulates.
He moves us up a little bit.
You could, you could, you could probably
hear that, we might play it again.
But you hear it happens, it's jubilant.
And then, it actually gets raised again.
And then, we get a little kind of a tag
at the end where there's all this
energy build up.
And as you can see, the whole orchestra
is kind of running, running, and
the rhythm is getting more and
more intense.
And what we have and, and
I think that this concept has
also been presented before.
But, what we get basically
here at the end.
Right after our third
theme zone has happened
is what we like to think of as a coda.
Coda I believe comes from Italian word for
tail, I believe.
And it really does kind of, add just a,
extra space on to our movement.
Or it could happen in a,
in a single contained piece that doesn't
have various movements, at the end.
But anyway, we get a coda that basically
kind of gives us a final hoorah.
In this case, the final hoorah is made
up of snippets of our first theme.
Right and so
you could hear at the end there
[MUSIC].
Right?
And so and then it builds and
it builds and
then at the very end it ends with a bang.
So in this case, our sonata form
then had kind of two additions
to our kind of classic exposition,
development, and recapitulation.
We had a slow introduction
which was never repeated.
And then we have a coda
which also only sounds once.
And so, that's basically in a,
in a nutshell,
a very nice encapsulation of sonata form
operating in some of the traditional ways.
And then, in some of the kind of
added bonus ways and
this is by no means unique to Dvorak.
Haydn, for
instance often had slow introductions to
movements that he wrote in sonata form.
Mozart, Beethoven.
So, this is by no means, something that
is a late 19th century development.
This is, this is something that
composers even in the 18th,
late 18th and early 19th century.
Are already playing with
these kinds of features.
In the way that they explore sonata form.
But I think that this is a really
it's a really neat movement.
Because we can hear a lot of cool themes
that have very distinctive characters.
And we can see how they play up.
So as you can see I've made these
little spirals here in the development.
But really in the spirals
we could have written,
we could have kind of notated things.
Like he's playing with a third them,
playing some of the bits of our first
them, and, of course,
there are also new material.
I don't know.
I'll just write the word new
thrown into the jumble there.
And so, that's kind of the,
that's the point of a development section.
The idea is that it's a,
a meditation, in sense, in a sense,
or, or a kind of rumination on the
material that was given in our exposition.
And of course, out of this Pssst.
The recap comes.
And so, that is basically how
our sonata form is working.
What I'm going to do then is, let's
just play the very end of the recap and
the coda one more time.
So that you,
you can kind of get a sense, once again,
of how that transition works
out of the recap into the coda.
And maybe we'll call it
a class at that point.
So here let me put the bottom here.
Maybe this is a good point.
[MUSIC]
So here we are.
We're kind of at the tail end
of our second theme group.
So you can hear, here we are,
relaxing, relaxing,
[MUSIC]
Sigh, and here's the third.
Here we are.
Music in this jubilant moment here.
[MUSIC]
>> [INAUDIBLE] We're rising.
Here we are now, getting into coda.
We're in coda world now.
Here in coda world we're playing
with aspects of our first theme.
All right.
[INAUDIBLE] this.
[MUSIC]
Momentum is building.
Here we go.
[MUSIC]
And one more time, yep.
It's a very emphatic end to that movement.
And, of course, what follows this movement
probably after a few seconds of break for
a, both conductor and
orchestra, and audience,
to kind of breath and, and have
a moment after that big adrenalin rush.
Was, of course, the second movement,
which starts out with some big,
kind of broad chords in, in the brass.
And, of course, the same melody that you
heard me playing when we started out here.
So I'm going to now,
I'm going to play, again,
that melody from the second movement,
the very famous melody.
I think it also has the nickname.
Going home.
This is what you would hear if you were
at a concert then you were at a symphony.
You would hear that movement,
then you would hear the opening of
the second movement, and then this melody,
which is actually not played by
the violin but by the English horn.
And so I will play this melody and,
bid you adieu for now, but thanks so
much for joining us for office hours.
I hope that was a,
a helpful walk through sonata form.
And I hope that if you liked that piece,
or that movement, i hope that you will go
check out the rest of the symphony and,
many more symphonies by Dvorjak and,
of course, plenty of other
symphonies by many other composers,
both of whom we've spoken
about in this class and
others that we haven't had
the opportunity to, to discuss.
But here we are the,
opening melody of the second
movement of Dvojak's new world symphony.
[MUSIC]