[MUSIC]
All right wasn't that beautiful.
We'll, I'm sad to say this is our
last Office Hour for this class.
But I wanted to share some really cool
stats that you might find interesting
about this course.
So since the intro to classical music has
launched, the lectures for this course
have been viewed over 1.4 million
times and that's pretty impressive.
As for the quizzes 3,
375,000 quizzes have been submitted.
And for the forums,
there have been 8,000 forum posts.
And I think those are pretty
remarkable numbers, and
we're glad you're enjoying the course and
engaging in it as much as you are.
So, with out further ado, let's just get
into some questions that you guys had.
Hi, Craig. Hi, James. >> Hi.
>> Hi, Lois.
Hi, everybody.
>> All right.
So, James,
this question we're going to aim at you.
>> Okay, sure.
>> [LAUGH] So this student asks, at this
point, I'm not sure how much material,
contemporary, classical music will be
included in the upcoming lectures.
So, I want to be sure to get some insight
into this music before the class finishes,
to that end,
I have the following question.
So, this is a four part question, but
I'm going to break it down one-by-one.
>> Okay.
Sure.
>> So the first is, what are the main
trends in contemporary classic, classical
music of the last, say, 25 to 30 years?
>> Oh, that's a good question.
I'm going to start my answer with kind
of a cop-out, which is to say that.
When you spend the time that I'm
spending on a very particular focus for
which for me right now is my dissertation
on the American composer Samuel Barber,
who is kind of a mid 20th century figure,
sometimes you don't always have your head
plugged into the more present day or
even the last couple of decades.
So so I, I'll preface it with that,
and, and apologize that I don't know,
necessarily all of the kind of big
trends that have happened in the last,
you know,
I guess since maybe the 80s or so.
But I can say, broadly speaking,
that over the 20th century we've seen
some very interesting occurrences in,
in, in, art music,
in classical music, which is to say
there was this kind of big bang,
maybe let's call it, a big bang of,
of kind of aesthetic options.
And so
you see composers who have stayed kind of
closer to the path of art music as it
has been given up to the 20th century.
And you start to see composers who,
who go in a totally opposite direction
some of whom completely relinquish,
for example, acoustic instruments and
deal only with electronic sounds and,
and music generated by computers.
And then you see a lot of the in between,
and I think the in between maybe is
where a lot of the music of the last
couple decades has has resided.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Composers who are kind of at home
writing music that uses acoustic
instruments, digital instruments,
digital sounds.
Sometimes they even use recordings,
of things out in the world.
A, a composer might go out and
make a recording of,
like a street noises from a busy city and
then incorporate that into their piece.
So while I can't necessarily
pin down the important trends,
I think maybe what that speaks to is that
there have just been so many trends in,
in every direction in, in the 20th and
into the 21st century.
So.
>> Okay.
Well thank you, we appreciate that answer.
I don't, I don't think it's a cop-out.
[LAUGH].
So the second part of this
person's question is.
Who are the key composers of
this period to take note of?
Say, maybe there's a half dozen or so?
>> Well, let's see here.
Once again this is actually,
this is probably the most dangerous
question that one might get.
[LAUGH].
And and I'm going to say that I am,
I am in no position to declare, you know,
any composers who are the ones to watch or
the ones who are going to make it through,
whatever that means.
If history has taught us
anything it's that it's almost
impossible to do that right now anyhow.
You know,
you think of someone like Bach who,
who very easily could have faded
completely away right after he died.
I mean obviously the cultural differences
and, and, and whatnot are in play.
But I mean if someone like Bach, who has
such a status today could have faded away,
I mean, you know, after 1750 who am I to
say anything about the composers today?
However, I can give you a couple of names
of composers that maybe I've noticed.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Out in the world and, you know,
I, I'm in no way endorsing or
saying that they are the luminaries but,
you know, they're up there, I mean.
John Adams is obviously a big
name in the scene right now, and
Philip Glass there's a Finnish
composer named Einojuhani Rautavaara.
>> Hm.
>> Who has a lot of his music performed
actually the former conductor of
the LA Phil Esa-Pekka Salonen,
is also very a well-respected composer.
Jennifer Higden is actually
an American composer who is,
who is writing a lot of music these days
and, and is getting a lot of performances.
There is a composer actually
from Yale from the he,
he actually was an undergraduate here and
then also got a degree in composition from
the music school who I understand is
doing very well, his name is Timo Andres.
>> Okay.
>> There's another Finnish composer,
I think her last name is Serio.
I'm sorry that my Finnish pronunciation
is probably absolutely terrible but
she is also another prolific composer.
I think she's had some operas produced
possibly even at
the Metropolitan in New York so.
>> Mm-hm.
>> I mean, there are,
there are lots of composers out there are,
our is another big name he's Estonian,
so these composers
are coming from all over the world and
Ton Dun is a Chinese Composer.
>> Okay.
>> So anyway, yeah,
these are just names that I've
kind of seen here and there.
And if you're interested in any of them,
please you know, go out and, and,
find their music and, and
see their performances, and
hear their performances, and, you know,
form an opinion for yourself.
>> That's great.
I mean, it sounds like you rattled off
more than half a dozen.
[LAUGH].
>> Oh.
Maybe, maybe seven.
>> So, that's, that's good news.
[LAUGH] And Craig,
did you have anything to add that, or?
>> No.
After James' fine answer, I,
I wouldn't begin to go anywhere near that.
[LAUGH].
I guess one obvious take away, if you
want to be a great contemporary kentuk,
con, compen, composure,
move to Estonia or Finland.
That would be [LAUGH] that
would be one good thing to do.
The other thought is that we probably,
it probably be 25,
30 years before we have really sense,
fore, before the general populous.
So society has a chance
to evaluate all this, and
it all begins to shake out into some
kind of pecking orders as to, to who,
in retrospect, we thought was really the,
the essential, influential composer.
So it may be too soon.
>> Mm-hm.
>> To really make any definitive de,
determinations.
>> Mm-hm.
Okay.
Fair enough.
All right let's move on to the third part
of this question, this big question,
and the student asks, what are three
pieces of contemporary classical music
that you feel could become staples
of the overall classical repertoire?
Well.
>> You're, you're the 20th century guy,
21st century guy.
>> Yeah.
I don't know.
I think I'm going to, I'm going to
pass on answering that question
by the letter of the,
of the law as it were.
I have no idea what pieces
are going to make it to the canon.
>> Yeah.
>> I would say that once again, I mean
any of the composers that I just named.
I think you, you should check out their
music and kind of, see what you like,
see what's out there.
I mean, there are so
many names that I, I-.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Regret that I haven't mentioned either
because they're not coming to mind, or
just there are too many to name.
But maybe one easy way to kind of,
get your feet wet is to look at if
you live near a major orchestra,
just kind of look at their program for
this season.
Or for last season or for next season.
And see if there are names of
composers who are living or
who might have just recently passed.
And see what they're playing and,
and, and, look it up and,
and hear what they sound like.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And just kind of and
can figure it out for yourself.
Your guess is as good as mine,
to some degree,
what, what pieces of today will,
will kind of live on.
>> Right.
I'm sure that's hard to tell.
Well, last but not least for
this person's questions,
how about some tips on listening to and
appreciating this music,
which many find difficult unlovely,
overtly intellectual, et cetera.
>> Well my first tip would be to go
listen to it a lot, get used to it,
maybe it's it's something like spinach
that you have to become acclimated to it,
to develop a taste for it.
[LAUGH] Well may maybe if
it's Brussels sprouts or
spinach you you don't develop a taste for
it, I'm not really sure.
[LAUGH] But I found that with say
say the music of Arnold Schoenberg.
If I take a piece and play, initially
I sit there playing it, I don't know,
why would I want to do this?
And you play it a couple of times.
Wow, you know, I, I understand this.
I'm getting, kind of getting, you sort
of go off into your own world and that.
Though, that world becomes
a new context for you.
So that would be my recommendation.
If, that if you engage something that
initially seems off-putting, maybe engage
it a lot, so that it becomes part of you
and you're more comfortable with it.
Actually if you stop and think about it,
that's how any sort of creating a
progressive event or happen with society.
The box is here somebody comes along and
moves the box slightly, everybody
initially objects then everybody climbs
in the box and we're in a new place.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And then somebody else comes along with
a new idea we all have
to get used to that, so
by listening to something frequently
they were just getting used to it.
Okay.
I can appreciate that, James.
>> Yeah.
>> I think that in addition
to everything Craig said,
my word of advice would be to think also,
about the context, and, and
kind of, the terms of the piece.
I'll give you an example
of what I mean here.
So let's run with Schaumburg,
for instance.
At first a lot of his music can
certainly sound challenging,
discordant, and
incomprehensible, whatever.
You can append whatever
adjective you'd like.
However, if you think
about it as being part
of a dialog with other
composers out there, and
part of a dialog with the music
that he kind of inherited.
>> From centuries before, or even decades
before, or even a couple years before.
You think about it as a relationship
between where he's seeing himself coming
from, and then you start to see
what he's trying to challenge.
It's it could be that way with modern art
as well, I mean sometimes I think to,
especially when I was younger, I think to
myself if I go to a modern art museum and
think I could have done that, but
that's not the point to some degree.
It's not or at least in, in visual
art I don't think it's necessarily
the point that you could have done it.
It's, it's about the, the frame of
reference or what, what are the terms that
that, what are the terms that define
what is, what the artwork is doing for
itself or for
its relationship with other works.
So with Shernburg if the music jumps
in weird ways and sounds wacky or
if the chords don't sound very good.
Good, you kind of have to also think about
what is Schoenberg trying to play with?
Like, i, i, if we're used to a nice
melody that just goes [SOUND] and
Schoenberg goes [SOUND] right?
The idea then is like, he's kind of
putting you in a position to, to hear that
rhythm, more traditional or kind of
beautiful music as as the background.
>> Okay.
>> It sits in, in dialog with it.
And so
maybe that's a way to kind of understand
where this music is positioning
itself with respect to other music.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
Good, very good point.
Very good point.
>> Yeah.
All right, well,
we have some questions here.
Actually, a very interesting questions,
question.
This person says, greetings Craig.
I am an American living in China.
I learn to read music, musical notes
as letters, A, B, C et cetera.
My wife is Chinese and
learned doe, re, me et cetera.
We both play violin, to a certain extent.
I've been playing longer, and
I try to each her new music, but
it is all a bit confusing,
especially sharps and flats.
Do you have any advice for her?
>> Advice?
No other than to,
to just get used to it [LAUGH]
because it's been around a long time.
That particular dichotomy and
this used to be something I would teach.
I think James was actually in the course
at one point, our medieval T&A class where
we, we dealt with all of these, all of
these issues of music theory goes back.
It's more than a 1,000 years old.
Initially around the year 1000,
we had this system of-
[MUSIC]
A, B, C, D, E, F, G and so on.
Then somebody discovered well,
that's confusing because at two spots,
you have these half steps.
I can't, how am I supposed to know the
difference, distance between A and B on,
on the open keyboard here is
only a half step, and but
the difference between C and
D is a whole step.
It's an anomaly.
So some clever figure, his name was Guido
Avaretto, comes along and says, well,
let's isolate this just one half step.
And we'll go do, or, ut, re, mi,
fa, so, la, and that was it.
He had a six six note in effect scale.
And those two competed.
For about 500 years until
the 17th century when the A,
B, C, D, E, F, began to win out, but
there was still a vestige in some
educational systems of that root, or
do, ra, me, fa, so, la and eventually
that was filled out to ti and do again.
So it really doesn't matter what
system that you, that you use.
That each is equally effective.
It's just that we have had, as a, and
again, another anomaly in western music,
two systems that's been going on for
1,000 years.
>> Mm-hm.
Okay.
Do you have anything to add, James?
>> Well, I mean, The question does
relate to playing the violin.
>> Yeah.
>> And
I'm trying to think here about useful ways
to kind of,
wed those two kind of, systems.
I mean, I guess, part of the problem I
guess, entails whether you're also trying
to deal with reading music
on the printed page.
Because when, when we are talking
about playing music from the score
at that point we are somewhat
dealing with fixed pitches
as they correlate to spots on the violin,
right.
So you could think in terms of do re mi.
But as far as the violin is concerned,
and man,
you now, many other instruments also do
this, there's going to be a specific point
on a string that corresponds to
a specific note on the page.
And so, I guess my recommendations would
be that, if you can find a way for
the two of you to, to kind of find the
common ground to have you're individual
knowledge set, skill sets to somehow also
linked to what you're seeing on the page.
That can probably help translate
that to the violin, but baring that,
you may have to find a violin teacher
who is who kind of specializes,
who specializes in this
kind of instruction.
So.
>> Okay.
Well, thank you.
>> Good luck.
>> [LAUGH] Hope that was helpful.
>> Don't fight over it.
[LAUGH].
>> Okay.
So our next question okay.
This is, I'm just going to give
you a little bit of context to
why this person is asking this question.
But he says, in the beginning of the
course, Professor Wright told us that we
would talk more about the emotions
that music can provoke.
I, myself, am a very sensitive person,
regarding music.
So I was really looking
forward to this one.
I really would like to learn,
about what happens in the brain,
while listening to music.
What makes the music touch the soul and
what doesn't?
Has any scientific research
been done about this theme?
And I'm sure someone in recent history,
has asked the same scientific question
before, but this person is hoping
you can address it in office hours.
>> Well it's a very interesting question.
And up until oh, I would guess,
maybe 20 years ago
there wasn't too much that one could
do with this, this type of question.
Said, oh, that's a heartfelt expression or
you, you've touched my heartstrings.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Well, of course.
Has nothing to do with
the heart whatsoever.
[LAUGH] It has everything to do with
your brain, and your cortex, and
the various associative linkages
that you make in the brain, and
particularly your limbic system.
Which is a, a part of the,
of the brain that
is particularly powerful when things
such as emotions and feeling and
memory begin to fire off and
begin to get in- integrated.
Creativity is, is,
is something that transpires, and
is generated into some measure in another
part of the brain, in, in the what?
Dorsolateral prefrontal
cortex I think the-.
>> Okay.
>> Is the specific term for that.
But if you're interested in this topic,
what I recommend.
And actually I went online and, and
posted an answer to this already.
>> Oh, okay.
>> Because I needed to give
specific information here.
I peaked ahead to see what
the questions might be there is a good,
very good article by Ann Blood,
and Robert Zatori.
She teaches at Harvard.
He teaches at the University of Maguil.
And it's published in
a national Academy of Science.
This proceedings of
the National Academy of Science 2001,
I think,
where they take you all through this.
It takes a fair degree of experience
understanding all the terms
of the parts of the brain.
And, what these various symbols mean,
and positions within the brain.
But, the upshot of it is,
that they, they track blood flow.
>> Hm.
>> As we experience music now with neuro
imaging, PET scans FMRIs,
that sort of thing, even EEGs.
It's possible to see
what the brain is doing.
And to watch the brain fire off
as we experience these emotion,
emotions, and watch blood flow change
in particular parts of these organs.
As we do so and that's,
that's fascinating, fascinating to see.
Oddly enough, now for
the first time in human history in about
the last 20 years with, with neural
imaging, is it possible to do that.
That's a kind of an intellectual
explanation for all of this.
It's not very [LAUGH] ironically, it's not
very satisfying emotionally it's taking it
out of out of the realm realm of feeling
and passion, and into the maybe part of
the analytical part of the brain, we're
going back to the frontal cortex now.
With with the issue of
thinking about the brain.
So we have thinking, we have feeling.
And feeling may be again,
tied up with the, the limbic system.
But we thought a and and I believe that,
that question even more further
with this question since every time
his wife listened to a particular
piece she would start to cry.
In interesting, interesting so
again we're talking about this and
the reason we had this
particular music teamed up here,
is that we've chosen
a piece that we both like.
>> Mm-hm.
>> I like it for reasons of memory and
I've always thought that memory and
emotions are, are deeply.
In twine because this takes me back
to practicing with my two children.
Not two children, I have four children but
the [LAUGH] the last two.
[LAUGH] One was a violinist,
one was a cellist.
So I worked through this piece with,
with both of them.
It was originally written for a violin.
James, do you want to say a word.
This is a piece by Massenet,
that we both like very much.
>> Right, sure.
>> Do you want to say a word about it?
>> It's, yeah, it is a piece by
the French composer Jules Massenet.
It, it is it's called the Meditation.
It's from one of his operas called Thai's.
It's I don't think
there's much else to say.
>> Well some of the cool,
some of the cool, why is it,
why is it a really cool piece?
Well we get these really
lush harmonic movements.
[MUSIC]
So really sort of great chords and then.
I, these moments in which music is up on
a high point, and we've reached the peak.
And now we're coming off it.
We begin to, to relax.
And it's oftentimes having to
do with the very powerful, and
secure harmonic patterns
underneath as the line unfolds-
[MUSIC]
In a sequence, could be a rhythmic
sequence, a melodic sequence it depends.
We get the harmony plus kind of a
relaxation of the emotions at that point,
maybe James you want to play off of that.
[MUSIC]
>> Sure.
>> That, that particular spot, are you,
you, you know, just play your line there.
>> Well yeah.
[CROSSTALK] We'll, we'll get to it but I,
I think I agree that part of
the effect of the piece comes
from the way that the phrase works,
or the phrasings work.
Which is that there's, for,
for the first part it,
there's kind of a constant Kind of climb,
but it doesn't climb very quickly.
Kind of climbs a little bit, back down.
>> Mm-hm.
Mm-hm.
>> Climb a little more, back down.
And then finally we get to
kind of the climactic-.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Part of the phrase where it really hits
the highest note, and then as Craig was
saying, now then we immediately begin
another sequence, but it's a descending
sequence where you, it's going down, and
down a little more, and
then down a little more.
So you cn kind of feel the kind of ebb and
flow of intensity.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Intensity.
And so
I think that that's what part of what
makes this an effective piece of music.
But I think both Craig and
I being on the artistic side of the-.
Scholarly enterprise, I think we.
>> We're in the right side of the.
>> Yeah, we, we I think some of
this stuff is, can be describing,
can be explained, but so much of it is
also just feel, na, natural in a sense.
>> Okay.
>> So where are we going to start?
We can, we probably don't have time for
the whole piece you,
you want to just take it or-
[MUSIC]
Should we climb up to that?
You want-
[MUSIC]
>> [MUSIC]
>> You want to
[MUSIC]
You want to take it up 40, my 40.
>> Yeah is that right there?
>> Yeah it's an F sharp.
>> Sure, sure, let's do that.
>> So this is coming from us
out to you and your enigma.
>> All right [LAUGH].
>> Whoever asked that question.
>> All right, here we go.
>> Amygdala, Amygdala.
Here we go.
>> Where should we go to?
Sorry.
>> And then I'll take it all
the way to the end, maybe.
>> Oh, okay.
Sure.
Okay.
>> We'll see.
[MUSIC]
Beautiful.
>> Yeah, that was fun.
Oh.
>> He's good.
[LAUGH]
>> You both are good.
>> He should cover me more often.
[LAUGH].
>> You need to practice more.
That's how I get good.
[LAUGH]
>> Well that was, that was great.
>> He should cover me more often.
[LAUGH].
>> All right.
So, I guess we should move
to the next question.
>> Sure.
>> And this question is asking can you
explain the difference between the most
basic musical terms you use throughout
the course, tune, theme, melody,
motif, are they synonyms, or?
>> That's good, that's a good question.
>> Mm-hm.
>> I think sometimes we
tend to use those terms.
Somewhat loosely, and
somewhat interchangeably,
but some of them are also separate.
So let's start with tune,
tune is a very informal term.
We will often use that to loosely describe
any sort of, recognizable melody.
[MUSIC]
Exactly.
Melody I think is,
is a mor, more conformal at least
a little bit more formal term.
Which really does tend to be used for
a musical idea that's
somewhat self enclosed.
>> Okay.
>> So, for instance,
if I were to hum something like bah,
dah, dah, dah, dah.
Like that.
>> Mm-hm.
>> We probably wouldn't call
that a melody.
I mean, it is self enclosed in that it's,
you know, it's right there, bah, dah,
dah, dah, dah.
But usually we tend to give melody
a little bit more of an expansive kind of
definition.
[MUSIC]
Yeah, exactly.
>> Okay.
>> Maybe one way of looking at it would be
a melody could be somewhat
akin to like a sentence.
>> Okay.
>> Like you'll kind of go,
a complete idea it doesn't necessarily
always have to map onto that.
It doesn't necessarily always
have a very strict end.
>> Mm-hm.
>> But usually has this kind of
self contained quality to it.
>> Okay.
>> And a theme is usually somewhat
of a similar type of term.
If you happen to watch the other video
that I made about new world symphony,
the first movement, you'll see that
there's some discussion about theme,
and some of the qualities
that it might have, and
how it's not necessarily always again
it's a totally encapsulated idea.
Sometimes it can start like a theme in,
you know, a,
a theme can start and
it might kind of trail off and keep going.
>> Mm-hm.
>> But the idea is that,
that it's still a kind of a parsable idea.
>> Okay.
>> And but on the other had, a,
a motif is a very different thing
[MUSIC]
Exactly, a motif is usually,
a shorter idea, and,
and it is not necessarily
meant to convey the same
kind of musical effect that a theme or
a melody might do.
Instead, it's more of a kind of a,
a piece, or building block.
>> Okay.
>> And it's often used,
kind of more frequently,
and sometimes used as a,
again, kind of as a building block,
a Lego for instance, for, for a piece.
So you might have in a piece
that has a melody and
then has other things, might also have
mot, motif run, running through it.
So the Beethoven five is a great one,
idea, the pa, pa, paa.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And, and that as a rhythmic motif, pa,
pa, pa.
Persistent, not only in
that first movement, but
across the different movements.
That's actually one of the ways composers
can give some sense of relationship
across movements within an entire work,
would be it a symphony or a concerto.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So that's a great question and
in this case we can kind of put theme and
melody maybe together.
And then in a separate category is motif.
>> Okay.
>> Tune is kind of on its
own as an informal term,
although it's probably more close to
theme and melody than it is to motif.
>> Okay, cool.
Hm, I think that's
a very good explanation.
An apology, I mispronounced motif.
>> We should craft a quiz
question along those lines.
>> Yeah.
>> Well the motif.
>> [LAUGH].
[LAUGH] So our next question.
Oh, this is a good one.
So if we're to take away one,
maybe two or three, things,
most important things from this course,
what would, what would they be?
What would that be?
>> Oh, wow.
>> [LAUGH].
>> That is a good question.
Should I take this one Greg?
>> We have taped, we have three?
>> Between one and three.
>> Yes.
>> What, one and three.
Well I'll do.
>> This person really wants three.
[LAUGH]
>> Wants three.
No more, no less.
I could do, let me do, part a and part b.
One thing well lots of
things you could say.
I hope that they had learned
from this experience that music
doesn't exist in a closed room or
in a box or in isolation.
And what we try to do in this
course is get it out there and
show people that it relates to
literature it relates to poetry, and
particularly the visual arts and
that you can understand music.
Sometimes better if you
understand the visual arts.
When I go to an art gallery,
I'm spending spend a lot of my time
thinking about musical analogies.
And when I go to a concert sometimes
I'm thinking about art that might be
playing out some thing that I've
seen recently in an art gallery.
So get out there, enjoy things and
think about your music,
think of it in connection with other
types of intellectual pursuits.
>> Okay.
>> Mm.
>> Very well said.
>> I think I I might build off of that and
say that one thing that I would
hope that we can all take away from this
course or, you know, any study of music,
is that one, there is always a larger
context not just other arts,
but also history the history of ideas,
history of culture.
And uh,many of those things get built
in to the music either directly or
indirectly depending on what
the composer is up to and
also depending on how we as listeners and
receivers our,
our position in our own time.
>> Mm-hm.
>> I mean,
we can learn a lot about the music and
we can learn a lot about its context but
to some degree some of that legwork also
comes from us and what we bring to it.
Think is an interesting or hopefully
useful take away from this course would
be the idea that this music and
a lot of music really,
not just not just the music we were
able to talk about in this course.
But but so much music out there is so
rewarding when you revisit it and
when you dedicate a lot of time and
energy to getting to know it.
So much of what we've done in this course
obviously takes place within a video
lecture but it can be done on your own and
repeatedly with all of
the music you listen to.
Music can, can be enjoyed on an emotional
level, without any kind of thought or
whatnot, you can kind of just
enjoy as it passes through you.
>> Mm-hm.
>> But it can also be extremely rewarding
if you come back to it again and again,
with different mindsets.
You come back with the idea that you to
parse it and you want to see what's it's
up to some degree or, or come back to it
again and try to figure out what it's
form is or come back to it again and
see how much you can remember of it.
Or how much you might try to hear
from different lines rather than just
the melodic line.
So I think that it, one of the things
that I, at least, find very rewarding,
is that so much of this music.
And again, and other repertoires
out there are so fulfilling and
are so
rewarding with repeated interaction.
>> Okay.
Great, wonderful.
Now do you want to add one more or
just leave at that?
>> One addendum to that.
Within the last 24 hours, one,
i was driving away from a gymnasium.
>> Mm.
>> If you look at me,
you wouldn't believe I'd
actually go to a gymnasium.
[LAUGH].
But I,
I've been known to go to a gymnasium.
And I was listening to the radio, and
there was this beautiful
piece by Otorina Raspini.
>> Mm.
>> And wow, I'd never heard that before,
it was called Autumnal Poem.
I've never heard the piece but, so
here's this vast repertoire
of music that's out there.
And then to, to reinforce, reiterate what,
what James was saying, then earlier
about oh, oh, about three, four,
three hours ago, I was there at my desk
and I was listening to a piece of music,
I wanted to find a piece of music from
the Middle Ages, needn't say why.
I started listening to this piece of music
and I hadn't heard it in a long time.
Now, I wasn't there for
the premier because, old as I may be,
I'm not 600 years old.
[LAUGH].
So, this was from about 1420, 1420.
And it was stunningly beautiful.
Now I'd heard this piece before,
and what this says to me is,
is the change is absolutely right here.
One of the great beauties of music and
art, generally, is we never get tired of
it, if you put it aside, you can come
back to it, and it seems just as fresh,
just as fresh now, as it did
the first time you encountered it.
Maybe it's like, like love, who knows?
>> Mm.
>> [LAUGH] But, but
there is an element to that.
The piece was the requiem
mass by Johannes Ochachum.
It's beautiful, go listen to it.
All right.
Okay.
Now, we have our last question for
our last office hour.
Very sad.
When will this course be repeated?
[LAUGH].
>> When will this course be repeated?
>> Yes.
>> That's an interesting question,
I don't think we're sure.
We were talking with our
friends here our broadcast
team here before we were coming in and
it may repe, be repeated as early as.
Six to eight weeks from
now it may be placed
on what Coursera is calling the on,
on-demand platform.
We would have to know.
There's things that we probably some
things we could do a little bit better.
We, we all can always do better,
so we might try to improve things.
We'll take it down for two months and then
put it back up either in a discrete time
format, or put it up again OnDemand so
that anybody, anywhere around the world,
at any time can come and
e,e,enjoy and engage this.
So, the, the wonderful thing about this
experiment with our broadcast team and
all has been that we don't always
know exactly what we're doing or
where we're going with this.
And that's part of the excitement and
part of,
part of the fun,
we'll see how it plays out.
The one thing we learned is,
judging from these numbers that Melissa
articulated at the beginning of our
gathering here, judging from these numbers
this is a powerful, powerful medium.
I had no idea that this
could be what it is.
People all around the world,
thousands of them,
engaging in an artistic or
intellectual project.
And I have learned an enormous amount
from reading what our learners are,
are sending me.
They're out there, again,
putting together learning groups
gathering discussion forums where
they're all learning together, and
they're solving everyone else's problems,
or answering everyone else's questions.
That, I think, you asked,
what's the big takeaway, here?
Give us one of three takeaways.
>> Mm-hm.
>> The the really big take away maybe the
elephant in the room here is that as a,
as a program, as an initiative this is
where in my opinion where the future lies.
>> Yeah, for sure.
All right well I think I can speak for
everyone here at the broadcast center and
in the office of digital dissemination
that we had a lot of fun,
putting this course together.
And thank you James, and
thank you Craig for being a part of it.
>> Thank you Melissa.
And thank you everyone out there.
We really enjoyed getting to
know you through Coursera.
>> And thanks to our team.
>> Yeah, thank you to the team for sure.
>> All right, shall we play a s,
play a sad tune for.
[LAUGH].
Perfect.
>> There's our Chopin.
[MUSIC]
>> Isn't it his birthday or something.
I got an announcement
about that the other day.
>> Sorry, I don't know Chopin's birthday.
>> No.
[MUSIC]
We can't end in a minor key, right?
[LAUGH].
[MUSIC]